{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "after-cataract-surgery-i-have-regained-my-balance-", "title": "After cataract surgery I have regained my balance? Why?", "question": "After cataract surgery I have regained my balance? Why?", "answer": "I need to have more information about your balance issues and the quality of your vision prior to the cataract surgery to be more certain. First, most people with vision problems do not have a great deal of problems with balance. Blind people do not fall over or have severe balance issues. It is possible that the development of a fairly thick cataract in a short period of time could make adaptation difficult and result in balance issues which would resolve with the removal of the cataract. Congratulations on your good vision and the return of your balance.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "APR 19, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/after-cataract-surgery-i-have-regained-my-balance-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\after-cataract-surgery-i-have-regained-my-balance-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "am-i-good-candidate-cataract-surgery-with-granulom", "title": "Am I a good candidate for cataract surgery with granulomatosis?", "question": "I am in remission from an autoimmune disease called granulomatosis with polyangiitis (causes inflammation of the blood vessels in the kidneys and other organs). I had a kidney transplant and had a heart valve replacement with a pacemaker. I recently found that I have cataracts forming in both eyes from prednisone (steroid) use . Will I be considered for surgery?", "answer": "You are absolutely a good candidate for cataract surgery and this type of cataract is often easier to remove. Your disease should not make the surgery any more difficult.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 13, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/am-i-good-candidate-cataract-surgery-with-granulom", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\am-i-good-candidate-cataract-surgery-with-granulom.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-cataracts-worsening-my-dizziness-from-meniere-", "title": "Are cataracts worsening my dizziness from Meniere’s disease?", "question": "I have Meniere’s disease (an ear condition that can cause vertigo/dizziness) and am getting cataracts . My dizziness is much worse even though I am taking medication for it. Could this be caused by the cataracts?", "answer": "It is very unusual for any eye problem to aggravate dizziness. I suppose if one had extremely severe cataracts it may increase a sense of disorientation that may make dizziness feel worse. However, I don’t think that cataract surgery will relieve your symptoms from Meniere’s disease.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 25, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-cataracts-worsening-my-dizziness-from-meniere-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-cataracts-worsening-my-dizziness-from-meniere-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-eye-drops-always-necessary-before-cataract-sur", "title": "Are eye drops always necessary before cataract surgery?", "question": "Are eye drops always necessary before cataract surgery ? I did not receive instructions or prescriptions from my doctor about pre-surgery eye drops.", "answer": "No, they are not always necessary. Many ophthalmologists prescribe them routinely, but others do not use them. If you did not receive instructions, you should clarify this with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "MAR 15, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-eye-drops-always-necessary-before-cataract-sur", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-eye-drops-always-necessary-before-cataract-sur.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-flashes-of-light-linked-to-my-cataract", "title": "Are flashes of light linked to my cataract?", "question": "I sometimes blink hard when I wake up. When I do, I often see a single flash of white, which is more or less in the shape of a little jellyfish or a firework . It happens only one time. I can't replicate it by blinking hard again. I was recently diagnosed with the beginnings of a cataract in my left eye. I'm 65, good health, and no blood pressure issues. My cataract is not ready for surgery yet . Is there a connection with the cataract?", "answer": "No, there is no connection to the cataract. Blinking hard can cause an entopic phenomenon (visual effect coming from within the eye itself). This can move the vitreous (jelly-like substance that fills the middle of the eye) around, which in turn can stimulate the retina into producing a false flash of light. This is nothing to be concerned about unless you develop many floaters and see continued spontaneous flashes of light .", "answer_links": [{"text": "vitreous (jelly-like substance that fills the middle of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/vitreous"}, {"text": "the retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "This is nothing to be concerned about unless you develop many floaters and see continued spontaneous flashes of light", "url": "https://www.aao.org/ask-ophthalmologist-q/when-are-floaters-problem"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "DEC 08, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-flashes-of-light-linked-to-my-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-flashes-of-light-linked-to-my-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-multifocal-lenses-successful-after-lasik", "title": "How successful are multifocal lenses in those who have had LASIK?", "question": "How successful are multifocal lenses in those who have had LASIK?", "answer": "This really depends on the amount of LASIK you had . Extended depth-of-focus lenses or the Light Adjustable Lens may be better choices. Ask your surgeon for recommendations taking into account your previous LASIK surgery as well as your specific visual goals.", "answer_links": [{"text": "This really depends on the amount of LASIK you had", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 26, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "LASIK and Laser Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-multifocal-lenses-successful-after-lasik", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-multifocal-lenses-successful-after-lasik.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-penicillin-clindamycin-used-in-antibiotic-eye-", "title": "Are penicillin and clindamycin used in the antibiotic eye drops prescribed after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am allergic to penicillin and clindamycin. Are either of these used in the antibiotic eye drops prescribed after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "It is quite unlikely that those antibiotics would be prescribed after surgery. But it's always important to remind your medical care team of your allergies.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "APR 21, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-penicillin-clindamycin-used-in-antibiotic-eye-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-penicillin-clindamycin-used-in-antibiotic-eye-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-there-any-extra-concerns-cataract-operation-of", "title": "Are there any extra concerns for a cataract operation of the \"good eye\" from a person with amblyopia?", "question": "Are there any extra concerns for a cataract operation of the \"good eye\" from a person with amblyopia? (extra possible complications, choice of lens, outcome, etc.)", "answer": "The first and foremost concern is safety. Cataract surgery is about 98% (or more) safe and effective. But complications can and do occur. These can be minimal to severe, with blindness occurring in less than one in ten thousand cataract surgeries. If severe complications occur in a one-eyed patient it can be terrible.\n\nIn my career, I performed cataract surgery on hundreds of patients with severe problems in the other eye such as amblyopia (poor vision in an eye that did not develop normal sight during early childhood) , advanced macular disease and even glass eyes. I thank the lord that all of them went well and all of these patients were happy with their vision after surgery. I usually told these patients much of what I have just told you and more. I would tell them I would not do cataract surgery on their only good eye until they almost grabbed me by the shirt and tie and told me that I must do the surgery. In other words, it’s best to wait to do surgery until it is interfering in a major way with your life since the risk to your good eye is real, even though low.\n\nIt's important to ask your surgeon about patching the operated eye after cataract surgery. Most of us would not use a patch on any patient after cataract surgery, but you need to check on this. Additionally, vision after cataract surgery can be blurry for a few hours to a few days. You would do well to have a loved one or friend live with you during your first few days after surgery. Consider preparing and freezing the meals you will need for a few days after surgery. You will also need someone to drive you to and from your ophthalmologist for your first, and possibly second, post op follow-up exams until your ophthalmologist tells you it is OK for you to drive. Be certain to fully understand all of your after-surgery instructions, do’s and don’ts, etc. before the procedure. Finally, you reference choice of the intraocular lens: this requires consultation with your ophthalmologist and some self-education on your part. I believe that all of the IOL options are good and offer choices of convenience relative to near, intermediate and distance vision with or without eyeglasses. These options are too lengthy for this discussion.\n\nI understand what you are going through and I sincerely wish you the very best of luck, and in my heart, I know you will love your new vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "amblyopia (poor vision in an eye that did not develop normal sight during early childhood)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amblyopia-lazy-eye"}, {"text": "IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "JUL 13, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-there-any-extra-concerns-cataract-operation-of", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-there-any-extra-concerns-cataract-operation-of.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-there-drops-other-than-gatiquin-p-my-wife-shou", "title": "Are there drops other than Gatiquin P my wife should use after her cataract surgery?", "question": "My wife is using Gatiquin P eye drops after cataract surgery for the last 5-6 years. Is this OK or are there other drops she should use regularly? Her eyes sometimes tear and can be a little painful.", "answer": "Gataquin is an antibiotic/steroid combination drop that should not be used long-term unless there is a specific reason. In addition, an ophthalmologist should be monitoring her eye pressure regularly. Ask her ophthalmologist if there are other drops they recommend to treat her symptoms.", "answer_links": [{"text": "eye pressure", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 12, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-there-drops-other-than-gatiquin-p-my-wife-shou", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-there-drops-other-than-gatiquin-p-my-wife-shou.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "are-there-recent-results-of-success-with-tecnis-sy", "title": "Are there recent results of success with Tecnis Symfony in post-LASIK patients?", "question": "Are there recent results of success with Tecnis Symfony in post-LASIK patients? I had LASIK 20 years ago and have my pre- and post-vision results/eye measurements. I have some astigmatism , but not severe. I am ready for cataract surgery but do not want to settle for a monofocal lens . Are there advanced procedures now available to help determine selection and placement of the latest Tecnis Symfony multifocal lenses in post-LASIK patients?", "answer": "Yes, Symfony can be placed in someone who has had LASIK in the past but is not embraced by all surgeons. There are pre-op measurements such as aberration values that can help determine if you are a good candidate as well. Discuss pros and cons with your surgeon.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 09, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/are-there-recent-results-of-success-with-tecnis-sy", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\are-there-recent-results-of-success-with-tecnis-sy.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "better-vision-reading-glasses-after-cataract-surg", "title": "Why do my reading glasses improve blurry reading and distance vision after cataract surgery?", "question": "It has been two weeks since I had cataract surgery on my left eye. I still have blurred vision. However, if I put on reading glasses of power 1.5, I can see perfect for both reading and distance. Why?", "answer": "It is not unusual for vision to fluctuate after cataract surgery. It is also possible to have some degree of farsightedness or nearsightedness and/or astigmatism after cataract surgery. This will also fluctuate and you may not have a final stable refraction (prescription) until after four weeks or more.", "answer_links": [{"text": "farsightedness", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/hyperopia-farsightedness"}, {"text": "nearsightedness", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 27, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/better-vision-reading-glasses-after-cataract-surg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\better-vision-reading-glasses-after-cataract-surg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "both-standard-iol-and-light-adjustable-lens", "title": "Would a standard IOL in one eye and a light adjustable lens in the other work?", "question": "Would a standard IOL in one eye and a light adjustable lens in the other work?", "answer": "Yes, this could work. Depending upon your needs, if you want the clearest distance vision the light adjustable lens (LAL) should go into the dominant eye with the goal of best distance vision. The LAL allows us to change the final power of the lens after surgery to fine tune your result.\n\nA standard, non-adjustable lens works very well and delivers great results, but it does not allow for adjustments after cataract surgery in a simple way like the LAL. It is very likely that you will still be satisfied with both eyes having an LAL in one and a standard, monofocal lens in the other.", "answer_links": [{"text": "dominant eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-dominance"}, {"text": "after cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 03, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/both-standard-iol-and-light-adjustable-lens", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\both-standard-iol-and-light-adjustable-lens.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-all-lens-implants-be-removed-replaced-are-ther", "title": "Can all lens implants be removed and replaced or are there some types that cannot?", "question": "Can all lens implants be removed and replaced or are there some types that cannot?", "answer": "Most, but not all, intraocular lens implants can be removed and replaced if it is medically necessary. Most insurances will only cover the cost of such an exchange in the event of a very compelling medical or optical necessity, not for convenience or small improvement in sharpness of focus. Every operation has risks and an implant exchange can be somewhat more risky if the implant is scarred into place, has had a YAG laser treatment, or some other concerns. I suggest you proceed only with the greatest of thought and consultation with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens implants", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "DEC 22, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-all-lens-implants-be-removed-replaced-are-ther", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-all-lens-implants-be-removed-replaced-are-ther.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-cause-monocular-diplopia", "title": "Can a cataract cause monocular diplopia?", "question": "Can a cataract cause monocular diplopia? I have monocular diplopia, separately, in both eyes. The separation of the main and ghost images varies. Some days the images are very close together and superimposed vertically, but on other days the separation is very wide.", "answer": "Monocular diplopia is seeing two images (either separate or overlapping or with ghosting or shadowing) from one eye with the other eye covered. In your case, you state that you have this in both eyes, meaning that with each eye covered the uncovered eye is having these symptoms. Cataracts can definitely cause this. As can corneal disease, severe dry eye and many other conditions.\n\nThe variations that you notice may be a result of different types and sources of light as well as background illumination. It may also be due to differences in the corneal surface that are variable such as a poor quality tear film as in dry eyes. This symptom need to be addressed during a comprehensive eye exam by an ophthalmologist to determine the cause and make a plan for treatment.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Monocular diplopia is seeing two images", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/symptoms/double-vision-2"}, {"text": "severe dry eye", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}, {"text": "poor quality tear film", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/anatomy/tear-film-3"}, {"text": "comprehensive eye exam by an ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "FEB 03, 2021", "categories": ["Double Vision", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-cause-monocular-diplopia", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-cause-monocular-diplopia.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-affect-depth-perception-video", "title": "Can cataract surgery affect depth perception? - Video Answer", "question": "Can cataract surgery affect depth perception ?", "answer": "It is common for there to be some change in depth perception after cataract surgery—especially in the time after the first eye is operated on and before the second one is done. The greater the difference in vision between the two eyes, the more likely it is that you'll notice a change in depth perception. G. Atma Vemulakonda, MD, discusses some of the possible outcomes of cataract surgery .", "answer_links": [{"text": "depth perception", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/depth-perception"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "G Atma Vemulakonda, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/4a89bb0e-cdeb-467c-ad06-ad413ba88291", "answered_at": "MAY 15, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-affect-depth-perception-video", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-affect-depth-perception-video.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-be-done-early", "title": "Can cataract surgery be done before the cataract is ripe?", "question": "I had radial keratotomy surgery (or RK, a surgery that at one time was used to correct nearsightedness ) in 1988. My eyes have been forming cataracts for the past five years, but my last exam said it might be another five to ten years before they are \"ripe.\" My vision cannot be corrected beyond 20/40 and 20/50 due to the RK. I see different shades of colors, and the worst cataract eye gives things a yellow appearance. Can cataract surgery be done before the cataract is ripe? I’m hoping the cataract replacement lens would also improve my vision. Would it?", "answer": "No modern-day eye surgeon I know uses the term ripe anymore—we of course are not talking about fruit. Today, if the vision is compromised by the cataract, it may be time to remove it, particularly since you are noting color changes. There is no way to know how much improvement you will have after surgery without a proper exam. There are surgeons who are more comfortable operating on post RK eyes and I would try to seek one out.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 23, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-be-done-early", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-be-done-early.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-be-done-without-sedation", "title": "Can cataract surgery be done without sedation?", "question": "My wife cannot have any sedation. Can she have cataract surgery without sedation? She has had other eye procedures performed with only local anesthesia.", "answer": "Cataract surgery is usually done with local/topical (eye drops) anesthesia. She may have some slight discomfort at the beginning of the surgery, but many patients decide to have no intravenous (given into the vein) sedating medications.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUL 10, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-be-done-without-sedation", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-be-done-without-sedation.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-cause-bleeding-in-my-good-eye", "title": "Can cataract surgery cause bleeding in my good eye and lead to vision loss?", "question": "I have wet AMD (abnormal growth of blood vessels in the back of the eye) in my left eye and it was treated with laser surgery. I still lost most of my central vision in that eye. I now have cataract in my right eye that is rapidly progressing. I will be having surgery but still have four weeks to wait for the surgery consultation. I know that cataract surgery is common and considered very safe. Yet I have fears as I really only have one good eye. I also am very hard of hearing and have been told I will eventually be totally deaf. So you can see that my vision is very important to me. I know I need to have the surgery regardless of risk but what are the risks if any that can occur to the retina ? Is there any way that the surgery could result in bleeding on the macula and trigger vision loss?", "answer": "This is a tough situation in that the biggest risk of getting bleeding from macular degeneration (wet AMD) is having wet AMD in the opposite eye. So, you are at risk to get this in the \"good\" eye no matter which way you go. You should be on ocular vitamins for AMD and should get a retina exam before the cataract evaluation if one has not been performed recently. Progression to wet AMD can certainly happen after cataract surgery but it can equally happen in eyes with a cataract as well. If the cataract surgeon and retina specialist agree you need the cataract removed, I would likely follow their suggestions. Make sure you understand exactly what your risk is during your pre-operative visits.", "answer_links": [{"text": "ocular vitamins for AMD", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amd-treatment"}], "answered_by": "William Barry Lee, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6e7ea7d6-fac3-4515-90c3-249b40819804", "answered_at": "APR 14, 2018", "categories": ["Macular Degeneration", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-cause-bleeding-in-my-good-eye", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-cause-bleeding-in-my-good-eye.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-improve-my-high-myopia", "title": "Can cataract surgery improve my high myopia?", "question": "I have a high index refractive error (-11 and -9). Can cataract surgery improve my vision?", "answer": "First, I assume by \"high index\" you mean you are very nearsighted (myopic) , with a prescription of -11.00 in one eye and -9.00 in the other eye. By replacing your natural lens with an artificial one (an intraocular lens or IOL) during cataract surgery , your prescription can be changed however you wish.\n\nSome “high myopes”—or those who are very nearsighted--choose to stay nearsighted, but less so. For example, changing your prescription from -11.00 to -3.00. This means you would still need glasses and/or contact lenses to see at a distance but would not have to hold objects so close to your face to be in focus for reading. Others choose to end up with good distance vision without glasses or contact lenses, but may then need reading glasses to see up close.\n\nEither way, the quality of your vision should be better as the cloudy lens (cataract) will be replaced with a clear one. Your personal \"refractive target\" is an important decision that you should discuss with your cataract surgeon before having surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "you are very nearsighted (myopic)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "with an artificial one (an intraocular lens or IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cloudy lens (cataract)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "SEP 27, 2023", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-improve-my-high-myopia", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-improve-my-high-myopia.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-increase-blood-pressure", "title": "Can cataract surgery increase blood pressure?", "question": "Can cataract surgery increase blood pressure due to the fact that the eye suddenly starts seeing things much clearer and the brain is not adjusted yet?", "answer": "There is no medical reason for an increase in blood pressure after cataract surgery . It is likely a pure coincidence.\n\nBlood pressure measures the pressure or force of blood against the blood vessel walls while circulating throughout the body. With high blood pressure (hypertension) the heart has to work harder to pump blood throughout the body, which can lead to serious health problems. With lifestyle changes like improving your diet, getting regular exercise, and taking prescription medication in some cases, you can lower your blood pressure. Talk to your doctor about the best way to lower yours.", "answer_links": [{"text": "blood pressure", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/blood-pressure"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 24, 2022", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-increase-blood-pressure", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-increase-blood-pressure.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-lasik-be-performed-at-same-ti-2", "title": "Can cataract surgery and LASIK be performed at the same time?", "question": "Can cataract surgery and LASIK surgery be performed at the same time?", "answer": "This should not be done. The selection of an intraocular lens (IOL) after cataract surgery can often accomplish the refractive change (vision correction) that one would obtain with LASIK or laser vision correction on the cornea . If there is a situation such as astigmatism , which is not planned to be treated at the time of cataract surgery but with laser correction of the cornea such as LASIK, this should be delayed after the cataract surgery by at least a month or several months. It is not advisable to do these procedures at the same time.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "LASIK or laser vision correction on the cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-refractive-surgery"}, {"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 17, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-lasik-be-performed-at-same-ti-2", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-lasik-be-performed-at-same-ti-2.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataract-surgery-trigger-naion", "title": "Can cataract surgery trigger NAION?", "question": "My wife had NAION damage in one eye several years ago which permanently affected the vision in that eye. She is now due for cataract surgery . Can cataract surgery trigger the same problem in her other eye?", "answer": "This is an excellent question without a clear answer. Research studies suggest that there is a slightly higher risk of NAION (non-arteritic anterior ischemic optic neuropathy ) after cataract surgery. This risk may be higher in patients with a history of NAION in their other eye. There are other rare complications from cataract surgery that cause permanent vision loss including infection inside the eye (endophthalmitis) and retinal detachment . Because cataracts slowly worsen over time, but do not typically damage the eye otherwise, patients are encouraged to weigh the risk of these uncommon complications against the relative interference of visual function from the cataract.", "answer_links": [{"text": "ischemic optic neuropathy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "infection inside the eye (endophthalmitis)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-endophthalmitis"}, {"text": "retinal detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}], "answered_by": null, "answered_by_url": null, "answered_at": "APR 22, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataract-surgery-trigger-naion", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataract-surgery-trigger-naion.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataracts-affect-depth-perception", "title": "Can cataracts affect depth perception?", "question": "If a person has cataracts in both eyes, but one is worse than the other, and they are not considered bad enough to have surgery , is it possible to start having difficulty with depth perception?\n\n<", "answer": "Any problem with vision affecting one or both eyes can cause a problem with depth perception—even an out-of-date glasses prescription.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 09, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataracts-affect-depth-perception", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataracts-affect-depth-perception.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataracts-cause-astigmatism", "title": "Can cataracts cause astigmatism?", "question": "Can cataracts cause astigmatism ?", "answer": "Yes. As the lens thickens and changes shape while developing a cataract there can be induced astigmatism due to these changes.", "answer_links": [{"text": "As the lens thickens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 15, 2018", "categories": ["Astigmatism", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataracts-cause-astigmatism", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataracts-cause-astigmatism.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-cataracts-cause-headaches", "title": "Can cataracts cause headaches?", "question": "Can cataracts cause headaches?", "answer": "It is unlikely for cataracts to cause headaches. However, if there is a change in the refraction (glasses power) due to the cataracts, that can cause discomfort and/or headaches. Also, loss of vision from cataracts can sometimes be partially compensated for by squinting the eyes which can give a feeling of strain or discomfort . Others will unconsciously use the brow to raise the eyelid to allow more light in and this can cause strain which may be perceived as headache.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "refraction (glasses power)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-do-astigmatism-measurements-mean"}, {"text": "feeling of strain or discomfort", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-eye-strain"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 30, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-cataracts-cause-headaches", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-cataracts-cause-headaches.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-depth-perception-be-off-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can depth perception be off after cataract surgery to one eye?", "question": "I had cataract surgery on my right eye and a premium lens put in. Ten days later while healing and waiting to do surgery for my left eye, I damaged my car backing out of the garage by colliding with the door frame. Could my depth perception be off and be the cause? I have backed in and out of the garage for 13 years with no issues.", "answer": "It is not uncommon to experience some difficulty with depth perception in the interval after cataract surgery in the first eye and before surgery in the second eye. This is particularly true if there is a large difference in glasses prescription between the two eyes during this interval. This situation is not unique to premium lenses and it usually resolves after surgery in the second eye, which can balance the prescription between the eyes. If the patient has elected to have monovision after surgery (one eye sees distance, the other eye sees up close), there may be a longer-lasting or even permanent decrease in depth perception. Any concerns about your visual function after cataract surgery should be discussed with your eye surgeon.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "SEP 21, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-depth-perception-be-off-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-depth-perception-be-off-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-distance-vision-fluctuate-after-cataract-surge", "title": "Can distance vision fluctuate after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can your distance vision fluctuate as you are healing from cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Yes. As the eye heals the eye’s surface can get dry or irritated and the vision can fluctuate. However, any significant and persistent decrease of vision after surgery should be immediately reported to your surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "eye’s surface", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 10, 2020", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-distance-vision-fluctuate-after-cataract-surge", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-distance-vision-fluctuate-after-cataract-surge.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-distance-vision-still-need-correction-after-ba", "title": "Can distance vision still need correction after a basic monofocal lens was implanted during cataract surgery?", "question": "Can distance vision still need correction after a basic monofocal lens was implanted during cataract surgery ? I have 20/30 vision in that eye three days after surgery and was wondering if I will still need glasses for distance vision for that eye, or whether the imperfect vision is due to mild corneal swelling and will correct on its own in the next month or two.", "answer": "Although it is possible that your vision will improve a bit further, you probably will need to have glasses to see \"perfectly\" at distance.\n\nMany cataract surgeons choose to use an implant that renders an eye a bit near-sighted, so that at least large objects can be visualized at near without glasses. Regardless, a weak prescription may be necessary for optimal distance vision.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "JUN 23, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-distance-vision-still-need-correction-after-ba", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-distance-vision-still-need-correction-after-ba.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-glasses-correct-halos-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can glasses correct halos after cataract surgery?", "question": "I have had cataract surgery and I see halos around lights at night. Can a prescription for glasses correct this problem?", "answer": "Perhaps. But a thorough complete examination by an ophthalmologist would be necessary to answer this question appropriately.", "answer_links": [{"text": "thorough complete examination by an ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "OCT 16, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-glasses-correct-halos-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-glasses-correct-halos-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-bungee-jump-after-having-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I bungee jump after having cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I bungee jump after having cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Generally, this activity is permissible a month after cataract surgery, but please check with your surgeon before doing this.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 04, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-bungee-jump-after-having-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-bungee-jump-after-having-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-choose-not-to-have-iol", "title": "Can cataract surgery cause dizziness and headache two months later?", "question": "I had cataract surgery in both eyes about two months ago. I have had a slight headache and dizziness over the left eye. It almost feels as if the lens is too powerful . Is this possible?", "answer": "Because your cataract surgeries were only two months ago, I would recommend contacting your cataract surgeon to let them know you are having these problems. Generally speaking, headache and dizziness are not typical symptoms this far out from surgery and may or may not be eye related.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "FEB 17, 2025", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-choose-not-to-have-iol", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-choose-not-to-have-iol.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-continue-to-wear-glasses-after-cataract-surg", "title": "Can I continue to wear glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I’ve worn glasses for 60 years and have an upcoming cataract surgery. Is it OK replicate my current measurements, which require glasses for both distance and reading?", "answer": "The goal for cataract surgery is a complex decision based on the individual needs of the patient. I strongly suggest you discuss this with your surgeon. There is no reason you could not wear glasses for distance and reading or progressives or bifocals after your cataract surgery no matter what goal you and your surgeon set.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "glasses for distance and reading or progressives or bifocals", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 25, 2022", "categories": ["Surgery", "Contacts and Glasses", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-continue-to-wear-glasses-after-cataract-surg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-continue-to-wear-glasses-after-cataract-surg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-fix-my-misshapen-macula-after-cataract-surge", "title": "Can I fix my misshapen macula after cataract surgery?", "question": "I have a misshapen macula resulting from an extremely difficult extraction of a very dense hyper-mature cataract . Is there a procedure to restore the macula ?", "answer": "It’s not possible to comment on this without an in-person exam . It could be that there is macular edema or some other disease causing the shape of the macula to be other than normal. The benefit of any potential treatment to your retina will vary depending on the underlying problem. Your surgeon or retinal specialist is best equipped to discuss the condition of your retina/macula and guide any necessary treatment.", "answer_links": [{"text": "in-person exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "macular edema", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-macular-edema"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "Abdhish R Bhavsar, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/58472acf-5519-403d-a07d-cd531a738f6d", "answered_at": "APR 25, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-fix-my-misshapen-macula-after-cataract-surge", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-fix-my-misshapen-macula-after-cataract-surge.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-get-iols-with-prism-correction", "title": "Can I get IOLs with prism correction?", "question": "I am 70 years old and have had prescription glasses with prisms for double vision for almost 50 years. I have very slight cataracts that do not require surgery now. However, could I have lens replacement surgery with lenses that have prisms?", "answer": "Unfortunately, there are no intraocular lenses (IOLs) that have prism in them. Depending on how much prism you have, eye muscle surgery can eliminate the need for prism in some cases.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses (IOLs)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "prism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/what-is-prism-correction-in-eyeglasses"}, {"text": "eye muscle surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/strabismus-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Aaron M Miller, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/1d353ee7-10f5-4298-a733-ea4d82f1bfc8", "answered_at": "AUG 16, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Double Vision"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-get-iols-with-prism-correction", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-get-iols-with-prism-correction.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-both-eyes-set-near-vision-during-catara", "title": "Can I have both eyes set for near vision during cataract surgery?", "question": "I had my right eye set for computer reading during cataract surgery and it went very well. I didn’t need glasses for driving, computer and other activities at all (except for reading tiny labels). The plan was to set my left eye for distance but now I wonder if I can set my left eye for near vision instead? I do a lot of sewing, quilting, reading printed sheet music, and cooking. So, I believe near vision would benefit me much more than distance.", "answer": "This question involves many issues which cannot be addressed here. You say you hardly need glasses now for most activities. How are you getting your distance vision? Is your computer eye giving you adequate distance vision or is it your left eye? If so, setting your left eye for reading will have you lose your distance. Is your left eye currently a reading eye? If so, then perhaps setting that eye for reading will work. It all depends on what your refractions are in your operated eye and unoperated eye. This is a very important conversation to have with your surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 03, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-both-eyes-set-near-vision-during-catara", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-both-eyes-set-near-vision-during-catara.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-retinal-dyst", "title": "Can I have cataract surgery if I have retinal dystrophy?", "question": "I have retinal dystrophy and mild cataracts. When my cataracts mature, is it possible to have them removed or would it not be an option?", "answer": "Yes, cataract surgery will be possible, and if and when the cataracts are affecting your vision significantly, it should be a good idea. There are many types of retinal dystrophies (a group of conditions one is born with that damage the retina over time), and any impact that they might have on surgical success would require much more information. Please discuss this with your cataract and/or retinal specialist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "OCT 19, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-retinal-dyst", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-retinal-dyst.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-cataract-surgery-only-on-worse-eye", "title": "Can I have cataract surgery only on the worse eye?", "question": "I have cataracts in both eyes, one worse than the other. The doctor recommended surgery on both eyes. I can see well out of the better eye so why do I need surgery on it? Can I have it only on the worse eye?", "answer": "Your doctor will never make you have surgery. However, I notice that in many cases, once the worst eye sees better, you will notice the cataract issue in the “better” eye. At this point it is all truly relative. Also, in some eyes which are very nearsighted or farsighted , removing both cataracts helps the eyes balance together in a better way optically.", "answer_links": [{"text": "nearsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "farsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/hyperopia-farsightedness"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 25, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-cataract-surgery-only-on-worse-eye", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-cataract-surgery-only-on-worse-eye.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-corneal-cataract-surgery-at-same-time", "title": "Can I have corneal and cataract surgery at the same time?", "question": "I am 77 and have Fuchs’ dystrophy and also need cataract surgery . Can cataract surgery and corneal transplant (endothelium, for Fuchs’) be done at the same time? If so, what is the success rate, and should I even have these done at my age?", "answer": "When patients have both Fuchs' corneal dystrophy and cataracts, the ophthalmologist needs to find out which condition is most responsible for the patient's visual decline. In some cases, only one of the conditions may need to be addressed. If the visual decline is mainly due to the cataract, and cataract surgery can be done without causing the cornea to permanently swell, then cataract surgery alone is the preferred treatment option. If Fuchs' dystrophy is the major cause for the symptoms, sometimes a transplant alone is performed without touching the cataract.\n\nIf your ophthalmologist believes that performing cataract surgery will cause the Fuchs' dystrophy to permanently swell, or if performing a corneal transplant will cause the cataract to become visually significant, he or she may opt to do a combined procedure (cataract surgery along with a partial or full thickness corneal transplant). My personal preference is not to do them at the same time, but instead to stage them one after the other. I often do the cataract surgery first to see if the cornea will recover prior to deciding if a transplant will be necessary. Unfortunately, this strategy calls for multiple trips to the operating room rather than getting it all done at the same time. Ophthalmologists have their own personal preference and you should discuss these issues with your doctor.\n\nAdvanced age only plays a role when discussing the recovery time needed from a surgical procedure. Often in partial thickness transplants, it may take three months for the vision to recover. In full thickness transplants, it can be over a year. A patient may not want to go through that recovery period of having often poorer vision during that time if they are of an older age. Also, as patients age, other health problems arise that may prevent surgical clearance for anesthesia (pain management, which can include loss of sensation as well as unconsciousness).", "answer_links": [{"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Omar R Chaudhary, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/8e0e0d43-5cc4-4c54-be05-971ce84e7afa", "answered_at": "DEC 09, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-corneal-cataract-surgery-at-same-time", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-corneal-cataract-surgery-at-same-time.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-intraocular-lenses-from-two-different-c", "title": "Can I have intraocular lenses from two different companies placed in my eyes?", "question": "My right eye has been operated upon for cataract and a Russian IOL was implanted. Can a lens manufactured by a different company be implanted in my left eye? Also, how much time gap is required to get my second eye operated on?", "answer": "It is common for patients to have intraocular lenses from different manufacturers in their eyes and this should cause you no problems. Your surgeon should be able to advise you on compatibility. Most ophthalmologists wait two to three weeks between eyes. When you see a surgeon for surgery on the second eye, it would be helpful to that second surgeon if you bring the information of the lens implant used on the first eye.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 08, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-intraocular-lenses-from-two-different-c", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-intraocular-lenses-from-two-different-c.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-monovision-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I keep my natural monovision after cataract surgery?", "question": "I have natural monovision and will soon have cataract surgery done on both eyes. Will my eyes continue to be this way after surgery or do I need to put special lenses in to ensure that I continue to have this vision? I have had wonderful vision until cataracts and want to continue as I had previously after surgery.", "answer": "Monovision is a condition in which one eye is focused for reading and the other eye for distance . Therefore, no glasses may be needed. If you have monovision naturally, then this can likely be duplicated after cataract surgery. The surgeon can choose an intraocular lens (IOL) powered for reading vision in the eye that is currently your reading eye and an IOL for distance vision in the eye that is currently distance.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Monovision is a condition in which one eye is focused for reading and the other eye for distance", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}, {"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 08, 2023", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-monovision-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-monovision-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-multifocal-iol-put-over-my-basic-iol", "title": "Can I have multifocal IOL put over my basic IOL?", "question": "I am 60 and have had cataract surgery on both eyes. On one eye I have a basic monofocal intraocular lens (IOL) , leaving me farsighted. The other eye has a mid-range lens. I regret not getting the advanced multifocal lens for both eyes. Do you know if there are multifocal lenses being manufactured that can be piggybacked on a basic monofocal lens?", "answer": "Multifocal intraocular lenses (IOLs) must be precisely positioned within the eye to work as intended.\n\nWhile it is technically possible to place a multifocal lens in front of a monofocal lens (a “piggyback” placement), this is rarely done due to potential visual distortions (aberrations) and difficulty stably centering the multifocal IOL. Both of these issues could leave you with more visual problems than you started out with. Research is being done in this area, so that answer may change in the future. Along the same lines, while an IOL exchange (removing a IOL and replacing it with a different IOL) is a reasonable option if you are removing a problematic multifocal IOL and replacing it with a monofocal IOL, it is rarely done for the reverse situation due to the difficulty in properly positioning and stabilizing the new multifocal lens.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses (IOLs)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "JUN 08, 2021", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-multifocal-iol-put-over-my-basic-iol", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-multifocal-iol-put-over-my-basic-iol.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-my-eyes-dilated-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I have my eyes dilated after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery almost two years ago. I went for an eye exam a few days ago and he dilated and numbed my eyes . Now my vision is blurry in my right eye where I had better than 20/20 vision. Are eyes supposed to be numbed and dilated after cataract surgery?", "answer": "Typically, a full dilated exam is done at least once a year after cataract surgery. If the vision does not clear up within a few days, you should get reexamined by your doctor.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 14, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Eye Exams"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-my-eyes-dilated-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-my-eyes-dilated-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-my-same-glasses-power-after-cataract-su", "title": "Can I have my same glasses power after cataract surgery?", "question": "My eyes are very bad, and I have cataracts . I do not want to change my visual acuity with a lens implant . Is this possible?", "answer": "If what you want is the same amount of myopia or hyperopia as you had prior to cataract surgery , yes, this can be done.", "answer_links": [{"text": "myopia", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "hyperopia", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/hyperopia-farsightedness"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 28, 2018", "categories": ["Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-my-same-glasses-power-after-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-my-same-glasses-power-after-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-surgery-done-under-general-anesthesia", "title": "Can I have surgery done under general anesthesia?", "question": "I'm a 55-year-old old male with extreme light sensitivity and a severe case of ommatophobia (fear of eyes). Treatments could not help me get rid of this psychological disorder. I had a cataract surgery under general anesthesia two years ago and now I have a secondary cataract. I'm trying to find a doctor to perform a YAG laser capsulotomy surgery under general anesthesia. Is that possible?", "answer": "YAG laser capsulotomy is the internationally accepted and preferred treatment for secondary cataract (also known as posterior capsular opacification) , or a clouding of the capsule that held your eye’s natural lens in place). This treatment requires the patient to look at a given point and not to move their eyes as each laser pulse is delivered, so you cannot be asleep during the procedure. In many cases the entire treatment can be accomplished with one or two laser pulses. It is much safer than the bladed surgery used before YAG that I know of no doctor that would not advise YAG laser for capsulotomy. There is no pain whatsoever.\n\nBefore YAG laser treatment was done, secondary cataracts were surgically treated with a special needle/knife in the operating room. In fact, general anesthesia is still used for this needle/knife procedure in children. The surgical risks are still very low, but definitely higher than YAG. If you are completely certain that hypnosis and tranquilizing medications would not make it possible for you to have YAG, then I would advise you to discuss this surgical approach to your problem with your ophthalmologist. He/she might refer you to a pediatric ophthalmologist as they would likely have more experience performing the bladed capsulotomy.\n\nThere are a few pediatric ophthalmologists around the country that do have a YAG laser that can be used under general anesthesia, however, most are located in a children's hospital. I would suggest you make some inquiries in your area to see if this exists. Otherwise, you could seek out the care of a retina specialist that might approach this from behind the implant.\n\nYou may have another problem however: an insurance problem. I suspect that you, your ophthalmologist and a qualified psychologist/psychiatrist would need to convince your insurance company why they need to pay the added expense of an operating room, anesthesia, and other related expenses when such a simple and cost-effective laser treatment can solve your medical problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "secondary cataract (also known as posterior capsular opacification)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 09, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-surgery-done-under-general-anesthesia", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-surgery-done-under-general-anesthesia.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-have-yag-capsulotomy-secondary-cataract-if-i", "title": "Can I have YAG capsulotomy for secondary cataract if I have dry eyes?", "question": "I was told I have dry eyes after cataract surgery three month ago. My ophthalmologist advised recently that I need YAG. Is it advisable to have this laser surgery with my dry eyes condition?", "answer": "Posterior capsule opacification and the need for a YAG capsulotomy (using laser to create an opening in the cloudy capsule that holds your artificial lens) is a separate issue from dry eyes. Dry eyes do not interfere with the performance of the YAG. The only caution is to understand that dry eyes can contribute to blurring. So the YAG laser treatment will clear up blurring caused by the cloudy capsule but will not help blurring that may be due to the dry eyes.", "answer_links": [{"text": "capsulotomy (using laser to create an opening in the cloudy capsule that holds your artificial lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 27, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-have-yag-capsulotomy-secondary-cataract-if-i", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-have-yag-capsulotomy-secondary-cataract-if-i.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-massage-my-client-after-recent-cataract-surg", "title": "Can I massage my client after their recent cataract surgery?", "question": "I am a massage therapist with a client who had cataract surgery five days before her appointment. I erred on the side of caution and told the client I'd feel more comfortable with her being cleared by her cataract surgeon before having a massage. How long should a patient typically wait to get massage therapy after having cataract surgery?", "answer": "They can have a massage within 10 days as long as no direct pressure is placed on the eye. Be sure to take caution with how they are situated on the head rest when lying face down.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 26, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-massage-my-client-after-recent-cataract-surg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-massage-my-client-after-recent-cataract-surg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-prevent-slow-development-of-my-mild-cataract", "title": "Can I prevent or slow the development of my mild cataract?", "question": "I am 67 years old and have just had a diagnosis of mild cataracts. Is there any way to prevent or slow its development?", "answer": "Cataracts are a normal function of aging . If you live long enough, you will develop cataracts. That being said, there are a few things that can be done to delay some forms of cataract.\n\nUltraviolet light (UV) causes cataracts, so it is wise to wear UV protective glasses , both for indoors and out of doors. Diabetes can cause cataracts so it’s important to regulate your blood sugar carefully if you are diabetic. Corticosteroids can cause cataract so it is wise to limit use of these medications whenever possible.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataracts are a normal function of aging", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "UV protective glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/sunglasses-3"}, {"text": "Diabetes can cause cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/diabetes"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 19, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-prevent-slow-development-of-my-mild-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-prevent-slow-development-of-my-mild-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-remove-my-dermolipoma-cosmetic-reasons", "title": "Can I remove my dermolipoma for cosmetic reasons?", "question": "I have a small dermolipoma that makes my eye look more red then other. Could a doctor place some sort of graft over it to make that area look more white and matching or could eye whitening work over the birth defect?", "answer": "Oculoplastic surgeons can remove dermolipomas (a tumor present in the eye at birth) in the operating room for cosmetic reasons. However, removing a dermolipoma is not necessary since it is benign and rarely enlarges. Other treatments are not effective.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "SEP 07, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-remove-my-dermolipoma-cosmetic-reasons", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-remove-my-dermolipoma-cosmetic-reasons.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-still-have-cataract-surgery-if-coronavirus-i", "title": "Can I still have cataract surgery if the coronavirus is still around in about a month?", "question": "My cataracts have been pretty annoying , and the last time I saw my ophthalmologist we discussed it might be time to have cataract surgery. Can I still have the surgery if the coronavirus is still around in about a month?", "answer": "In general, cataract removal is an elective procedure, and medical experts say elective surgery should be postponed during this pandemic . There are some exceptions that are considered urgent (including cataracts causing other complications, such as angle-closure glaucoma , or cataracts resulting from an eye injury that needs surgery). Many ophthalmic practices are postponing cataract surgery right now. You can always call your ophthalmologist to discuss your individual situation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract removal", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "pandemic", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/coronavirus"}, {"text": "angle-closure glaucoma", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-glaucoma"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 27, 2020", "categories": ["Coronavirus", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-still-have-cataract-surgery-if-coronavirus-i", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-still-have-cataract-surgery-if-coronavirus-i.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-take-dmso-with-iol", "title": "Can I take DMSO with an IOL?", "question": "Will taking DMSO harm the IOL inside my eye?", "answer": "DMSO is a chemical approved by the FDA for interstitial cystitis (chronic or ongoing bladder pain and sometimes pelvic pain) and used \"off-label\" by doctors to treat a variety of conditions. There is currently no evidence that DMSO causes any harm to implanted intraocular lenses (IOLs) . That said, if you are taking it for an off-label problem (anything other than interstitial cystitis), then you should discuss its use and general safety with your primary care provider.", "answer_links": [{"text": "implanted intraocular lenses (IOLs)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "MAR 14, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-take-dmso-with-iol", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-take-dmso-with-iol.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-take-xiidra-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I take Xiidra after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it safe to take Xiidra for dry eye after cataract surgery?", "answer": "There is no restriction against using Xiidra after cataract surgery . But I would not start using it until several weeks after surgery because if symptoms arise such as burning, redness or irritation, it would be difficult to know whether they resulted from Xiidra or the surgery itself.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 15, 2022", "categories": ["Dry Eye", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-take-xiidra-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-take-xiidra-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-use-eye-exercises-to-expedite-healing-after-", "title": "Can I use eye exercises to expedite healing after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I use eye exercises to expedite healing after cataract surgery? My vision is worse in the operated eye after six days.", "answer": "People may have blurry vision after cataract surgery for a variety of reasons. In many cases the vision improves with time and healing or with corrective lenses (glasses or contact lenses). Unfortunately, there are no eye exercises that will speed up this process. You should discuss your concerns about your vision with your cataract surgeon, who should be able to explain why your vision seems worse if it has not improved by this point. If your vision is actually worsening in the first week after surgery, this could be a sign of a problem so please call your surgeon now to discuss your symptoms.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "NOV 07, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-use-eye-exercises-to-expedite-healing-after-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-use-eye-exercises-to-expedite-healing-after-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-use-flonase-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I use Flonase after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I use Flonase after cataract surgery?", "answer": "Flonase—a steroid nasal spray used for rhinitis and allergies —will likely not interfere with your healing after cataract surgery . However, to be safe, please check with your surgeon before resuming this or any other medication shortly after your procedure. Flonase and similar allergy medications can raise intraocular pressure (IOP) and increase your risk of infection.", "answer_links": [{"text": "rhinitis and allergies", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/allergies"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "intraocular pressure (IOP)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 15, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-use-flonase-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-use-flonase-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-use-my-glasses-12-days-after-cataract-surger", "title": "Can I use my glasses 12 days after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery 12 days ago, but my sight is still cloudy. Is it OK to use my old glasses from before the surgery?", "answer": "Some post-cataract patients see well in just a few days after surgery, but it is not uncommon for vision to still be cloudy. Keep up with the drops as prescribed and call your surgeon if you have concerns to get an earlier follow-up visit if necessary. Pain or a sudden drop in vision would be more of an urgent concern. Your glasses will probably not correct your vision, but if you find them useful there is no harm.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "William Barry Lee, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6e7ea7d6-fac3-4515-90c3-249b40819804", "answered_at": "APR 15, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-use-my-glasses-12-days-after-cataract-surger", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-use-my-glasses-12-days-after-cataract-surger.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-use-something-other-than-atropine-inflammati", "title": "Can I use something other than Atropine for inflammation after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am 70 and had cataract surgery three weeks ago. I now have inflammation (swelling, redness, and irritation) in that eye and the second surgery was cancelled. Atropine eye drops were ordered but I can’t afford them and insurance does not cover it. Is there another drop other than Atropine that can be used?", "answer": "Persistent inflammation three weeks after cataract surgery is not that unusual and is very treatable. Atropine causes dilation (widening) of the pupil and protects the barrier between inflammation and the eye. The class of drugs is called cyclopegics. Similar drugs that can be substituted are cyclopentolate or homatropine. Sadly, in my practice I have found that insurers and formularies sometimes don’t cover any of these drugs. For that I have no explanation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "dilation (widening)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/drugs/what-to-expect-eyes-are-dilated"}, {"text": "pupil", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/pupil"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 28, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-use-something-other-than-atropine-inflammati", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-use-something-other-than-atropine-inflammati.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-use-warm-compresses-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I do warm compresses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery and now have mild blepharitis. Will warm compresses damage my new lenses?", "answer": "The heat will not damage your intraocular lens (IOL) as it is inside your eye and the heat is applied externally to your eyelids. But I would not do the warm compresses immediately after surgery and am assuming your operation was a month or more ago.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Mar. 16, 2015.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 02, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-use-warm-compresses-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-use-warm-compresses-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-wear-contact-lens-in-one-eye-after-surgery-o", "title": "Can I wear a contact lens in one eye after surgery on the other eye?", "question": "I’m having cataract surgery on my right eye. Can I still wear a contact lens in left eye?", "answer": "Yes, you may wear a contact lens on the non-operated eye after cataract surgery , but I advise you to speak with your ophthalmologist about your intention prior to the surgery. He or she might have some concern about proper handling of your contact lens and any risk of infection from your hands to your newly operated eye. Some people wear a contact lens in the operated eye after it has healed if they require additional focusing.", "answer_links": [{"text": "contact lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens-102"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "OCT 21, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-wear-contact-lens-in-one-eye-after-surgery-o", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-wear-contact-lens-in-one-eye-after-surgery-o.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-wear-contact-lenses-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I wear contact lenses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery in both eyes about 15 years ago with monofocal lenses inserted. For many years my vision was just fine with the mono lenses (I had worn mono contacts for years before the cataract surgery) but my near vision is beginning to go and I need readers to see almost all type sizes . Can I now have contact lenses to wear over the mono cataract lenses or must I use readers forever?", "answer": "To clarify some of these terms for our readers, it sounds as though you had cataract surgery with implantation of monofocal lenses in each eye. These monofocal lenses were used to achieve monovision, where one eye was set for distance and the other set for near.\n\nTo answer your question, unless you have another ailment, you can almost certainly wear contact lenses after having cataract surgery, and there are a variety of choices are available to you. You can wear a contact that improves the distance vision in the near eye, you can wear a contact that improves the near vision in the distance eye, or you could even wear a contact to enhance the near vision in the near eye. This question was originally answered on Oct. 05, 2015.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "SEP 19, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-wear-contact-lenses-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-wear-contact-lenses-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-wear-glasses-with-monovision", "title": "Can I wear glasses with Monovision?", "question": "I have just had cataract surgery in my right eye and my vision was corrected to allow me to read without glasses. I asked my ophthalmologist about cataract surgery on the left eye to correct for distance, but he is reluctant to recommend that because some people have adjustment problems. I am content to wear glasses all the time, but he said with monovision you don't wear glasses. My question is: couldn't I still wear glasses to correct each eye for all distances, and only rely on the monovision in a pinch?", "answer": "Monovision is the planned imbalance of the glasses need of each eye, such that one eye is focused for distance and the other for near . It is sort of like wearing a high heeled shoe on one foot and a flat on the other.\n\nMonovision, in the best case, can make eyeglasses unnecessary. As you can imagine, if the high heel shoe is too high, you would be unable to function. Similarly, if the difference between the two eyes is too great, the patient will have double vision.\n\nThere is a popular variation of monovision called mini-monovision whereby the difference between the two eyes is made so as to protect distance vision in one eye and also provide limited near vision in the other eye, as in using a computer, but not necessarily reading a book or newspaper. Eyeglasses can be prescribed to wear over monovision or mini-monovision to eliminate the imbalance between the two eyes. It is very important to note that you already have one eye set for near vision. That means that your unoperated left eye must be focused carefully based on the focus of the right eye so as to insure comfortable vision for you.\n\nThere is another concern. Right handed people usually (but not always) have a dominant right eye and vice versa. Vision imbalance works out best when the dominant eye is focused for distance and the non-dominant eye for near. The best news is that your monovision or mini-monovision result can be tested in advance with a contact lens test drive. Your doctor can place a soft contact lens in your left eye to demonstrate what your vision would be like with one or more different power lens selections. You must keep in mind that predicting the focusing power of an eye after cataract surgery is pretty accurate, but there is no way to guarantee your eyeglasses need after cataract surgery. This means that your ophthalmologist is going to want to leave a little room for error after the surgery.\n\nI advise that you discuss this carefully with your ophthalmologist and request a contact lens test drive of your options: 1) both eyes for near and you wear distance glasses, 2) Monovision with distance vision in the left eye and wear glasses as needed, 3) mini-monovision with the left eye for improved but less than perfect distance vision and wear glasses as needed.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Monovision is the planned imbalance of the glasses need of each eye, such that one eye is focused for distance and the other for near", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}, {"text": "contact lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens-102"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAR 02, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-wear-glasses-with-monovision", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-wear-glasses-with-monovision.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-i-wear-non-prescription-glasses-after-cataract", "title": "Can I wear non-prescription glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am considering cataract surgery with a monofocal lens for clear distance vision. I've worn eyeglasses for years , and I like the protection from brush, bugs and limbs when outdoors. Will it cause problems to continue wearing non-prescription glasses for eye protection after the surgery?", "answer": "There should be no problem with non-prescription protective eyewear after cataract surgery. In fact, protective eyewear (safety glasses) is strongly recommended for any activity in which there is risk of objects or debris striking the eye .", "answer_links": [{"text": "In fact, protective eyewear (safety glasses) is strongly recommended for any activity in which there is risk of objects or debris striking the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/injuries-protective-eyewear"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 27, 2021", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-i-wear-non-prescription-glasses-after-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-i-wear-non-prescription-glasses-after-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-intraocular-lens-become-damaged-once-inside-ey", "title": "Can an IOL become damaged once inside the eye?", "question": "I had cataract surgery about a year and a half ago. Can the IOL become damaged or scratched once inside the eye?", "answer": "Once your IOL (or artificial intraocular lens) has been placed inside of your eye there is very little chance that any damage can occur to it, especially a year and a half after surgery.\n\nThere are a few very uncommon conditions that can harm your implant, but they are very unlikely. First, the treatment of a cloudy membrane (secondary cataract) with a YAG laser (called a posterior capsulotomy) rarely produces slight imperfections in the lens, most of which do not affect the quality of your vision. Still more uncommon, the IOL can be squeezed from its normal shape and position by abnormal contraction of the bag or sac into which the lens has been implanted. Even more uncommon is severe trauma to the implanted eye as in an auto accident.\n\nIf you have any specific concerns I would suggest you follow up with your surgeon, but I think you will continue to do fine.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Dec. 21, 2016.", "answer_links": [{"text": "IOL (or artificial intraocular lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "First, the treatment of a cloudy membrane (secondary cataract) with a YAG laser", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "JAN 30, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-intraocular-lens-become-damaged-once-inside-ey", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-intraocular-lens-become-damaged-once-inside-ey.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-iols-get-dirty-inside-of-eye-cause-blurry-visi", "title": "Can IOLs get dirty inside of the eye and cause blurry vision?", "question": "I had cataract surgery 12 to 13 years ago. About 4 months following the surgery, I developed posterior capsular haze (when the tissue holding your new intraocular lens in place becomes cloudy after cataract surgery) and a YAG laser was used to clear up my vision. Over time, my vision has gotten cloudy again. Can the IOL itself get \"dirty?\" If so, can it be cleaned? If not, what are some possible causes?", "answer": "The IOL being in your eye is in a sterile environment and cannot get dirty and the capsular haze rarely returns after YAG. I would go to your ophthalmologist as soon as you can and get this evaluated, as retinal and other issues can affect vision as well.", "answer_links": [{"text": "retinal", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 26, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-iols-get-dirty-inside-of-eye-cause-blurry-visi", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-iols-get-dirty-inside-of-eye-cause-blurry-visi.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-muzzle-flashes-from-tank-firing-cause-cataract", "title": "Can the muzzle flashes from a tank firing cause cataracts?", "question": "My brother had cataracts removed from both of his eyes when he was in his early 40s. During basic training in the National Guard years earlier, he was exposed to flashes of bright light from a tank firing without wearing eye protection. Is it possible these bright flashes contributed to his premature cataracts?", "answer": "There are many causes for the early development of cataract including eye injuries, genetic syndromes, inherited predisposition, diabetes , steroid use, smoking , UV light exposure (sunlight, tanning beds, arc welding without protection), etc. While it is \"possible\" that some aspect of your brother's military experience and personal behaviors during his term of service could have contributed to his premature cataracts, there would be no way to identify the impact of any one specific exposure such as the cannon flashes.", "answer_links": [{"text": "diabetes", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/diabetic-eye-disease"}, {"text": "smoking", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/smokers"}, {"text": "UV light exposure", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/sun"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "MAY 28, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-muzzle-flashes-from-tank-firing-cause-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-muzzle-flashes-from-tank-firing-cause-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-my-mother-in-law-have-cataract-surgery-while-b", "title": "Can my mother-in-law have cataract surgery while being treated for cancer?", "question": "My mother-in-law has breast cancer and is currently on chemotherapy, gemcetabine and kapacitabine and has developed cataract . Can she have surgery to remove it while undergoing cancer treatment?", "answer": "I know of no problem having cataract surgery while under chemotherapy with those medications. The decision to have cataract surgery depends more on her overall medical condition. These medicines do have side effects that may make it advisable to wait until completion of treatment. For example, if nausea and vomiting are not well controlled it would be wiser to wait. While bruising and bleeding can be issues with these medications that is not usually an issue with cataract surgery. Increased risk of infection can occur and may be a reason to hold off on cataract surgery.\n\nTherefore, if the cataract is severe enough to warrant surgery while having chemotherapy, then it certainly can be done provided that her medical condition is stable and she is not suffering from immediate side effects of the treatment.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 19, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-my-mother-in-law-have-cataract-surgery-while-b", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-my-mother-in-law-have-cataract-surgery-while-b.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-new-stem-cell-treatments-treat-missed-congenit", "title": "Can new stem-cell treatments treat a missed congenital cataract in a 21-year-old?", "question": "Can new stem-cell treatment treat a missed congenital cataract in a 21-year-old?", "answer": "There is no approved stem cell treatment for cataracts at this time. A great deal of research is being done with stem cells and the eye and it is possible that work in this very area is underway somewhere. It is possible that the congenital cataract deprived the eye of its normal development during youth and resulted in a condition we call amblyopia, or lazy eye . This condition must be diagnosed and treated prior to the age of seven for significant recovery of vision to occur.\n\nI offer a caution as there are several unaffiliated or free-standing stem cell clinics that offer solutions to problems that are actually beyond the scope of their expertise. For any medical treatment, be sure to see a board-certified MD or DO, who is fully licensed to practice in your state. There was a case in Florida where several people were blinded in both eyes by stem cell injections that were not well founded in science.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "a condition we call amblyopia, or lazy eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amblyopia-lazy-eye"}, {"text": "There was a case in Florida where several people were blinded in both eyes by stem cell injections that were not well founded in science.", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/unregulated-stem-cell-treatments-can-be-dangerous"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "APR 23, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-new-stem-cell-treatments-treat-missed-congenit", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-new-stem-cell-treatments-treat-missed-congenit.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-newly-approved-symphony-iol-be-used-if-patient", "title": "Can the newly approved Symphony IOL be used if the patient has a macular pucker?", "question": "Can the newly approved Symphony IOL be used if patient has a macular pucker ?", "answer": "It can be used but it will not provide the maximum vision that a healthy retina would allow. For this reason, I would pick a single vision lens or an accommodative intraocular lens (IOL).", "answer_links": [{"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 20, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-newly-approved-symphony-iol-be-used-if-patient", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-newly-approved-symphony-iol-be-used-if-patient.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-ophthalmologist-notice-cataract-when-looking-a", "title": "Can an ophthalmologist notice a cataract when looking at your eye?", "question": "I recently went to an ophthalmologist for a check-up . He noticed I've become slightly more nearsighted . My question is about cataracts . Would he have noticed it when he looked at my eye or could I actually have had that without him realizing it? How noticeable are cataracts to an ophthalmologist looking at your eye?", "answer": "Cataracts develop much like day turns to night. There are many shades of darkness as day ends and night begins. The development of cataracts usually progresses very slowly. Ophthalmologists usually grade cataract 1-4 with 4 being the least bothersome for the patient. Cataract surgery is usually not considered unless the cataract is grade 2 or more advanced and the patient is having vision problems. Just about everyone in the over-65 age group has some degree of clouding in their eye’s natural lens . Most of us do not label this minimal clouding as cataract until it is more noticeable and begins to impact your best corrected vision (with glasses).\n\nWith that being said, yes, I think your ophthalmologist would have noticed cataracts in your eyes if you had them. He/she would have told you if your diagnosis was cataract. He/she might NOT have said anything if the clouding of your lens was very slight and not yet up to the classification of cataract. Mild change in glasses prescription can occur from many reasons other than cataract. I suggest you discuss your concerns with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "eye’s natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAY 08, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-ophthalmologist-notice-cataract-when-looking-a", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-ophthalmologist-notice-cataract-when-looking-a.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-polocaine-be-used-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can polocaine be used for cataract surgery?", "question": "Can polocaine be used for cataract surgery?", "answer": "Polocaine (Mepivocaine) is a painkiller, a cousin of \"novocaine,\" so it is used in all sorts of eye procedures. It can be given by injection around the eye, or with eye drops for cataract surgery.\n\nStill, preservative-free lidocaine is probably most frequently used for cataract surgery .", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "JUN 28, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-polocaine-be-used-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-polocaine-be-used-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-sight-ever-be-restored-after-getting-infection", "title": "Can sight ever be restored after getting an infection during cataract surgery?", "question": "Can sight ever be restored after getting an infection during cataract surgery?", "answer": "An infection associated with cataract surgery ay be discovered as early as one day and as late as several months after the surgery. The outcome of an intraocular infection after surgery, known as endophthalmitis, can vary from no adverse effect on vision to total loss of vision. This usually depends on the microbe that caused the infection, when the infection is discovered, and how the patient responds to treatment. So sight can be restored in an infection after cataract surgery in many, but not all, cases.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 11, 2016", "categories": ["Infections", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-sight-ever-be-restored-after-getting-infection", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-sight-ever-be-restored-after-getting-infection.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-toric-iol-be-replaced-with-simple-monofocal-io", "title": "Can a toric IOL be replaced with a simple monofocal IOL?", "question": "Can a toric IOL be replaced with a simple monofocal IOL (without astigmatism correction) ? Toric lenses make ball sports nearly impossible.", "answer": "Toric lenses (artificial intraocular lenses with astigmatism correction placed in the eye during cataract surgery) have absolutely no effect on any sport. Just like a pair of glasses with astigmatism correction, they will only make your vision of better and clearer quality. I expect something else is going on here—maybe what you have is a multifocal lens. Any lens can be replaced with a monofocal lens, but the surgery can be difficult and complications that can limit vision can occur so it is not to be taken lightly. Please speak to your surgeon about what is going on with your vision and ask for alternatives.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 11, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-toric-iol-be-replaced-with-simple-monofocal-io", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-toric-iol-be-replaced-with-simple-monofocal-io.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-trauma-cause-posterior-capsular-opacification", "title": "Can trauma cause posterior capsular opacification?", "question": "Can head trauma or falling and hitting your head cause a posterior capsular opacification?", "answer": "Posterior capsular opacification (or PCO, and sometimes referred to as a “secondary cataract”) is a harmless clouding of the thin membrane or lens capsule that supports the new artificial lens after cataract surgery. While it is not completely understood why some people get this and some do not, it is safe to say that trauma is not a cause. If you have cloudy vision from a PCO, a posterior capsulotomy restores clear vision by making an opening in the lens capsule . If you are having vision issues after hitting your head, please consult your primary care physician or ophthalmologist immediately.", "answer_links": [{"text": "the thin membrane or lens capsule", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}, {"text": "new artificial lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "a posterior capsulotomy restores clear vision by making an opening in the lens capsule", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "NOV 10, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-trauma-cause-posterior-capsular-opacification", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-trauma-cause-posterior-capsular-opacification.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-treatment-wet-amd-cause-cataract-formation", "title": "Can treatment for wet AMD cause cataracts?", "question": "Can treatment for wet AMD cause cataract formation? After one year of monthly injections with aflibercept (Eylea) I developed a cataract in the treated eye. Before treatment there was no cataract, and I always have worn sunglasses with 100% UV ray protection.", "answer": "Research has not found a link between treatment for wet AMD and cataract. Although cataract is mentioned as a side effect in the manufacturer’s Patient Safety Information for aflibercept, this is not felt to be a common problem. Cataracts can progress despite UV protection, and many different factors play a role, including age, genetics, medical conditions, smoking, and more.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Nora Khatib, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/65611fdf-e347-49bc-8c49-9fedc116e7c2", "answered_at": "FEB 07, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Macular Degeneration"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-treatment-wet-amd-cause-cataract-formation", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-treatment-wet-amd-cause-cataract-formation.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-using-beauty-products-make-cataract-worse", "title": "Can using beauty products make a cataract worse?", "question": "Can wearing eye makeup , perfume, hairspray, nail polish or other beauty products worsen a pre-existing cortical cataract ? I was recently diagnosed and I want to know which products to avoid that could make it worse.", "answer": "Most common beauty products are very unlikely to cause or worsen cataract if used properly. Products designed to be used on the eyelids (mascara, eye liner, eye shadow) are usually formulated to be safe for use near the eyes, but should not be placed in the eye. Improper use of beauty products, such as allowing contact with the surface of the eye, can definitely lead to irritation and even permanent damage of the eye. Always read and follow the warnings and precautions for each product. Do not allow any beauty product to touch your eyeball.", "answer_links": [{"text": "eyelids", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eyelid-4"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "JUN 25, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-using-beauty-products-make-cataract-worse", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-using-beauty-products-make-cataract-worse.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-yag-laser-capsulotomy-be-done-with-pvd-in-both", "title": "Can YAG laser capsulotomy be done with PVD in both eyes?", "question": "Can YAG laser capsulotomy be done after a PVD in both eyes?", "answer": "A posterior vitreous detachment (PVD) is a separation of the vitreous gel inside the back cavity of the eye. It is most often part of the aging process but can also occur following cataract surgery or YAG laser capsulotomy . A PVD can be associated with retinal tears and detachments . Any new floaters or flashes of light should be evaluated by an ophthalmologist.\n\nA posterior capsular opacity (PCO) is a clouding of the thin membrane (lens capsule) holding the intraocular lens following cataract surgery . YAG laser treatment makes a hole in this cloudy lens capsule to restore clear vision.\n\nYes, a YAG laser capsulotomy can be performed in the presence of pre-existing PVD. Rarely, it can lead to a retinal tear or detachment, although people like you who already have a PVD may be at somewhat lower risk.", "answer_links": [{"text": "A posterior vitreous detachment (PVD)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-posterior-vitreous-detachment"}, {"text": "YAG laser capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "retinal tears and detachments", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}, {"text": "floaters or flashes of light", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-floaters-flashes"}, {"text": "thin membrane (lens capsule)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "AUG 22, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-yag-laser-capsulotomy-be-done-with-pvd-in-both", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-yag-laser-capsulotomy-be-done-with-pvd-in-both.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-yag-laser-disturb-toric-lens-after-cataract-su", "title": "Can YAG laser disturb a toric lens after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can a YAG capsulotomy (using laser to clear the cloudy capsule that holds your artificial lens) disturb a toric lens’s rotation or axis after cataract surgery over 6 months ago?", "answer": "No, the intraocular lens should be firmly positioned inside the lens capsule and this should not be a problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "lens capsule", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUL 18, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-yag-laser-disturb-toric-lens-after-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-yag-laser-disturb-toric-lens-after-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-you-have-cataract-surgery-again-if-pressure-is", "title": "Can you have cataract surgery again if pressure is high?", "question": "If you had cataract surgery once, can you have it again because your eye pressure keeps rising?", "answer": "Cataract surgery is done once per eye and never repeated. In some cases, cataract surgery can lower high pressure caused by certain types of glaucoma (most commonly narrow-angle glaucoma) . If your pressure is too high after cataract surgery, talk with your ophthalmologist about possible treatments, which include drops, laser, or surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "certain types of glaucoma (most commonly narrow-angle glaucoma)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-glaucoma"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 13, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Glaucoma"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-you-have-cataract-surgery-again-if-pressure-is", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-you-have-cataract-surgery-again-if-pressure-is.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-you-have-eyelash-lift-two-weeks-before-catarac", "title": "Can you have an eyelash lift two weeks before cataract surgery?", "question": "Can you have an eyelash lift two weeks before cataract surgery?", "answer": "Eyelash lifts (a procedure performed at a beauty salon that permanently curls eyelashes upwards) can use various methods and occasionally use chemicals.\n\nWhile I don’t know of any reason to not do this, I would recommend against it out of an abundance of caution. You will only have one cataract surgery in each eye in your life and I would not want to introduce anything that even in the faintest of possibilities could create any sort of adverse consequences. I would suggest doing the lift about a month or so after your cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 04, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-you-have-eyelash-lift-two-weeks-before-catarac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-you-have-eyelash-lift-two-weeks-before-catarac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "can-you-tell-me-minimum-corneal-diameter-required-", "title": "Can you tell me the minimum corneal diameter required for IOL implantation?", "question": "My child had cataract from birth. Can you tell me the minimum corneal diameter required for IOL implantation?", "answer": "The decision to implant an IOL (artificial lens to replace they eye’s cloudy lens, or cataract) in an infant with a cataract is complicated. While implantation may be done in normal eyes, placement of an IOL in small eyes is risky because of the risk for glaucoma as well as damage to the cornea . I do not think there is a single corneal diameter to use as a cut-off point for all patients, but typically corneas larger than 9.5 mm in early childhood would seem reasonable candidates for implantation. The use of IOLs during the first year of life, while done infrequently, has increased risks documented by results from the Infant Aphakia Study.", "answer_links": [{"text": "implant an IOL (artificial lens to replace they eye’s cloudy lens, or cataract)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "glaucoma", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-glaucoma"}, {"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Michael X Repka, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9c91065f-d048-4fd2-93c0-b2fefe845c2a", "answered_at": "SEP 01, 2016", "categories": ["Pediatric Cataracts", "Babies and Infants", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/can-you-tell-me-minimum-corneal-diameter-required-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\can-you-tell-me-minimum-corneal-diameter-required-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-astigmatism", "title": "Can you explain the surgery for cataract with astigmatism?", "question": "Can you explain the surgery for cataract with astigmatism ?", "answer": "Cataract is a clouding of the focusing lens of the eye. The cornea is the clear window of the eye through which light must pass first to reach the lens and then proceed on to reach the retina which acts like the film in a camera to capture what we see.\n\nAn astigmatism is an oval-shaped cornea that is normally perfectly round and it causes blurry vision . Most astigmatism is corrected with eyeglasses or contact lenses . Historically, cataract surgery was performed without fixing the pre-existing astigmatism and people wore glasses or contact lenses after cataract surgery to correct their astigmatism.\n\nWe now have two methods of correcting astigmatism simultaneously with cataract surgery and one method after cataract surgery for those who want to maximize the vision of their \"naked\" eyes (not requiring glasses or contact lenses).\n\nLimbal relaxing incisions (LRI) can be performed at the time of surgery to eliminate or reduce astigmatism. LRIs are very small, but very deep, extra incisions that are placed in the cornea at the exact clock hour of the astigmatism in the cornea. LRIs usually heal nicely and can last forever. Because LRIs are made by hand and because each person heals differently, LRIs have a given degree of variability of result in the short term and the long term. There is often an extra charge for LRIs.\n\nA toric intraocular lens corrects astigmatism (in addition to the usual correction for near or distance vision). It must be ordered or inventoried specifically for the degree of astigmatism to be corrected. The lens is implanted inside the eye in a very exact orientation so as to line up the corrective power of the lens in the exact clock hour needed to correct the astigmatism. Toric IOLs usually do a very good job at correcting astigmatism and allow the patient to be less dependent on glasses.\n\nThe third way to correct astigmatism occurs after cataract surgery and after the eye has had time to heal. LASIK or PRK can be performed as an off-label (not an FDA-approved use) method of reducing or eliminating astigmatism. In LASIK and PRK, an Excimer laser is use to reshape the cornea. PRK can be performed sooner than LASIK and is usually more uncomfortable for the first few days. LASIK would require more healing time from the date of the cataract surgery and is much less uncomfortable.\n\nYour ophthalmologist can provide more details specifically tailored to your visual goals prior to making such an important decision.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Jan. 1, 2013.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts"}, {"text": "An astigmatism is an oval-shaped cornea that is normally perfectly round and it causes blurry vision", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}, {"text": "eyeglasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "contact lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "LASIK or PRK", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-refractive-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 02, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-astigmatism", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-astigmatism.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-possible-with-pseudoexfoliation", "title": "Is it possible to have a successful cataract surgery with pseudoexfoliation?", "question": "I have psuedoexfoliation (when flaky dandruff-like deposits peel off the lens inside the eye and potentially block fluid from leaving the eye) and need to have cataract surgery . Is it possible to have a successful surgery with this condition? The ophthalmologist wasn't very encouraging about my problem. I wasn't aware of it until I had an appointment to schedule cataract surgery.", "answer": "Most patients with pseudoexfoliation have no problems with the surgery and if you do, there are corrective actions that can be taken during the surgery to produce a good outcome. If you surgeon does not feel comfortable with such surgery, you are entitled to get a second opinion.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 24, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-possible-with-pseudoexfoliation", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-possible-with-pseudoexfoliation.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-reading-glasses", "title": "Do I need store-bought or prescription reading glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery four years ago and now I need reading glasses. Do I need prescription reading glasses or can I use store-bought reading glasses?", "answer": "Typically, if you can see great at distance without any glasses, then over-the-counter reading glasses (i.e., the ones that you can buy at nearly any pharmacy or store) will be sufficient. They range anywhere from +1.00 D to +3.00 D. In most cases, patients will require +1.25 D for computer use and +2.25 to 2.50 D for reading near. The rule of thumb is that if you want to see things closer, select a higher number like +3.00 D, and if you want to see farther away like at a music stand, choose +1.00 D. This question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Robert F Melendez, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/4c869531-d85b-48ed-9794-9a355dfb0fc9", "answered_at": "SEP 12, 2023", "categories": ["Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-reading-glasses", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-reading-glasses.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-safe-while-sneezing-coughing", "title": "Is cataract surgery safe if I sneeze and cough a lot?", "question": "Is cataract surgery safe with allergic rhinitis? I sneeze and cough a lot.", "answer": "Sneezing and coughing can be very problematic during cataract surgery . You need to address this with your surgeon.\n\nMost cataract surgery is done with some intravenous sedation (medication to help you relax given by injection) which can suppress sneezing and coughing. There are also systemic medications that can be given before surgery to suppress these reflexes. Rarely, if we think there is a likelihood that sneezing and coughing cannot be controlled, we may consider general anesthesia. I have not had a case of allergic rhinitis requiring general anesthesia.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 12, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-safe-while-sneezing-coughing", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-safe-while-sneezing-coughing.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-vision-worse", "title": "Why does my vision seem worse two years after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery two years ago on my right eye but rather than improve my vision it actually seems worse to me. Could there be something wrong with the IOL ?", "answer": "It is unlikely that something is wrong with the IOL. Many factors can decrease vision after cataract surgery. A common finding is a posterior capsule opacity which is essentially a build-up of various proteins on the back side of your new lens implant. This can be cleared in the office with a laser known as a YAG capsulotomy. Another common finding is refractive error that needs to be corrected with glasses . Dry eye syndrome is another common finding that can change vision after cataract surgery. Corneal and retinal diseases should also be ruled out as certain corneal conditions can worsen after cataract surgery (like Fuchs' corneal dystrophy ) and some retinal diseases can progress after cataract surgery such as macular degeneration or macular edema . An ophthalmologist should be able to determine whether any of these findings are present. This question was originally answered on Mar. 10, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "Dry eye syndrome", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/dry-eye"}, {"text": "Fuchs' corneal dystrophy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/fuchs-dystrophy"}, {"text": "macular degeneration", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amd-macular-degeneration"}, {"text": "macular edema", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/macular-edema"}], "answered_by": "William Barry Lee, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6e7ea7d6-fac3-4515-90c3-249b40819804", "answered_at": "SEP 06, 2023", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-vision-worse", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-vision-worse.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataract-surgery-visual-balance-neural-adaptation", "title": "How long should one wait for the brain to adjust to new vision after cataract surgery?", "question": "It’s been five weeks since my cataract surgery in both eyes. I am still struggling to feel visually balanced between both eyes. I’m told I am 20/20 in left dominant eye and 20/25 in right eye. I suspect that I will need a final prescription, as no doubt my astigmatism, although minor, is still in play.\n\nI failed the glare test (vision decreases in bright light conditions) in both eyes as well. As I am under 60, the doctor is suggesting that the capsular opacification (or secondary cataract, when the outer membrane that holds the eye’s natural lens becomes cloudy) is actually occurring faster causing the glare. So YAG (a later procedure to treat the secondary cataract) is in my future.\n\nDoes this all sound normal? Regarding neural adaption (brain adjusting to new vision)—how long should one sit in visual limbo waiting for the brain to catch up?", "answer": "It is not uncommon for a patient to experience new visual sensations and perceptions immediately after cataract surgery in both eyes. Generally speaking, vision of 20/20 in one eye and 20/25 in the fellow eye is a very good result. Opacification of the posterior capsule so early after the cataract surgery is quite uncommon by not rare. I am not able to evaluate the density of the opacification, but I believe that, if your ophthalmologist is recommending treatment, you should go ahead with this simple procedure.\n\nThe timetable for neural adaptation is not something that is the same for everyone. I would assume that by three to six months you will have reached maximum neural adaptation. Your problems seem to dishearten you and I think you should discuss them more fully with your ophthalmologist. This question was originally answered on Mar. 30, 2015.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "SEP 19, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataract-surgery-visual-balance-neural-adaptation", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataract-surgery-visual-balance-neural-adaptation.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "cataracts-light-sensitivity-do-i-need-surgery", "title": "Is my light sensitivity due to cataracts?", "question": "I'm due for cataract surgery soon and my eyes cannot tolerate bright sunlight . Is this due to the cataracts?", "answer": "The answer depends on what you mean by “tolerate.”\n\nIf you mean that sunlight is causing glare or difficulty seeing things, then that is very likely caused by cataracts . If the sunlight is causing pain then another diagnosis may be considered and you should probably discuss these symptoms with your ophthalmologist before the surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "caused by cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "FEB 06, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/cataracts-light-sensitivity-do-i-need-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\cataracts-light-sensitivity-do-i-need-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "competitive-boxing-safe-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I competitively box after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I competitively box after cataract surgery?", "answer": "It would be best to ask your surgeon her opinion based on her specific recommendations. Theoretically, there may be a heightened risk of retinal detachment. Modern incisions in cataract surgery are very sturdy. If boxing is your profession or an important part of your life, I would think you could resume once your eyes are fully healed after the surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 10, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/competitive-boxing-safe-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\competitive-boxing-safe-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "comprehensive-eye-exam-before-surgery", "title": "Why might my exam before surgery seem brief compared to others?", "question": "Is it normal to have a less exhaustive eye exam prior to cataract surgery when compared to previous eye exams for glasses?", "answer": "Anyone having cataract surgery requires a comprehensive exam with the addition of several diagnostic tests. An exam for cataract surgery should be more complete and \"exhaustive\" than an exam for glasses. It is possible that your perception of the exam may not reflect what was accomplished during the visit, but if you feel that your cataract pre-op evaluation was not comprehensive, then it would be good to ask your surgeon so that they can explain the elements that went into your exam.", "answer_links": [{"text": "comprehensive exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "An exam for cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "OCT 04, 2024", "categories": ["Eye Exams", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/comprehensive-eye-exam-before-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\comprehensive-eye-exam-before-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "contact-lens-over-iol-for-blurry-vision", "title": "Is it possible to prescribe and wear a single contact lens over a monofocal intraocular implanted lens to correct blurry near vision that was not corrected by the monofocal lens?", "question": "Is it possible to prescribe and wear a single contact lens over a monofocal intraocular implanted lens to correct blurry near vision that was not corrected by the monofocal lens?", "answer": "Yes, it is quite possible, but it is not possible to predict if you will be happy with the result. There are several variables involved. Some patents adjust quite well whereas others do not. Still, you can certainly try it with no risk.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "OCT 20, 2016", "categories": ["Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/contact-lens-over-iol-for-blurry-vision", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\contact-lens-over-iol-for-blurry-vision.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "contact-lenses-cataract-surgery", "title": "Do I need to stop wearing contact lenses, prior to cataract surgery?", "question": "I was told to stop wearing contact lenses for 2 to 4 weeks before my cataract surgery . Is this correct?", "answer": "Patients need to be out of contact lenses prior to their preoperative measurements for cataract surgery. The length of this time depends on what contact lenses are worn.\n\nThis is needed because contact lenses alter the shape of the cornea, on the outer surface of the eye . When measurements are taken for the intraocular lens (IOL) , it is extremely important for the cornea to be in its natural, unaltered state. The surface measurements are inaccurate if not out of the contact lenses, which leads to the wrong IOL being placed during cataract surgery. Hard lenses should be discontinued for a longer time compared to soft contacts as they take longer for the corneal surface to return to normal. If these instructions are not followed prior to the cataract surgery measurements, your postoperative vision outcome can be disappointing.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "the shape of the cornea, on the outer surface of the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "William Barry Lee, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6e7ea7d6-fac3-4515-90c3-249b40819804", "answered_at": "FEB 01, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/contact-lenses-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\contact-lenses-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "did-my-six-month-glutathione-deficiency-cause-my-c", "title": "Did my six-month glutathione deficiency cause my cataracts?", "question": "I have recently been diagnosed with cataracts . The doctor was surprised because he said I was about 10 years too young for the onset, and that they were just starting to form. In light of recent other illnesses, I may have had a glutathione deficiency for about six months. Could a six-month deficiency be long enough to cause cataracts to start forming?", "answer": "Glutathione deficiency has been associated with cataracts in mice. There is very little evidence that glutathione deficiency causes cataracts in humans, but it certainly is possible theoretically. I am not sure what your doctor means that you are ten years too young for cataracts because cataracts can occur at any age although they are more common as people age. Regardless of the cause, once a cataract is visually significant and is causing difficulties in normal activities, the treatment is to do cataract surgery .", "answer_links": [{"text": "the treatment is to do cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-treatment"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAY 01, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/did-my-six-month-glutathione-deficiency-cause-my-c", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\did-my-six-month-glutathione-deficiency-cause-my-c.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "did-my-traumatic-brain-injury-cause-early-cataract", "title": "Did my traumatic brain injury cause early cataracts?", "question": "Two years ago, I was in a car accident and suffered a traumatic brain injury (TBI). My vision prior to and immediately after the TBI showed little to no change. After a routine eye exam last week my ophthalmologist said I have cataracts forming in both eyes , primarily in my left. I’m 37 with no health issues and I don’t smoke and rarely drink. Is it possible the TBI has started the formation of the cataracts?", "answer": "Unless you hit your eyes, the TBI would not cause a cataract. However, if you were put on high doses of steroid medication after the injury, which is commonly done to help prevent brain swelling/inflammation, this could cause earlier cataract formation. If the cataract change is not affecting your vision, I would not worry about it for now. Have your ophthalmologist check it yearly.\n\n<", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 21, 2018", "categories": ["Injuries", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/did-my-traumatic-brain-injury-cause-early-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\did-my-traumatic-brain-injury-cause-early-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "difference-between-monofocal-multifocal", "title": "What is the difference between monofocal and multifocal lenses?", "question": "What is the difference between monofocal and multifocal lenses?", "answer": "The monofocal lens has one point of focus which is usually set for your distance vision but you would be blurred for near vision. In many cases, one eye can be set for a distance focus and the other eye for a near focus (so called \"monovision\") to reduce the need for reading glasses. This type of lens is usually covered by your health insurance.\n\nMultifocal lenses are considered \"premium lenses\" and patients have to pay additional fees both for the lens and for the surgeons to implant the lens . These lenses have both a near and a distance focus out of the same lens (much like bifocal glasses) so the need for reading glasses is reduced and both eyes see both far and near. There are advantages and potential disadvantages to either type of lens so you need to discuss your options with your surgeon.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Dec. 3, 2010", "answer_links": [{"text": "Multifocal lenses are considered \"premium lenses\"", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/presbyopia-correcting-iols"}, {"text": "the surgeons to implant the lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "There are advantages and potential disadvantages to either type of lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "James J Salz MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/4a347b20-c56f-496e-ac29-5577ff8afaca", "answered_at": "JAN 29, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Diseases", "Conditions"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/difference-between-monofocal-multifocal", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\difference-between-monofocal-multifocal.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "difference-trifocal-versus-multifocal-iol-cataract", "title": "What is the difference between trifocal and multifocal IOLs?", "question": "What is the difference between trifocal and multifocal IOLs? My doctor said the multifocal will give me near, intermediate, and distance correction.", "answer": "Both types of IOLs (intraocular lenses) give you near, intermediate, and distance correction, but the weak point of multifocal IOLs may be intermediate or computer distance. The advantage of a trifocal is that it can have less glare and halo at night time.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Both types of IOLs (intraocular lenses)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUL 21, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/difference-trifocal-versus-multifocal-iol-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\difference-trifocal-versus-multifocal-iol-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "distance-vision-improving-with-age", "title": "I'm 62 years old and my distance vision has improved without spectacles. Why is that?", "question": "I'm 62 years old and my distance vision has improved without spectacles. Why is that?", "answer": "Some call this \"second sight\" which has a simple physiological explanation. As the lens of the eye hardens as we age (the predecessor of frank cataracts ) it changes the way light is \"bent\" as it enters the eye much the way different prescriptions in a pair of glasses do. So if you were hyperopic (needed plus correction) and you start developing pre-cataract changes, your vision may temporarily go through a phase where either the near or distance vision gets better. Unfortunately as you continue to age, this process will make your overall vision worse and you will need cataract surgery . Enjoy it while you have it! This question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 06, 2023", "categories": ["Conditions", "Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/distance-vision-improving-with-age", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\distance-vision-improving-with-age.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "do-eye-exercises-help-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I use eye exercises to expedite healing after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I use eye exercises to expedite healing after cataract surgery? My vision is worse in the operated eye after six days.", "answer": "People may have blurry vision after cataract surgery for a variety of reasons. In many cases the vision improves with time and healing or with corrective lenses (glasses or contact lenses). Unfortunately, there are no eye exercises that will speed up this process. You should discuss your concerns about your vision with your cataract surgeon, who should be able to explain why your vision seems worse if it has not improved by this point. If your vision is actually worsening in the first week after surgery, this could be a sign of a problem so please call your surgeon now to discuss your symptoms.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "NOV 28, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/do-eye-exercises-help-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\do-eye-exercises-help-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "do-i-have-to-stop-taking-ativan-before-cataract-su", "title": "Do I have to stop taking Ativan before cataract surgery?", "question": "Do I have to stop taking Ativan before cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Your doctor will usually give you an anxiety-easing or pain-relieving medication prior to the procedure that is very closely related to Ativan. So I would wait and ask on the day of surgery. Just bring the medicine with you.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 08, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/do-i-have-to-stop-taking-ativan-before-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\do-i-have-to-stop-taking-ativan-before-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "do-iol-manufacturers-each-use-differing-iol-insert", "title": "Do IOL manufacturers each use differing IOL insertion tools?", "question": "Do IOL manufacturers each use differing IOL insertion tools or are they all the same?", "answer": "Each intraocular lens (IOL) has a recommended insertion tool based on the manufacturer as well as the specific type and power of the IOL.", "answer_links": [{"text": "", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "Each intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAY 25, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/do-iol-manufacturers-each-use-differing-iol-insert", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\do-iol-manufacturers-each-use-differing-iol-insert.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "do-you-lose-depth-perception-after-cataract-surger", "title": "Do you lose depth perception after cataract surgery?", "question": "Do you lose depth perception after bilateral cataract surgery? How can an accurate visual acuity exam be performed when the patient has dementia but needs corrective lenses?", "answer": "If cataract surgery is intended to correct distance vision in both eyes, and if one has normal depth perception, things should be fine following surgery. That said, many patients choose to have multifocal lens implants or to do monovision (having one eye set for near vision and the other for distance), and that could influence depth perception for near work. Regardless, details regarding expected outcomes should be discussed before surgery with the ophthalmologist.\n\nAs far as dementia, in some forms patients can still determine what makes them see optimally. If not, the ophthalmologist can objectively determine what would be the optimal optical correction.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "multifocal lens implants", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "NOV 12, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/do-you-lose-depth-perception-after-cataract-surger", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\do-you-lose-depth-perception-after-cataract-surger.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "do-you-need-to-test-covid-before-cataract-surgery", "title": "Do you need to test for COVID before cataract surgery?", "question": "Do you need to test for COVID before cataract surgery ?", "answer": "This policy is created locally by state, city and county health departments. It depends on case rate and severity within a community as well as political considerations by the government. It also may vary from week to week.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 21, 2022", "categories": ["Coronavirus", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/do-you-need-to-test-covid-before-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\do-you-need-to-test-covid-before-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-astigmatism-correcting-cataract-surgery-exten", "title": "Does astigmatism-correcting cataract surgery extend the recovery process?", "question": "If you have limbal relaxing incisions for astigmatism with cataract surgery , does it change the recovery process of the surgery?", "answer": "While a normal cornea has the shape of a slightly peaked dome, similar to the smaller end of an egg, we often talk about the cornea as a round sphere like a basketball. Astigmatism is the name we give to a cornea that looks more like a football than a basketball. For example, if you picture a football lying on a clock face with the long axis running from 3:00 to 9:00, the curvature is steeper in the axis at 12:00 on the clock face and flatter in the axis at 3:00, 90 degrees away. This is called “regular” astigmatism.\n\nThis difference in the curvature produces two or more focus points on the retina which creates blurred vision. Eyeglasses and contact lenses are used to correct astigmatism and can produce excellent vision. There are times when a person might wish to correct his/her astigmatism with surgery to remove this astigmatism and it is common to do this at the time of cataract surgery, either with a toric implant lens or with limbal reading incisions. However, if the axis of astigmatism does not line up to make a perfect cross (perpendicular lines) then it is called “irregular” astigmatism and may require a hard contact lens or corneal surgery to correct.\n\nLimbal relaxing incisions correct regular astigmatism by flattening the overly steep curves in the cornea. The ophthalmologist can make these incisions by hand with a tiny blade or with a laser. Since relaxing incisions are an elective procedure, most insurance programs consider them to be cosmetic in nature and do not cover the added cost of this procedure.\n\nThere are really two different aspects to recovering after cataract surgery: one that deals with the healing of the eye and the other deals with the final clearness of vision. The “recovery” from surgery is not prolonged with the relaxing incisions. There can be a mild scratchy feeling for a few days, but this seldom causes any recovery issue. The final visual sharpness you will have after cataract surgery can take a bit longer with astigmatism-correcting incisions. The cornea takes a little more time to stabilize after relaxing incisions, but this usually happens within a few weeks, depending on the degree of astigmatism.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "Eyeglasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "contact lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens-102"}, {"text": "ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/ophthalmologists"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "DEC 28, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Astigmatism"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-astigmatism-correcting-cataract-surgery-exten", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-astigmatism-correcting-cataract-surgery-exten.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-cataract-surgery-with-nearsightedness-have-hi", "title": "Does cataract surgery with nearsightedness have higher risk of retinal problems?", "question": "I am nearsighted and have a preexisting posterior vitreous detachment (PVD) and floaters in both eyes. Does cataract surgery carry a higher risk of retinal detachment, more PVD, and/or an increase in the floaters?", "answer": "Although cataract surgery does increase your risk for a retinal detachment , this risk is still fairly low, as less than 1% of cataract surgeries lead to retinal detachment.\n\nThe risk is greater if you are young, male, nearsighted (myopia) or if you have not had a posterior vitreous detachment (PVD) . A pre-existing PVD decreases your risk but does not eliminate it.\n\nFloaters normally increase with age and following a PVD. With a pre-existing PVD, cataract surgery may allow the floaters to be seen more clearly but usually will not cause an increase in the number of floaters.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "retinal detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}, {"text": "nearsighted (myopia)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "posterior vitreous detachment (PVD)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-posterior-vitreous-detachment"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "JUL 27, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Torn or Detached Retina"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-cataract-surgery-with-nearsightedness-have-hi", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-cataract-surgery-with-nearsightedness-have-hi.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-distance-vision-change-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can I expect to have similar distance vision without glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am nearsighted with glasses and am considering near vision monofocal IOLs in both eyes . This will allow me to see up close without glasses but continue to wear glasses for distance. Can I expect my distance vision without glasses after cataract surgery to be similar to what it is today?", "answer": "It is very likely you will see better at distance without glasses after cataract surgery . It depends on the severity of your cataracts and the degree of your nearsightedness before surgery.\n\nFor example, if you are -7.00 and after cataract surgery you are -2.50 you will see much better without glasses post-op. If you are -1.50 and end up -2.50 after surgery, you may still see better even with increased nearsightedness because your IOL (artificial intraocular lens) will be clearer than your cataract . It is important to talk with your ophthalmologist prior to surgery to discuss your expectations and visual goals. Your surgeon will be able to best answer your questions based on your current eye exam .", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "than your cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "current eye exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 25, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-distance-vision-change-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-distance-vision-change-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-having-herpes-of-eye-affect-lens-choice-catar", "title": "Does having herpes of the eye affect lens choice for cataract surgery?", "question": "I need surgery after developing cataract from steroid use while treating shingles . I will be taking steroid drops and oral acyclovir for the rest of my life. Does this affect my lens choice? Can I have a multifocal lens ?", "answer": "Fortunately, this issue should not affect your lens choice. If you are deemed to be a good candidate by your ophthalmologist, either a multifocal or an extended depth-of-focus lens could be good choices.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 24, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-having-herpes-of-eye-affect-lens-choice-catar", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-having-herpes-of-eye-affect-lens-choice-catar.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-inflammation-swelling-cause-hazy-vision-glare", "title": "Does inflammation (swelling) cause hazy vision and glare after cataract surgery?", "question": "Does inflammation (swelling) cause hazy vision and glare after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Yes, it can. Inflammation can occasionally be associated with swelling in the macula (small area in back of eye responsible for detailed central vision) . It can also be responsible or associated with clouding and swelling of the cornea (clear front window of the eye) . Even if you don't have swelling of the cornea or macula, inflammation can cause hazy vision and glare. The treatment is to attempt to identify the cause of the inflammation, if one can be found, and treat that and also to treat the inflammation with anti-inflammatory drops.", "answer_links": [{"text": "macula (small area in back of eye responsible for detailed central vision)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/macula-6"}, {"text": "cornea (clear front window of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 07, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-inflammation-swelling-cause-hazy-vision-glare", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-inflammation-swelling-cause-hazy-vision-glare.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-it-make-sense-to-have-both-iols-set-near-comp", "title": "Does it make sense to have both IOLs set for near/computer distance and then wear glasses for driving?", "question": "I have cataracts and wish to have both intraocular lenses set for near and computer distance and then wear glasses for distance and driving as this would seem best for my lifestyle. Is there any disadvantage in having this? At present I am very nearsighted in both eyes and wear gas permeable contact lenses .", "answer": "No disadvantage, but you should consider having your doctor try it in a contact lens first to see how you like it.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 27, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-it-make-sense-to-have-both-iols-set-near-comp", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-it-make-sense-to-have-both-iols-set-near-comp.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-laser-corrected-astigmatism-change-pre-determ", "title": "Does laser-corrected astigmatism change the pre-determined strength of IOL?", "question": "I’m having laser-assisted cataract surgery . I also have mild astigmatism that will be corrected with the femtosecond laser. If the strength of my lenses is based on measurements before the surgery, then after my astigmatism is corrected won’t that change the prescription of the IOL being inserted?", "answer": "Your surgeon knows how to take this into account when ordering the proper power for the intraocular lens.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "OCT 01, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Astigmatism"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-laser-corrected-astigmatism-change-pre-determ", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-laser-corrected-astigmatism-change-pre-determ.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-ophthalmologist-look-fuchs-before-cataract-su", "title": "Does an ophthalmologist look for Fuchs’ before cataract surgery?", "question": "Does an ophthalmologist look for Fuchs’ before cataract surgery?", "answer": "Before cataract surgery , the cornea is evaluated as part of a comprehensive eye exam . Special testing for Fuchs’ dystrophy may include corneal thickness measurements and endothelial cell count. This is not necessarily part of the pre-operative testing unless an abnormality such as guttata (deteriorated endothelial cells, which is a sign of Fuchs’) is found during the exam. It is certainly possible that Fuchs’ dystrophy can exist without it being seen on the exam.\n\nSo, in summary, the cornea is examined for abnormalities but special tests for Fuchs’ may not be done unless there is something on the exam to suspect that diagnosis.\n\nIf you have a family history of Fuchs’ or have special concerns you should let your surgeon know and she might order additional testing. However, if there are not clinical indications for this testing you could be responsible for the cost as it may not be covered by your insurance carrier.", "answer_links": [{"text": "", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "Before cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "comprehensive eye exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "Fuchs’ dystrophy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-fuchs-dystrophy"}, {"text": "endothelial", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/endothelium"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 15, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-ophthalmologist-look-fuchs-before-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-ophthalmologist-look-fuchs-before-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-traumatic-cataract-move-around-like-eye-float", "title": "Does a traumatic cataract move around like eye floaters?", "question": "Does a traumatic cataract move around like eye floaters?", "answer": "The natural lens of one’s eye may become cloudy. This is called a cataract. Blunt force trauma (injury) can cause a cataract. The lens of the eye is held firmly in place by a structure called zonules. The zonules can also be injured in trauma. This can result in the lens being loose and jiggly within the eye. If there is damage to the zonules there are certain precautions and advanced techniques required to manage this during cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "This is called a cataract.", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 18, 2020", "categories": ["Injuries", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-traumatic-cataract-move-around-like-eye-float", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-traumatic-cataract-move-around-like-eye-float.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "does-using-baby-shampoo-cause-cataracts", "title": "Does using baby shampoo to cleanse the eye contribute to the formation of cataracts?", "question": "Does using baby shampoo to cleanse the eye contribute to the formation of cataracts? I have had ophthalmologists disagree on whether using baby shampoo to cleanse the eye is a good practice.", "answer": "Baby shampoo, when used properly, is a great way to clean the external eyelids and eyelashes. I suggest unscented baby shampoo as the chemical that makes the scent can be irritating to some people. Baby shampoo does not cause cataracts , which are clouding of the lens inside the eye. Some caustic chemicals can penetrate the eye and cause serious internal eye damage like cataracts and worse, but baby shampoo is gentle and is not one of them.\n\nThe best way to use baby shampoo to clean the eyelids and eyelashes is to place about half a teaspoon full in a cup or so of warm water (measurements are not exact) and then dip in a washcloth that is not too rough. Gently rub the washcloth back and forth, not up and down, to protect the eyeball from being scratched. Wash off the baby shampoo and dry carefully.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 03, 2022", "categories": ["General Eye Health", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/does-using-baby-shampoo-cause-cataracts", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\does-using-baby-shampoo-cause-cataracts.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "ear-wax-drops-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Will it be a problem if I used ear wax drops in eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "I accidentally put an ear wax removal drop in my eye 3 weeks after cataract surgery . Is this going to cause a major problem? I immediately inserted several eye drops and then flushed with room temperature water.", "answer": "If you feel better it should not cause any long term or permanent issues, but please bring this to the attention of your cataract surgeon. If you still have any discomfort, redness or blurred vision, please see your cataract surgeon immediately.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 13, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/ear-wax-drops-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\ear-wax-drops-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "feeling-lens-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is it normal to feel discomfort in my eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery three weeks ago. My vision is great, however, I continue to have discomfort in this eye. It feels like I have a contact lens in that eye. I feel and see the edges of my lens. It also feels like the lens is floating on a liquid substance. Can you tell me if this is a normal part of the cataract surgery three weeks out?", "answer": "It does take some time to heal after cataract surgery, and people heal differently. However, I would say it is not typical to have a sensation of a contact lens on the eye this long after surgery. You should talk to your surgeon or ophthalmologist about your symptoms. As far as the feeling that you can see the edge of the lens, that can happen after surgery. That sounds like a condition called \"negative dysphotopsia.\" In that case, we think patients are perceiving some glare off the edge of the lens implant . As the eye heals and the capsule holds the lens implant tighter, those symptoms usually resolve. This question was originally answered on Mar. 16, 2015.", "answer_links": [{"text": "lens implant", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "SEP 07, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/feeling-lens-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\feeling-lens-in-eye-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "floaters-risk-after-posterior-capsulotomy", "title": "What is the risk of large floaters after a posterior capsulotomy?", "question": "I have vestibular disorder (malfunction of parts of the brain and inner ear that control balance and eye movements) stemming from right-eye cataract surgery three years ago. Now I need posterior capsulotomy in that eye and am concerned about the risk of large floaters that might make the vestibular problems worse. What is the risk of large floaters (requiring vitrectomy ) after a posterior capsulotomy?", "answer": "Cataract surgery will not affect your vestibular system so I’m not sure what really is going on. However, a laser capsulotomy is normal in most everyone that has cataract surgery and should be quick, painless and rarely leaves you with long term significant floaters. You may notice some floaters in the first week after surgery, which is also normal. Also, there is no good alternative as the membrane will get more opacified and make the vision worse as time goes on.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 21, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/floaters-risk-after-posterior-capsulotomy", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\floaters-risk-after-posterior-capsulotomy.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "glasses-cataracts", "title": "Can stronger glasses suffice until I need cataract surgery?", "question": "I have cataracts but can see well enough now with prescription glasses . As the cataracts advance, can my glasses be made stronger periodically until I decide it is time for surgery? A relative has told me an optometrist will not prescribe increasingly powerful glasses to compensate if the cause of any worsening vision is due to cataracts.", "answer": "As cataracts develop, they often result in a change in the eyeglass prescription. Therefore, at this early stage, new eyeglasses may restore good vision. But as the cataract worsens, a point will be reached where new eyeglasses will not help. At this point, the optometrist may recommend cataract surgery , because new glasses will not correct the vision any longer. Because the eyeglass prescription always changes following cataract surgery, the optometrist would be correct in not prescribing new glasses if the cataracts are advanced enough to warrant surgery.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "David F Chang, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/bb4af357-043b-4e33-a33f-ddbd3977db52", "answered_at": "JAN 17, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/glasses-cataracts", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\glasses-cataracts.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "glasses-one-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Glasses for one eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am severely myopic in both eyes. I’ve worn glasses since age 6 and am now over 65. I just had a monofocal lens put in my dominant/reading eye after cataract surgery . I can't read as I have done for decades. No glasses, with book five inches away from left eye. As I have multiple pairs of glasses (computer/driving/bifocals/progressive) , should I just get a dummy lens put in temporarily into the left/operated upon eye?", "answer": "What you are describing is very common for nearsighted patients after cataract surgery, especially while they are waiting to get cataract surgery in the other eye. You may find placing a blank or \"dummy\" lens over your operated eye causes more trouble than the expense is worth. You probably will be best served getting a pair of +2.50 or +2.75 over- the-counter reading glasses for your up-close work and relying on your operated left eye in the distance until you can get the right eye corrected to a similar level as the left. This question was originally answered on Sep. 08, 2015.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Stephen N Lipsky MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/51c960e5-c79f-4145-bf1f-75ec4e5aeab7", "answered_at": "SEP 19, 2023", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/glasses-one-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\glasses-one-eye-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "gritty-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Can the eye feel gritty after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it possible for the eye to feel gritty or as if there is something in it after cataract surgery?", "answer": "It is not only possible, but expected. There were incisions made into the eye and these often create a gritty feeling. Typically, the feeling lasts for days to weeks, but some people may feel these symptoms months after cataract surgery .\n\nYou may also have you may have dry eyes or eyelid inflammation , which can cause similar symptoms. Your should let your surgeon know and they should be able to address your symptoms.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "You may also have you may have dry eyes", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}, {"text": "eyelid inflammation", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blepharitis"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 05, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/gritty-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\gritty-eye-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "halo-cataract-surgery-multifocal", "title": "How can I reduce halo and glare after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is there any means of reducing or eliminating the halo and glare effects associated with multifocal intraocular lenses ? Driving is hazardous for me now—it is difficult to judge the distance and speed of oncoming vehicles, more so at night.", "answer": "Most patients with multifocal intraocular lenses (IOL) are aware of a slight halo around lights at night. Rarely, these halos can be very annoying or even debilitating.\n\nThere are a few eye conditions, such as posterior capsular opacity (PCO)— treatable with a posterior capsulotomy —that may worsen this symptom. Occasionally, an ocular medication, brimonidine, can be successful as an \"off- label\" treatment for glare and halo. Please discuss your symptoms with your ophthalmologist to see what options are available to you.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Mar. 13, 2013.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "treatable with a posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 05, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/halo-cataract-surgery-multifocal", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\halo-cataract-surgery-multifocal.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-are-my-son-s-cancer-related-cataracts-monitore", "title": "How are my son’s cancer-related cataracts monitored?", "question": "My son has PSC cataracts in both eyes that were latent side effects from cancer treatment. He has problems with night vision/glare and now needs reading glasses. I read that PSC cataracts can change rapidly. What specific tests/imaging should I ask the doctors for to monitor changes and to quantify the size and location of them?", "answer": "Thank you for sharing your information regarding your son and I do hope that he has had a successful course with his cancer treatment.\n\nPCS cataracts (or “posterior subcapsular cataract,” a cataract that forms on the back of the eye’s lens , beneath the capsule that holds the lens in place ) can occur following treatment and usually form after anti-inflammatory steroid use or radiation treatment to areas around the eyes. The cataracts are monitored through vision assessment and there are multiple ways this can be done, depending on the age of the child. If there is a belief that the vision is decreasing, this could be a sign that the cataracts have worsened. The best course is to maintain regular follow-up visits with your ophthalmologist or preferably a pediatric ophthalmologist, as they have special training in vision assessment in children.", "answer_links": [{"text": "eye’s lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "capsule that holds the lens in place", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}, {"text": "maintain regular follow-up visits", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-is-ophthalmologist"}], "answered_by": "Aaron M Miller, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/1d353ee7-10f5-4298-a733-ea4d82f1bfc8", "answered_at": "MAY 03, 2019", "categories": ["Eye Exams", "Cataracts", "Children's Eye Health"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-are-my-son-s-cancer-related-cataracts-monitore", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-are-my-son-s-cancer-related-cataracts-monitore.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-artificial-lens-power-cataract-surgery", "title": "How is lens power determined before cataract surgery?", "question": "When preparing for cataract surgery , how is the lens power or strength determined? Human calculation or a computer? How accurate is it?", "answer": "The most important measurements we take are the length of the eye and the shape (curve) of the cornea (clear dome-shaped window at the front of the eye) . These measurements, plus a few other factors and the features of your chosen intraocular lens , are used in various formulas to choose the right power of lens. These formulas give you and your ophthalmologist a choice of power. The calculations have gotten better and are based on mathematics and population data. They are extremely accurate but not 100%. This is because each eye is unique and may have characteristics that defy the assumptions of the formulas. Sometimes we can anticipate this and sometimes we can’t. There is art and science to this. We don’t always get it exact, but nearly all patients are happy with their vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cornea (clear dome-shaped window at the front of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 26, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-artificial-lens-power-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-artificial-lens-power-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-can-i-have-two-types-of-cataract-in-one-eye", "title": "How can I have two types of cataract in one eye?", "question": "I found out I have two cataracts in one eye: a subcapsular and an oil drop. I didn't even know a person could get two in one eye. Is this rare? How rare are oil drop cataracts? I've been trying to find more information on an oil drop cataract, but there doesn't seem to be as much as the more common types.", "answer": "You will not find oil drop cataract as it is a visual description, not the type of cataract. No one has more than one cataract in their eye. Remember, a cataract is just the lens of your eye that has gotten more dense and cloudier as time passes. It is not a separate growth. Having a subcapsular cataract (a cataract that affects the back of your eye’s natural lens) and an oil drop cataract is just a description of the cataract that is useful only to the surgeon and should not cause you any unnecessary concern.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 14, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-can-i-have-two-types-of-cataract-in-one-eye", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-can-i-have-two-types-of-cataract-in-one-eye.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-can-i-help-elderly-patient-who-doesn-t-want-ca", "title": "How can I help elderly patient who doesn’t want cataract surgery?", "question": "I am a nurse working with the elderly and provide hands-on-care in a long- term care facility. We have a 98-year-old woman who refuses cataract surgery . Are there any tips for our staff to maintain quality of life for her and similar residents? For example, could sunglasses help reduce light sensitivity?", "answer": "The treatment for a cataract is cataract surgery. If a patient refuses cataract surgery or is unable to have cataract surgery for other reasons, the options are very limited. Simply using sunglasses in this type of patient is not likely to enhance quality of life. This situation may be handled by low vision techniques to enhance abilities in the setting of poor vision. These techniques may include reading aids such as special magnifiers and lighting or other devices. It can also include tinted lenses to enhance contrast in certain situations. These interventions are customized based on each patient’s diagnosis and needs. A low vision specialist can help devise a plan.\n\nDepending on her abilities and access to technology, there are also many apps and features available on smartphones and tablets that can help those with low vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "treatment for a cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-treatment"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "sunglasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/sun"}, {"text": "low vision techniques", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/low-vision"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 30, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-can-i-help-elderly-patient-who-doesn-t-want-ca", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-can-i-help-elderly-patient-who-doesn-t-want-ca.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-can-i-keep-cataracts-from-getting-worse", "title": "How can I keep cataracts from getting worse?", "question": "I have been diagnosed with mild to moderate cataract (a clouding of the eye’s lens over time) and was told that I do not need surgery at the moment but to check in a year. How can I prevent progressive increase in my cataracts?", "answer": "Most individuals over age 50 to 60 technically have age-related changes in their lenses that might be termed \"very early cataracts.\"\n\nIn general, prevention is difficult; but the most helpful practice is to avoid ultraviolet light from the sun with sunglasses . Avoid using steroid eye drops unless absolutely necessary. Avoid the rare medications that may be associated with cataract progression. This question was originally answered on March 11, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "avoid ultraviolet light from the sun with sunglasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/sun"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "FEB 20, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-can-i-keep-cataracts-from-getting-worse", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-can-i-keep-cataracts-from-getting-worse.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-can-i-treat-iridonesis-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "How can I treat iridonesis after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery two months ago, and I was left with iridonesis. My iris jiggles constantly. What can be done to solve or reduce this problem?", "answer": "I would have to exactly see what's going on. Do you have visual symptoms from this or is it a cosmetic problem? Also, is the pupil a normal size and does it react properly to light? The treatment would depend on these issues. If the vision is good and the eye is healing well without issues, I would not do anything for this for at least six months or more from the date of surgery. If this becomes a persistent or difficult problem for you, the options range from drops to possible iris suture. Ask your ophthalmologist about the proper treatment.", "answer_links": [{"text": "pupil", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/pupil"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAY 26, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-can-i-treat-iridonesis-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-can-i-treat-iridonesis-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-do-i-treat-my-keratitis-if-i-m-steroid-respond", "title": "How do I treat my keratitis if I’m a steroid responder?", "question": "I’ve had nummular keratitis for three years and am wondering how long it persists. I can't stop prednisolone because it recurs. I’m a steroid responder and now I have cataract as well. What other options do I have?", "answer": "Nummular keratitis describes a pattern of corneal inflammation that is usually caused by a virus like varicella zoster, which causes chicken pox/ shingles , or adenovirus, which causes conjunctivitis (pink eye) .\n\nThe treatment is steroid eye drops, but occasionally it can be difficult to taper them off without the inflammation coming back. Sometimes this is due to the steroids being tapered too early or too quickly. In these cases, I prefer not to start the steroid taper until a few weeks after I feel the inflammation is completely resolved. With each recurrence, I also extend the steroid a bit longer, sometimes waiting a few weeks before tapering to the next step.\n\nOnce someone is down to one steroid drop a day, I may further taper the steroid to every other day, every third day, or every week. If a patient is taking a strong steroid such as difluprenate, I always switch to a weaker strength steroid before stopping. If all of these strategies do not work, I have also tried another anti-inflammatory drop cyclosporin off-label with occasional success.\n\nHowever, even if you need to stay on steroids for successful treatment, that is okay. Inflammation control is always the first priority. Steroids can cause the eye pressure to go up and can also cause cataracts . But elevated eye pressure can be treated, and cataracts can be removed, but inadequately controlled inflammation can lead to more significant consequences.", "answer_links": [{"text": "keratitis", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-keratitis"}, {"text": "inflammation", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/inflammation"}, {"text": "shingles", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/herpes-zoster-shingles"}, {"text": "conjunctivitis (pink eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/pink-eye-conjunctivitis"}, {"text": "eye pressure", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}, {"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Omar R Chaudhary, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/8e0e0d43-5cc4-4c54-be05-971ce84e7afa", "answered_at": "APR 17, 2019", "categories": ["Glaucoma", "Cataracts", "Infections"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-do-i-treat-my-keratitis-if-i-m-steroid-respond", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-do-i-treat-my-keratitis-if-i-m-steroid-respond.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-does-diabetes-cause-cataracts-to-form", "title": "How does diabetes cause cataracts to form?", "question": "How is it that diabetes can cause cataracts to form?", "answer": "Cataracts are significantly more common in those with diabetes . It is believed to result from high glucose (a type of sugar in the blood that the body uses for energy) in the aqueous humor, which is the liquid in front of the lens . The glucose can accelerate the build up of proteins on the lens that lead to cataract. Age, duration of disease, and poorly managed diabetes are linked with cataract progression. Controlling blood sugar may slow the development of cataracts.", "answer_links": [{"text": "diabetes", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/diabetic-eye-disease"}, {"text": "aqueous humor, which is the liquid in front of the lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/aqueous-humor"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 25, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Diabetic Retinopathy"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-does-diabetes-cause-cataracts-to-form", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-does-diabetes-cause-cataracts-to-form.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-far-will-i-see-with-distance-iol-implanted", "title": "How far will I see with a distance IOL implanted?", "question": "What would be my range of focus if I had a distance-only IOL implanted ?", "answer": "Generally, only far away vision—probably 20 feet and beyond. Anything intermediate (computer or speedometer) or near will be out of focus without glasses.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 21, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-far-will-i-see-with-distance-iol-implanted", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-far-will-i-see-with-distance-iol-implanted.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-far-will-i-see-with-my-intraocular-lens", "title": "How far will I see with my intraocular lens set for distance?", "question": "I'm having difficulty finding any information on what the expected distance is with near, mid and far lens implant. I am quite myopic and plan to choose the \"distance\" lens, but have no idea what my vision will be like at various distances. Can I expect to see reasonably well three feet away? Ten feet away, etc.?", "answer": "Your best focus will be only at 10 or more feet away. You will need glasses for close and intermediate vision.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 21, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-far-will-i-see-with-my-intraocular-lens", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-far-will-i-see-with-my-intraocular-lens.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-is-lens-power-determined-before-cataract-surge", "title": "How is lens power determined before cataract surgery?", "question": "When preparing for cataract surgery , how is the lens power or strength determined? Human calculation or a computer? How accurate is it?", "answer": "The most important measurements we take are the length of the eye and the shape (curve) of the cornea (clear dome-shaped window at the front of the eye) . These measurements, plus a few other factors and the features of your chosen intraocular lens , are used in various formulas to choose the right power of lens. These formulas give you and your ophthalmologist a choice of power. The calculations have gotten better and are based on mathematics and population data. They are extremely accurate but not 100%. This is because each eye is unique and may have characteristics that defy the assumptions of the formulas. Sometimes we can anticipate this and sometimes we can’t. There is art and science to this. We don’t always get it exact, but nearly all patients are happy with their vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cornea (clear dome-shaped window at the front of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 26, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-is-lens-power-determined-before-cataract-surge", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-is-lens-power-determined-before-cataract-surge.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-long-do-i-have-to-use-antibiotic-eye-drops-aft", "title": "How long do I have to use the antibiotic eye drops after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery two weeks ago. How long do I have to use the antibiotic eye drops after cataract surgery?", "answer": "Your surgeon should give you instructions on this but two weeks is often enough if there is no sign of infection. Please have your doctor check or call him/her for instructions. This question was originally answered on Jul. 06, 2017.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 08, 2023", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-long-do-i-have-to-use-antibiotic-eye-drops-aft", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-long-do-i-have-to-use-antibiotic-eye-drops-aft.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-long-do-i-have-to-wear-patch-over-my-eye-after", "title": "How long do I have to wear a patch over my eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "How long do I have to wear a patch over my eye after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "At this time, most ophthalmologists may suggest a patch until the day after surgery, but opinions differ and times of patching are judged on a case by case basis.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "MAR 15, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-long-do-i-have-to-wear-patch-over-my-eye-after", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-long-do-i-have-to-wear-patch-over-my-eye-after.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-long-does-second-sight-last", "title": "How long does “second sight” last?", "question": "How long does “second sight” last?", "answer": "\"Second sight\" is defined as the myopia (nearsightedness) that occurs due to cataracts . If you are farsighted , then the cataract-induced nearsightedness may actually improve your distance vision for a time. If you are not farsighted but need glasses to read, then reading may be made easier for a time. However, the cataract, over time, reduces contrast, dulls color perception , and worsens vision overall until most things become blurry. The time it takes to go from second sight to blurry vision varies and depends both on an individual’s vision needs as well as how quickly the cataract progresses. In my experience this phase usually progresses to significant visual loss over a few months to a year or two but may last much longer if an individual's visual needs are not extreme.", "answer_links": [{"text": "myopia (nearsightedness)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "farsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/hyperopia-farsightedness"}, {"text": "dulls color perception", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/colors-look-dull-faded-different"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 29, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-long-does-second-sight-last", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-long-does-second-sight-last.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-long-until-cataracts-develop", "title": "How long does it take for cataracts to develop?", "question": "How long does it take for cataracts to develop?", "answer": "There is no way to predict how rapidly a cataract will develop. There are many kinds of cataracts and they can develop very slowly or progress rapidly. Usually, if one can determine their speed of development in the past few years, an educated guess can be made as to how rapidly they will develop over the next few years. There is no guarantee that the speed of cataract development will not increase or decrease in the future. Your ophthalmologist will be happy to provide you with his best estimate during your comprehensive eye examination. This question was originally answered on Dec. 22, 2011.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 20, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Conditions", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-long-until-cataracts-develop", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-long-until-cataracts-develop.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-often-does-incomplete-removal-of-cataract-occu", "title": "How often does incomplete removal of a cataract occur?", "question": "How often does incomplete removal of a cataract occur?", "answer": "Thankfully it is rare not to be able to remove the entire cataract . However, in cases of traumatic (caused by injury) or dense (mature) cataracts, it is more common for the back capsule of the cataract to be damaged, which can allow pieces of the cataract to float to the back of the eye. Thankfully these pieces can be removed by a retina specialist with a low complication rate.", "answer_links": [{"text": "remove the entire cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 08, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-often-does-incomplete-removal-of-cataract-occu", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-often-does-incomplete-removal-of-cataract-occu.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-serious-is-it-to-have-fold-in-my-intraocular-l", "title": "How serious is it to have a fold in my intraocular lens?", "question": "I had cataract surgery 10 weeks ago and now have been told that my IOL implant has a fold in it. How serious is it? It’s been suggested that laser treatment will help.", "answer": "Based on your description I think it is likely that you have a wrinkle or fold in the posterior capsule and that there is nothing wrong with the intraocular lens (IOL).\n\nWhen the cataract is removed, in most cases, the capsular bag (which is your own tissue that held the cataract in place) is left intact and the IOL is placed into the capsular bag. It is common for the back (posterior) part of this capsule to develop a lack of clarity or folds that can degrade the vision. This is fixed by an outpatient laser procedure called a YAG capsulotomy or posterior capsulotomy . Please ask your ophthalmologist for clarification.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Sept. 21, 2015.", "answer_links": [{"text": "outpatient laser procedure called a YAG capsulotomy or posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "FEB 20, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-serious-is-it-to-have-fold-in-my-intraocular-l", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-serious-is-it-to-have-fold-in-my-intraocular-l.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-soon-after-cataract-surgery-can-you-have-pet-s", "title": "How soon after cataract surgery can you have a PET scan for staging of melanoma?", "question": "How soon after cataract surgery can you have a PET scan (a special imaging test that helps diagnose or measure disease inside the body) for staging of melanoma?", "answer": "A PET scan does not place pressure on the eye, so as soon as you are comfortable, you can have the scan performed.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 12, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-soon-after-cataract-surgery-can-you-have-pet-s", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-soon-after-cataract-surgery-can-you-have-pet-s.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-soon-can-i-take-viagra-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "How soon can I take Viagra after cataract surgery?", "question": "How soon can I take Viagra after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Some surgeons recommend avoiding vigorous activity for a few days after cataract surgery . Please discuss this with your surgeon, who can give you a more detailed answer based on your overall health.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Some surgeons recommend avoiding vigorous activity for a few days after cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/resume-exercise-sports-after-eye-surgery-injury"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 11, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-soon-can-i-take-viagra-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-soon-can-i-take-viagra-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-will-drops-cataract-surgery-affect-myasthenia-", "title": "How will drops for cataract surgery affect myasthenia gravis?", "question": "How will antibiotic eye drops for cataract surgery affect myasthenia gravis? Gatifloxacin is on the do-not-take list, but this what my doctor prescribed.", "answer": "There are no studies that show that the topical use of these antibiotic drops worsens myasthenia gravis (a disorder that causes muscle weakness) . However, the oral form (taken by mouth) of the medication has a better chance of affecting the rest of the body.\n\nSince very small amounts of the drop can be absorbed in the body, there is a theoretical risk of exacerbation. You can ask your surgeon if she can use a different drop. If she asks you to use the Gatifloxacin, you can reduce the risk by keeping your eyes closed and putting pressure in the corner of your eye between the lids and the nasal bridge to block the tear duct . Do this for five minutes after inserting the drops.", "answer_links": [{"text": "myasthenia gravis (a disorder that causes muscle weakness)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-myasthenia-gravis"}, {"text": "tear duct", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/tear-duct"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 22, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-will-drops-cataract-surgery-affect-myasthenia-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-will-drops-cataract-surgery-affect-myasthenia-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "how-would-monovision-affect-binocular-vision-also-", "title": "How would monovision affect binocular vision and also the use of binoculars?", "question": "How would monovision (reading and distance) lenses affect binocular vision and also the use of binoculars?", "answer": "It is not clear whether you are asking about contact lenses or IOLs , but monovision should have little or no effect on binocular vision. With regard to binocular use, as long as you use binoculars that allow you to adjust the power of each eye, it shouldn’t be a problem. But if your binoculars only allow adjustment of one eye and you wear monovision contacts, try taking the contact out in order to balance your vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "contact lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts-list"}, {"text": "IOLs", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 25, 2021", "categories": ["Contacts and Glasses", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-would-monovision-affect-binocular-vision-also-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\how-would-monovision-affect-binocular-vision-also-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "i-can-see-rim-of-my-iol-implant-can-it-be-correcte", "title": "I can see the rim of my IOL implant—can it be corrected?", "question": "I've had an IOL (artificial intraocular lens placed in eye after cataract surgery) in my left eye for over 30 years now. Just started to see the rim of the implant along with blurriness. It’s really bad when driving at night. Do IOLs slide off the eyes? Is there anything that can be done to correct it?", "answer": "While it is uncommon, IOLs can shift in position and this can produce a combination of symptoms including blurriness and glare. Fortunately, your IOL should never slide out of your eye, but if the symptoms become troublesome, there are surgical procedures to reposition and more steadfastly hold an IOL in place. Talking with an experienced cataract surgeon, preferably the one who performed your procedure, would be a good place to begin.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "APR 09, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/i-can-see-rim-of-my-iol-implant-can-it-be-correcte", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\i-can-see-rim-of-my-iol-implant-can-it-be-correcte.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "i-had-iols-put-in-several-years-ago-have-not-had-t", "title": "Is it normal to need glasses several years after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had IOLs put in several years ago and have not had to wear glasses for reading or distance. Now, my vision seems to be changing and my ophthalmologist has recommended glasses. Is this normal?", "answer": "Yes, this can be very normal, depending upon the nature of the glasses prescription. It is not too uncommon for the focusing power of an eye with a lens implant to change a small amount over time. The wearing of glasses as needed would be a wise solution. On rare occasions, a lens implant might twist or otherwise have its shape altered and cause more significant blurring. If this happens, a surgical approach to the problem could be required. Your ophthalmologist can help you understand any such changes.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "DEC 21, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/i-had-iols-put-in-several-years-ago-have-not-had-t", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\i-had-iols-put-in-several-years-ago-have-not-had-t.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "i-have-had-cataract-surgery-just-had-my-eyes-dilat", "title": "I have had cataract surgery and just had my eyes dilated at check-up. Can I use refresh tears after?", "question": "I have had cataract surgery and just had my eyes dilated at check-up. Can I use refresh tears after?", "answer": "Absolutely, tears are fine to use right away.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 04, 2016", "categories": ["Dry Eye", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/i-have-had-cataract-surgery-just-had-my-eyes-dilat", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\i-have-had-cataract-surgery-just-had-my-eyes-dilat.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "i-have-kidney-disease-is-it-safe-to-take-ketorolac", "title": "I have kidney disease. Is it safe to take Ketorolac eye drops after cataract surgery?", "question": "I have kidney disease. Is it safe to take Ketorolac eye drops after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "The amount of the active medication absorbed into the blood stream from a single eye drop or two, even when taken three to four times a day, is so small as to be near zero risk when given to a normal adult. There are eyedrop medications that can be dangerous to small children, or adults if taken in doses larger than directed by the prescribing physician, but Ketorolac eye drops, when taken as directed, are not a danger to your kidney function.\n\nThe body’s absorption of oral (pill, by mouth) Ketorolac is a different story and can be a great risk to your kidney function. I suggest you consult with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAY 26, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/i-have-kidney-disease-is-it-safe-to-take-ketorolac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\i-have-kidney-disease-is-it-safe-to-take-ketorolac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "i-have-posterior-polar-cataract-wondered-whether-p", "title": "I have posterior polar cataract and wondered whether prescription glasses can be helpful in improving my vision through a microscope. PM", "question": "I have a posterior polar cataract (a type of cataract or cloudy lens that people are born with) in my right eye. It makes it very hard to adjust focus while viewing slides through a microscope (I am a medical student). I don’t want to consider surgery since there is a high risk of complications in surgery of posterior polar cataract. Can prescription glasses be helpful in improving my vision through a microscope?", "answer": "It is true that posterior polar cataracts can be riskier to remove than many other types of cataracts. However, it is possible that you also have a refractive error and that your vision in a variety of settings, including microscope use, could be improved with a pair of glasses . A visit with an ophthalmologist should be able to address this question.", "answer_links": [{"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "DEC 12, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/i-have-posterior-polar-cataract-wondered-whether-p", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\i-have-posterior-polar-cataract-wondered-whether-p.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-cataract-is-causing-astigmatism-is-toric-iol-ne", "title": "If a cataract is causing astigmatism, is a Toric IOL necessary?", "question": "If a cataract is causing the astigmatism and the cataract is removed , why would a Toric lens be necessary?", "answer": "Typically, the astigmatism you have with a cataract may come from both the cataract and the cornea . The Toric lens corrects the astigmatism that exists due to the corneal curvature. Your surgeon will know these measurements and make the appropriate recommendation. To your point, though, if there is no corneal astigmatism, then you should not require a Toric intraocular lens.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}, {"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "The Toric lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 04, 2022", "categories": ["Astigmatism", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-cataract-is-causing-astigmatism-is-toric-iol-ne", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-cataract-is-causing-astigmatism-is-toric-iol-ne.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-i-don-t-have-posterior-capsulotomy-procedure-wi", "title": "If I don't have the posterior capsulotomy procedure will my vision get worse?", "question": "If I don't have the posterior capsulotomy procedure will my vision get worse?", "answer": "Posterior capsular opacity (PCO, or “secondary cataract”) occurs in as many as half of patients who have had cataract surgery . PCO is more common with certain lens implants , with certain surgical techniques and with length of time after surgery. The posterior capsule is a living membrane that holds the eye’s natural lens . Lens cells can grow over the capsule after surgery, causing blurred vision and glare from lights. Once it starts, PCO will often worsen, causing your vision to decrease. In this situation, laser posterior capsulotomy is recommended to restore your vision. Fortunately, this laser is quick, painless and usually has a low risk of complications.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "lens implants", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "posterior capsule", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}, {"text": "eye’s natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "laser posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "AUG 12, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-i-don-t-have-posterior-capsulotomy-procedure-wi", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-i-don-t-have-posterior-capsulotomy-procedure-wi.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-i-had-cataract-removed-as-child-who-do-i-see-ab", "title": "If I had a cataract removed as a child, who do I see about having an intraocular lens placed as an adult?", "question": "I had a cataract removed from my right eye when I was 5 years old (20+ years ago). A decision was made at the time of surgery not to place an intraocular lens (IOL implant) into the right eye during surgery as advancements in this field would \"evolve over my lifetime and other options would be available.\" I've worn a soft contact lens in the right eye ever since, with a max power 10+ and had decent peripheral vision. It’s uncomfortable (because of the thickness) and does not provide very good vision. In 2016, I had corneal abrasions twice due to wearing a contact lens in the right eye. I refuse to put a contact lens back into my eye as the abrasions were painful and avoidable. What are my options for this eye? Surgery to place a permanent lens, do nothing, or are there other options? I also do not know who exactly I need to see. Do you know where I could go to seek advice regarding care of an eye after cataract surgery without an IOL?", "answer": "A good cataract specialist who places lens implants should be able to evaluate your condition and make a recommendation about the possibility of a lens implant. There are a number of options for lens implants.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract specialist", "url": "https://secure.aao.org/aao/find-ophthalmologist"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 03, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-i-had-cataract-removed-as-child-who-do-i-see-ab", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-i-had-cataract-removed-as-child-who-do-i-see-ab.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-i-have-one-eye-corrected-near-vision-other-midd", "title": "What if I have one eye corrected for near vision, the other for middle distance vision?", "question": "If I have one eye corrected for near vision and the other for middle distance vision during cataract surgery , will my distance vision be worse than with the nearsighted vision I now have? Should I have one eye for distance instead of middle distance vision?", "answer": "The eye corrected for middle distance and the eye corrected for near will have poor distance vision (far away as in driving). Another option would be an extended depth of focus lens or a multifocal lens rather than compromising either eye by setting them at different distances. Please speak with your ophthalmologist about which option would best suit your unique situation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "multifocal lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 07, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-i-have-one-eye-corrected-near-vision-other-midd", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-i-have-one-eye-corrected-near-vision-other-midd.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-i-m-allergic-to-acrylic-nail-products-could-i-a", "title": "Could I have an allergic reaction to an acrylic IOL?", "question": "I’m allergic to acrylic nail products and am considering cataract surgery . Could I also have a reaction to the acrylic IOLs placed in my eye during the surgery?", "answer": "I am not sure what your allergy to acrylic nail products is exactly. However, there has not been a reported allergic reaction to any of the materials in an acrylic polymer-based intraocular lens . These lenses are inert and do not leak antigens that can cause an allergy.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 24, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-i-m-allergic-to-acrylic-nail-products-could-i-a", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-i-m-allergic-to-acrylic-nail-products-could-i-a.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "if-my-iol-is-scratched-should-i-have-it-replaced", "title": "If my IOL is scratched, should I have it replaced?", "question": "My intraocular lens (or IOL, the artificial lens that replaces the eye’s natural lens during cataract surgery ) was scratched during insertion and needs to be replaced. Is it common to just leave a scratched lens in?", "answer": "If the defect does not affect vision, I would not touch it. If it is causing visual issues, then, by all means have it replaced. This is usually an uneventful procedure.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 05, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/if-my-iol-is-scratched-should-i-have-it-replaced", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\if-my-iol-is-scratched-should-i-have-it-replaced.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "in-cataract-surgery-if-wrong-size-lens-was-implant", "title": "In cataract surgery, if the wrong size lens was implanted, what is the time frame during which the wrong lens be removed and replaced by the correct size safely?", "question": "In cataract surgery , if the wrong size lens was implanted, what is the time frame during which the wrong lens be removed and replaced by the correct size safely?", "answer": "You cannot have the wrong size implant as all implants are about the same size. What you may mean is the implant is the wrong power for correcting your vision. If this is the case, the lens may not even need to be changed as the power can be correct by laser vision correction in many cases. Some surgeons are not comfortable changing out lenses and other will change them out within 6 months of implantation but again, laser vision correction may be the simpler option. Speak to your surgeon about the choices.", "answer_links": [{"text": "implants", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "DEC 27, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/in-cataract-surgery-if-wrong-size-lens-was-implant", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\in-cataract-surgery-if-wrong-size-lens-was-implant.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "iol-close-up-vision", "title": "What's the best IOL to preserve near vision after cataract surgery?", "question": "For a patient with extreme nearsightedness and astigmatism , what is the best lens to implant during cataract surgery to preserve great close-up vision?", "answer": "Almost any brand of IOL can preserve your nearsightedness, if the proper power of lens is selected for you. IOLs may vary in their makeup and configuration, but they all come in a wide range of refractive (focusing) powers. This means that your ophthalmologist can help preserve your myopia by selecting a lens power that works for your desires. Astigmatism can be corrected with a special IOL, the cost of which is not covered by insurances. This lens is called a toric IOL. They have a wide range of astigmatism focusing errors built into them. This lens can be ordered such that it corrects the astigmatism while preserving the near vision you seem to value so much. You and your ophthalmologist can select the IOL that best meets your lifestyle and visual needs during an in-person consultation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Almost any brand of IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "You and your ophthalmologist can select the IOL that best meets your lifestyle and visual needs", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/best-artificial-lens-iol-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "SEP 06, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/iol-close-up-vision", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\iol-close-up-vision.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-anesthesia-used-combined-cataract-glaucoma-surg", "title": "Is anesthesia used for combined cataract and glaucoma surgery?", "question": "Is anesthesia used for combined cataract and glaucoma surgery?", "answer": "is done these days with some combination of topical anesthesia (numbing eye drops or gel) and intravenous sedation.\n\n, some ophthalmologists may also perform an injection around the eye that helps with numbing and temporarily prevents eye movement, however this is up to the individual surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The majority of cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "If inserting a glaucoma stent at the same time", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/combined-cataract-glaucoma-surgery-facts"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "SEP 23, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glaucoma", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-anesthesia-used-combined-cataract-glaucoma-surg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-anesthesia-used-combined-cataract-glaucoma-surg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-cataract-surgery-possible-if-taking-finasteride", "title": "Is cataract surgery possible if taking finasteride?", "question": "Is cataract surgery possible if taking finasteride?", "answer": "Finasteride should not interfere with your surgery.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 22, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-cataract-surgery-possible-if-taking-finasteride", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-cataract-surgery-possible-if-taking-finasteride.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-cataract-surgery-recommended-on-patient-with-hi", "title": "Is cataract surgery recommended on a patient with high IOP?", "question": "Is cataract surgery recommended on a patient with high IOP due to glaucoma ?", "answer": "As a general rule, we try to lower intraocular pressure (IOP) before cataract surgery with medication and laser surgery. If we are unable to control eye pressure, a patient is better served with either a standalone glaucoma surgery or a combined cataract and glaucoma surgery . While it is true that cataract surgery can modestly lower pressure in some patients, uncontrolled IOP requires a more targeted glaucoma procedure than cataract surgery alone.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular pressure (IOP)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "combined cataract and glaucoma surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/combined-cataract-glaucoma-surgery-facts"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "NOV 03, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glaucoma"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-cataract-surgery-recommended-on-patient-with-hi", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-cataract-surgery-recommended-on-patient-with-hi.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-current-measurement-technology-more-predictable", "title": "Is current measurement technology more predictable than using pre- and post-LASIK records for selecting an IOL for cataract surgery?", "question": "Is current measurement technology more predictable than using pre- and post- LASIK records for selecting an IOL for cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Yes, current formulas paired with measurement technology give more accurate IOL powers than pre- and post-LASIK information.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 08, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-current-measurement-technology-more-predictable", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-current-measurement-technology-more-predictable.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-eye-with-stronger-prescription-dominant-eye", "title": "Is the eye with stronger prescription the dominant eye?", "question": "My right eye has always had the stronger prescription for my contact lenses . Does this indicate that my right eye is my dominant eye, and should be the one set for distance during cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Eye dominance is measured separately from prescription. Just the fact that one eye has a stronger prescription does not make it the dominant eye.\n\nMost people have one eye that they use for distance activities (like sighting a gun or looking through a telescope). This is usually the “dominant eye.” Even when both eyes are open, the brain pays more attention what the dominant eye is seeing.\n\nWith contact lenses or with intraocular lenses (after cataract surgery) , some patients choose to have monovision where one eye is set to focus for distance and the other eye is set for reading or computer work. The dominant eye is typically set for distance vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses (after cataract surgery)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": null, "answered_by_url": null, "answered_at": "APR 11, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-eye-with-stronger-prescription-dominant-eye", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-eye-with-stronger-prescription-dominant-eye.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-hair-loss-side-effect-of-avastin-injections-in-", "title": "Is hair loss a side effect of Avastin injections in the eye?", "question": "Is hair loss a side effect of Avastin injections in the eye ? I noticed large amount of hair loss after four treatments.", "answer": "There is no evidence that hair loss is a side effect of Avastin injections.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Paul Sternberg Jr., MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/0d86e7a6-93dd-44e1-a027-981014dfd11f", "answered_at": "JUN 12, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-hair-loss-side-effect-of-avastin-injections-in-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-hair-loss-side-effect-of-avastin-injections-in-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-best-to-select-cataract-surgeon-who-also-doe", "title": "Is it best to select a cataract surgeon who also does LASIK when looking for someone to do post-LASIK cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it best to select a cataract surgeon who also does LASIK when looking for someone to do post-LASIK cataract surgery?", "answer": "When selecting a cataract surgeon, I recommend relying on the recommendations of others—family, friends, etc. It is best to pick the best cataract surgeon as those that do not do LASIK usually have arrangements with other surgeons to perform laser vision correction if necessary. What’s most important is that you select a surgeon who is comfortable with post-LASIK cataract surgery . If you choose a surgeon who does both, that definitely works. But is not a requirement for good surgical results.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 06, 2017", "categories": ["LASIK and Laser Surgery", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-best-to-select-cataract-surgeon-who-also-doe", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-best-to-select-cataract-surgeon-who-also-doe.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-normal-to-need-lower-power-reading-glasses-a", "title": "Is it normal to need lower power reading glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it normal to have a lower reading glasses prescription after cataract surgery ? My eyes are completely healed from the surgery.", "answer": "The reading glasses prescription depends on the power of the lens implant (intraocular lens or IOL) that was placed inside your eye. Your reading glass power is inconsequential. What’s more important is that your reading vision is satisfactory while wearing the glasses.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The reading glasses prescription", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/glasses-contacts-list"}, {"text": "lens implant (intraocular lens or IOL)", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 10, 2021", "categories": ["Contacts and Glasses", "Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-normal-to-need-lower-power-reading-glasses-a", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-normal-to-need-lower-power-reading-glasses-a.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-possible-that-iol-implant-after-cataract-sur", "title": "Is it possible that the IOL implant after cataract surgery would prohibit use of progressive eyeglasses?", "question": "Is it possible that the IOL implant after cataract surgery would prohibit use of progressive eyeglasses (“no-line” glasses that correct vision at more than one distance)?", "answer": "My general answer is that it would be quite unusual. I would tend not to use the word prohibit, and instead say that there could be something about the way the optics of the eye and the lens interact to make the progressive eyeglasses ineffective or less comfortable. Unfortunately, it is difficult to answer your question without knowing more about the implanted lens and your refractive outcome.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "SEP 28, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-possible-that-iol-implant-after-cataract-sur", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-possible-that-iol-implant-after-cataract-sur.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-possible-to-get-posterior-capsular-opacifica", "title": "Is it possible to get posterior capsular opacification without having cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it possible to get posterior capsular opacification without having cataract surgery?", "answer": "No, this only develops after cataract surgery . One can develop posterior subcapsular cataract that clouds the center part of the lens in front of the posterior capsule of the lens . This is more common in young people with cataract, or cataract resulting from chronic steroid use, or from trauma to the eye.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "capsule of the lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 05, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-possible-to-get-posterior-capsular-opacifica", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-possible-to-get-posterior-capsular-opacifica.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-possible-to-have-successful-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is it possible to have successful cataract surgery if you have had radial keratotomy?", "question": "Is it possible to have successful cataract surgery on patients who have had radial keratotomy (prior to LASIK being an option)?", "answer": "People who have had radial keratotomy (or RK, a refractive surgery similar to LASIK that is no longer done) can have very successful results after cataract surgery. However, radial keratotomy reshapes the cornea in ways that can continue to change over many years, and even from day to day, causing fluctuation of vision. This can make it more difficult to target a precise glasses prescription after surgery, and your glasses prescription may continue to change over time. Fortunately, most RK patients can achieve good vision with glasses or contact lenses after cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "glasses prescription", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "contact lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens-102"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "JUL 24, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-possible-to-have-successful-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-possible-to-have-successful-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-possible-to-have-two-different-types-of-cata", "title": "Is it possible to have two different types of cataracts?", "question": "Is it possible to have one type of cataract in one eye and another in the fellow eye?", "answer": "Yes it’s possible and not uncommon. Cataracts differ in appearance and where they form on the eye’s lens . People can have a combination of cataract types while others will only have one.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "the eye’s lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "DEC 12, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-possible-to-have-two-different-types-of-cata", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-possible-to-have-two-different-types-of-cata.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-getting-", "title": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery after getting permanent makeup?", "question": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery after getting permanent makeup?", "answer": "Permanent eye makeup will have no bearing on future cataract surgery .", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 16, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-getting-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-getting-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-having-l", "title": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery after having laser and freezing treatment on my retina?", "question": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery after having laser and freezing treatment on my retina?", "answer": "Cataract surgery is a relatively safe operation with an extremely low complication rate. There are some ocular, medical and surgical conditions that can add to this very low risk. Previous retinal surgery might indicate an underlying weakness in the retina —such as high nearsightedness and previous eye injury —that could add to the risk of cataract surgery. However, areas of the retina that have been fully treated are usually the least likely areas to cause any of these complications.\n\nPrior to your cataract surgery, your ophthalmologist will fully and carefully examine your eye, including the retina, to prepare accordingly and provide you a safe operation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "nearsightedness", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "eye injury", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/injuries"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "NOV 15, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-having-l", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-after-having-l.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-absc", "title": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery if I have an abscessed tooth?", "question": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery if I have an abscessed tooth?", "answer": "As with any surgery, any active infection should be treated prior to cataract removal.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 17, 2018", "categories": ["Infections", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-absc", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-i-have-absc.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-you-have-ny", "title": "Is it safe to have cataract surgery if you have nystagmus?", "question": "I am 59 years old and have congenital nystagmus (involuntary, rapid movement of the eyes) . Now I have developed cataract in both eyes and need surgery. How would this surgery be performed while my eyeballs are moving? My ophthalmologist surgeon thinks he can handle it and wants to do it in local anesthesia. Would it be safe? Is there a safer way?", "answer": "I have performed cataract surgery on a number of patients with nystagmus, and I’ve never found it to be a particularly challenging problem. It is relatively straightforward to immobilize the eye with a second instrument while making incisions. Once the incisions are complete, having the surgical instruments in the eye dampens the nystagmus, and makes the procedure relatively routine.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "SEP 30, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-you-have-ny", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-have-cataract-surgery-if-you-have-ny.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-have-mri-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is it safe to have an MRI after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it safe to have an MRI body scan if I had cataract surgery two years ago?", "answer": "Yes, it's safe. However, any interior magnetic items (such as a pacemaker or inner ear implant) should always be discussed with your doctor before an MRI. This question was originally answered on Jul. 26, 2017.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "SEP 11, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-have-mri-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-have-mri-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-safe-to-use-flaxseed-eye-mask-after-cataract", "title": "Is it safe to use flaxseed eye mask after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it safe to use flaxseed eye mask for dry eye after cataract surgery?", "answer": "I do not recommend this treatment. If you have dry eye the treatments may include various types of drops and punctual plugs . If you have eyelid inflammation such as blepharitis , eyelid scrubs and warm compresses may also help. Warm compresses can be applied in a number of ways. Microwaveable flaxseed eye mask is not going to be any better than applying a warm facecloth to the eye. That being said, check with your eye surgeon before doing anything not specifically described in your post-op instructions during the early months after cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "If you have dry eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}, {"text": "punctual plugs", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/punctal-plugs"}, {"text": "blepharitis", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blepharitis"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 25, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Dry Eye"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-safe-to-use-flaxseed-eye-mask-after-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-safe-to-use-flaxseed-eye-mask-after-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-true-that-after-cataract-surgery-my-new-eyeg", "title": "Is it true that after cataract surgery my new eyeglasses prescription will never change?", "question": "Is it true that after cataract surgery my new eyeglasses prescription will never change?", "answer": "Assuming healthy eyes, you may have slight changes as you age, but no large changes anymore.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 25, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-true-that-after-cataract-surgery-my-new-eyeg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-true-that-after-cataract-surgery-my-new-eyeg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-it-true-that-i-should-expect-my-vision-to-chang", "title": "Is it true that I should expect my vision to change after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it true that I should expect my vision to change after cataract surgery ? Even if I choose the standard lens?", "answer": "In a healthy eye, the sharpness of vision is a function of several features: the front surface curvature (cornea) , the focusing power of the lens , and the length of the eyeball. When one of these is less than perfect for sharp vision, eyeglasses or contact lenses are prescribed to sharpen the vision. Cataract surgery destroys the lens of the eye and a replacement artificial lens is placed inside the eye. It almost always lasts forever. The focusing power of that artificial lens can be calculated, within a small degree of error, to be whatever you and your ophthalmologist desire the visual outcome to be. Therefore, if you want to have excellent distance vision you may make that choice. If you prefer to have excellent near vision you may choose that option. If you wish to have the same vision you currently have, you may make that choice. All of this depends on several factors, one of which is the focusing power of the fellow eye as they must be kept reasonably close to the same so as not to make an imbalance. I fear I may have oversimplified this issue for the purposes of this setting and strongly urge you to discuss your visual outcome preferences fully with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "the front surface curvature (cornea)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "replacement artificial lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "FEB 24, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-it-true-that-i-should-expect-my-vision-to-chang", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-it-true-that-i-should-expect-my-vision-to-chang.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-laser-surgery-better-my-cataract-type", "title": "Is laser surgery better for my cataract type?", "question": "For surgery fixing a posterior subcapsular cataract, does laser cataract surgery offer benefits over traditional cataract surgery?", "answer": "Laser assisted cataract surgery and conventional cataract surgery are highly successful methods for treating, generally, all types of cataracts. Studies suggest that clinical outcomes are no different when comparing different surgical approaches. Speak with your ophthalmologist about what approach would be best for you.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAY 11, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-laser-surgery-better-my-cataract-type", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-laser-surgery-better-my-cataract-type.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-midazolam-good-anesthetic-to-use-during-catarac", "title": "Is midazolam a good anesthetic to use during cataract surgery?", "question": "Is midazolam a good anesthetic to use during cataract surgery?", "answer": "The choice of anesthetic or sedative to use during cataract surgery will vary, depending on preferences of the surgeon and anesthesiologist. Of course, the medical issues of the patient and the patient preferences also are important. Midazolam is not an anesthetic but rather a benzodiazepine sedative. Personally, I think midazolam is often a good option to use for cataract surgery, but there are many options available.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Devin A Harrison, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/eace7ac1-cdd0-40af-8b3d-e2696585f26e", "answered_at": "JUN 03, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-midazolam-good-anesthetic-to-use-during-catarac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-midazolam-good-anesthetic-to-use-during-catarac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-monovision-option-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is monovision an option for me after cataract surgery on my second eye?", "question": "Three years ago, at age 63, I had cataract surgery on my non-dominant right eye, with the intraocular lens set for distance vision, and incisions to address some astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea) . I have been nearsighted all my life, in glasses since age 13, and have worn single-vision glasses since the right eye surgery to sharpen my right eye to 20/20 distance. My dominant left eye cataract now needs to be addressed. From what I have read about monovision, the proper set-up is that the dominant eye is set to distance. Since my non-dominant right eye has already been set to distance, is monovision a viable option for me? Also, if I were to go with monovision versus both eyes set to distance, how will my depth perception be affected, especially driving at night?", "answer": "Monovision would not be recommended for your situation for two reasons: Near vision in the dominant eye and distance in the non-dominant eye can be visually confusing and, yes, can affect depth perception. Also, if you have never tried monovision in contact lenses when you were younger, I never recommend monovision, as most do not adapt well to it without previous experience. Nothing is wrong with setting both eyes for distance and wearing some reading glasses. Please discuss your options with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Monovision", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 22, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-monovision-option-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-monovision-option-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-mri-safe-one-week-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is MRI safe one week after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is it safe to have an MRI one week after cataract surgery?", "answer": "There is no problem having an MRI solely due to recent or not so recent cataract surgery . So, yes, one week after cataract surgery does not make an MRI exam less safe.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 11, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-mri-safe-one-week-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-mri-safe-one-week-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-multifocal-iol-after-cataract-surgery-option-if", "title": "Is a multifocal IOL after cataract surgery an option if you have nystagmus?", "question": "My husband has nystagmus (involuntary movement of the eyes) and needs cataract surgery . Is a multifocal lens an option with nystagmus?", "answer": "Multifocal lens implants are reserved for eyes with normal optical systems meaning normal muscle function, normal tear layer (area above the cornea that keeps the eye lubricated), normal cornea (clear, front window of the eye) , and normal retina (light sensitive tissue lining the back of the eye) . Nystagmus involves abnormal muscle function so a multifocal lens implant should not be used in this situation and both eyes should either be set for distance vision or near vision. Monovision (one eye set for near vision and the other for distance vision) is also not an option with nystagmus. If distance correction is decided, then glasses will be needed for near vision. Alternatively, both eyes can be set at near vision meaning glasses will need to be worn for distance.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Multifocal lens implants", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "muscle", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-muscles"}, {"text": "normal tear layer", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/tear-film-3"}, {"text": "cornea (clear, front window of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "retina (light sensitive tissue lining the back of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "William Barry Lee, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6e7ea7d6-fac3-4515-90c3-249b40819804", "answered_at": "APR 17, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-multifocal-iol-after-cataract-surgery-option-if", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-multifocal-iol-after-cataract-surgery-option-if.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-multifocal-iol-safe-use-uncomplicated-diabetes", "title": "Is a multifocal IOL safe for use if you have uncomplicated diabetes?", "question": "Is a multifocal IOL safe/recommended for use if you have uncomplicated diabetes ?", "answer": "Yes, as long as you have no diabetic retinopathy . Be sure to confirm with your ophthalmologist after you have had a complete dilated eye exam that the diabetes has not affected your vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "diabetic retinopathy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-diabetic-retinopathy"}, {"text": "dilated eye exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/drugs/dilating-eyedrops"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 22, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Diabetic Retinopathy"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-multifocal-iol-safe-use-uncomplicated-diabetes", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-multifocal-iol-safe-use-uncomplicated-diabetes.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-my-child-s-cataract-related-to-her-lyme-disease", "title": "Is my child’s cataract related to her Lyme disease?", "question": "My daughter, who is 6 years old, was recently diagnosed with a cataract . She had some blood work done, and her ANA test (a blood test that helps diagnose autoimmune disease) was positive. We did a second round of blood work to test for Lyme, and that is positive as well. Is this cataract directly related to the Lyme disease?", "answer": "There is no way to give a true answer to this, as most with Lyme disease or autoimmune disease (goes with the ANA) do not necessarily develop early cataracts. However, if she has been on chronic steroid treatment, this could lead to early cataract. A pediatric ophthalmologist would be best to follow up with in regard to these issues.", "answer_links": [{"text": "pediatric ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/ophthalmology-subspecialists"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 11, 2018", "categories": ["Children's Eye Health", "Pediatric Cataracts", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-my-child-s-cataract-related-to-her-lyme-disease", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-my-child-s-cataract-related-to-her-lyme-disease.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-pupil-size-factor-in-lens-choice-cataract-surge", "title": "Is pupil size a factor in lens choice for cataract surgery?", "question": "Is pupil size a consideration when choosing a lens for cataract surgery?", "answer": "may be a consideration when choosing\n\nbefore\n\n. The Light Adjustable Lens (LAL) requires at least a 7 mm dilated pupil, so the power can be adjusted after surgical healing. Pupil size can also affect the performance of multifocal IOLs. A too small pupil may decrease the sharpness of near and intermediate vision, while a bigger pupil may cause problems with glare and distance vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Pupil size", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/anatomy/pupil"}, {"text": "certain types of intraocular lenses (IOLs)", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Odalys Mendoza, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c96ab28c-526c-4860-abe5-61b1de5a9641", "answered_at": "JAN 23, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-pupil-size-factor-in-lens-choice-cataract-surge", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-pupil-size-factor-in-lens-choice-cataract-surge.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-refractive-testing-before-after-cataract-surger", "title": "Is refractive testing before and after cataract surgery necessary if you’re using a monofocal lens?", "question": "Is pre- and post-refractive testing necessary for cataract surgery when you are using a standard Medicare-covered lens?", "answer": "Yes, the pre-tests are to check the health of the eye as well as taking the corneal measurements, which are used to calculate the lens implant power. The testing after surgery is for deciding on what glasses , if any, are needed after surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "corneal", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "lens implant", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 05, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Eye Exams"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-refractive-testing-before-after-cataract-surger", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-refractive-testing-before-after-cataract-surger.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-there-another-steroid-that-by-brother-can-take-", "title": "Is there another steroid that my brother can take after cataract surgery that doesn't have preservatives?", "question": "My brother had cataract surgery . Immediately following surgery his vision improved markedly, then got increasingly worse. The doctor said he has a sensitivity to the preservatives in prednisolone that is causing worsening vision, eye pain, headaches, but he needs the prednisolone. My brother can't take the side effects anymore and wants to quit the prednisolone. Is there another steroid he can take that doesn't have preservatives?", "answer": "There is no commercially available non-preserved steroid, however it is possible that a compounding pharmacy can make one for you. However, there are several different types of commercially available steroids and if your brother absolutely requires a steroid for inflammation after cataract surgery perhaps your ophthalmologist can try a different one.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 13, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-there-another-steroid-that-by-brother-can-take-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-there-another-steroid-that-by-brother-can-take-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-there-cure-mydriasis-dilated-pupils", "title": "Is there a cure for mydriasis (dilated pupils)?", "question": "Is there a cure for mydriasis (dilated pupils )? I have lived most of my life with pupils that are abnormally huge and take up most of my iris . In normal lighting, they're huge, but outside, they're able to respond to light accordingly. This condition is very embarrassing because it leads people to ask the question, \"Are you on drugs?\"", "answer": "You are lucky that your pupils are not paralyzed in the open position. Therefore, they apparently are able to constrict (narrow or become smaller) with light input. There is a very effective drug which can constrict pupils which you might consider. This drug is an ancient one in ophthalmology called Pilocarpine. It is used to treat the elevated pressure of glaucoma , but in young persons also affects focusing and so it has fallen out of favor. However, in low doses, at about the level of 1/2 to 1/4 percent, it can bring down the pupils with little effect on the focusing. Two problems: It is not a cure and will need to be applied daily and secondly pharmacies do not regularly stock this, and when available, is usually in the 2% concentrations so you would need a compounding pharmacy to prepare the more diluted (less powerful) solution. A few bottles prepared this way might help you out if you use it only prior to potentially embarrassing social situations. It is also exceptionally stable so if you get several bottles prepared this way, they can be stored in the refrigerator or even in the freezer and be kept for many years.", "answer_links": [{"text": "glaucoma", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-glaucoma"}], "answered_by": "Richard E Bensinger MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6ba9cec3-5d75-463d-a97b-f0d9c0d6a8a1", "answered_at": "DEC 13, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Eye Exams"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-there-cure-mydriasis-dilated-pupils", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-there-cure-mydriasis-dilated-pupils.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-there-treatment-available-starbursts", "title": "Is there treatment available for starbursts?", "question": "I had a light adjustable lens (LAL) implanted in one eye 4 months ago. After YAG treatment a month later, I developed prominent starbursts around lights and it has been persistent ever since. Now, with the lens power locked in, I have good vision. But is there treatment available for the starbursts?", "answer": "I would have your ophthalmologists take a thorough look during a dilated eye exam . Sometimes, simply making the YAG laser opening larger can improve these symptoms.", "answer_links": [{"text": "dilated eye exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/drugs/dilating-eyedrops"}, {"text": "YAG laser opening", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": null, "answered_by_url": null, "answered_at": "NOV 07, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-there-treatment-available-starbursts", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-there-treatment-available-starbursts.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-vision-test-required-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is the refraction vision test required after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is the refraction vision test required after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "It is not required but is usually performed in the first two to three weeks after surgery. It is not covered by insurance, so if the vision is close to 20/20, it does not have to be performed.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 19, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-vision-test-required-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-vision-test-required-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-vitrectomy-surgery-riskier-after-having-catarac", "title": "Is vitrectomy surgery riskier after having cataract surgery?", "question": "Is vitrectomy surgery riskier after having cataract surgery?", "answer": "risks typically include infection,\n\nand/or\n\n, bleeding, decreased vision, and needing more or additional surgery.\n\ntypically does not increase the risks of vitrectomy surgery.\n\nIt is important to have a\n\nto evaluate the health of your eyes and to discuss the risks and benefits of vitrectomy surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Vitrectomy surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-vitrectomy"}, {"text": "retinal tear", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-torn-retina"}, {"text": "detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}, {"text": "Prior cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "complete eye exam by your ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}], "answered_by": "Nora Khatib, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/65611fdf-e347-49bc-8c49-9fedc116e7c2", "answered_at": "SEP 16, 2022", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-vitrectomy-surgery-riskier-after-having-catarac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-vitrectomy-surgery-riskier-after-having-catarac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "is-yag-capsulotomy-safe-with-eds", "title": "Is YAG capsulotomy safe with EDS?", "question": "Is YAG capsulotomy safe with hypermobile EDS (or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, a disease that affects connective tissue)?", "answer": "If the lens implant (intraocular lens) is stable there is no reason a YAG capsulotomy—a laser treatment needed for some people after cataract surgery—cannot be done.", "answer_links": [{"text": "lens implant (intraocular lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Michael X Repka, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9c91065f-d048-4fd2-93c0-b2fefe845c2a", "answered_at": "JUN 25, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/is-yag-capsulotomy-safe-with-eds", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\is-yag-capsulotomy-safe-with-eds.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "laser-cataract-surgery-swelling-macular-pucker", "title": "Is laser cataract surgery a risk for swelling with existing macular pucker?", "question": "Is laser-assisted cataract surgery a risk for macular swelling with a macular pucker?", "answer": "The laser can be used to soften the cataract before it is removed, decreasing the amount of energy required to break up and remove the cataract. The laser allows for more precise placement of the incisions made in the cornea and lens , which can be helpful with more advanced implant lenses (toric or multifocal IOLs) . Both laser-assisted and standard cataract surgery have a low risk of cystoid macular edema (swelling) . Your macular pucker (also called epiretinal membrane) may increase the risk of this complication with either procedure. Your surgeon knows your specific situation and can better explain your risk of this problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "implant lenses (toric or multifocal IOLs)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "macular edema (swelling)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-macular-edema"}, {"text": "macular pucker", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-macular-pucker"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "NOV 28, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/laser-cataract-surgery-swelling-macular-pucker", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\laser-cataract-surgery-swelling-macular-pucker.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "lasik-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Will LASIK help my vision after cataract surgery?", "question": "within the last year. Is it possible to have LASIK surgery now to reduce my dependence on glasses? I have astigmatism in both eyes.", "answer": "Depending on the type and amount of correction and the health of your corneas, LASIK is certainly a possibility . Schedule a discussion with your surgeon who can identify the best strategy to meet your visual goals given your eye health.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK is certainly a possibility", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 28, 2023", "categories": ["LASIK and Laser Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/lasik-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\lasik-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "lasik-with-cataracts", "title": "Should you have LASIK if you have cataracts?", "question": "Should you have LASIK if you have cataracts ?", "answer": "LASIK surgery is not advised if cataracts are affecting your vision. Moreover, having any amount of cataract means that the good vision gained from LASIK may be short lived as the cataract will continue to grow and eventually change your vision. It is actually common for LASIK to be done after cataract surgery to fine-tune the patient’s vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "LASIK surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 10, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "LASIK and Laser Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/lasik-with-cataracts", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\lasik-with-cataracts.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "lazy-eye-cured-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why is my lazy eye gone after cataract surgery?", "question": "In 2018 I developed a lazy eye turning in. I just had cataract and astigmatism surgery. My eye is now normal and straight. What happened? I don’t need prism or glasses to see anymore.", "answer": "It’s hard to know for sure what lead to this improvement. But if a cataract reduces vision significantly, surgery to remove it can also improve the strabismus as it is easier for the brain to hold the images from each eye together.", "answer_links": [{"text": "But if a cataract reduces vision significantly, surgery to remove it", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "the strabismus", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/strabismus-in-children"}], "answered_by": "Michael X Repka, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9c91065f-d048-4fd2-93c0-b2fefe845c2a", "answered_at": "JUN 17, 2024", "categories": ["Amblyopia, Strabismus and Lazy Eye", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/lazy-eye-cured-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\lazy-eye-cured-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "light-adjustable-lens-after-macular-pucker-surgery", "title": "Is the light-adjustable lens an option if I had surgery for macular pucker 5 years ago?", "question": "Is the light-adjustable lens an option if I had surgery for macular pucker 5 years ago?", "answer": "Yes, it’s actually a good idea. Because after cataract surgery , your surgeon adjusts the power of the light-adjustable lens to achieve the best possible vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Because after cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "power of the light-adjustable lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 13, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/light-adjustable-lens-after-macular-pucker-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\light-adjustable-lens-after-macular-pucker-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "nauseous-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why am I nauseous after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery with a monofocal lens implant placed in my left eye three weeks ago. Since then I have been disoriented and nauseous. My right eye is almost 20/20 and I have not done surgery in that eye yet. I had to get stronger reading glasses after the surgery. What is making me so nauseous?", "answer": "The difference in correction from the distance eye to the now near eye may be a bit much for you to handle — about two diopters is all that most can tolerate. See where you are with your ophthalmologist and if there is too much difference, consider LASIK to bring the eyes a bit closer together (less nearsighted in the monofocal IOL near eye).\n\nThis question was originally answered on Mar. 10, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "nearsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 22, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/nauseous-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\nauseous-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "near-vision-with-distance-iol-cataract-surgery", "title": "If I have an IOL set for distance, will my near vision be worse after surgery?", "question": "If I have a monofocal IOL set for distance, will my near vision be worse than it was before cataract surgery?", "answer": "Yes. The only reason you have good near vision in that eye now is you have some nearsightedness (myopia) . This will be gone after your cataract surgery , and you will require readers.\n\nAn alternative–if you are willing to pay out-of-pocket–is to get a more advanced IOL that focuses at both near and far distances .", "answer_links": [{"text": "you have some nearsightedness (myopia)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "a more advanced IOL that focuses at both near and far distances", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/presbyopia-correcting-iols"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 31, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/near-vision-with-distance-iol-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\near-vision-with-distance-iol-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-1-17-2025-5-04-28-pm", "title": "Can I see another cataract surgeon for my other eye?", "question": "I had a cataract removed from my right eye , but I don’t want to use the same surgeon for the other eye. Can I go to a different surgeon, and if so, which records do I need to provide?", "answer": "In most cases, where the surgery on the first eye was standard or uncomplicated , the new surgeon would not need much from the old record. It would be ideal to have the power and model of the intraocular lens (IOL) used in the right eye . If you experienced any complicating issues—either during the surgery or afterwards-- the new surgeon may want to know the details, and in that case, the entire record would be helpful.\n\nYour new surgeon can decide what they might need from you—aside from the IOL and its power--after learning the details of your first procedure.", "answer_links": [{"text": "In most cases, where the surgery on the first eye was standard or uncomplicated", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "the power and model of the intraocular lens (IOL) used in the right eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 17, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-1-17-2025-5-04-28-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-1-17-2025-5-04-28-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-1-21-2025-5-57-12-pm", "title": "How soon can I have cataract surgery with a PVD?", "question": "I just developed a PVD and see floaters and flashes . How long should I wait to have cataract surgery with less chance of complications?", "answer": "After an uncomplicated posterior vitreous detachment (PVD), you can have cataract surgery as soon as your schedule allows without an increase in risk. However, please consult your cataract surgeon to see if they have any specific rules.", "answer_links": [{"text": "you can have cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 21, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-1-21-2025-5-57-12-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-1-21-2025-5-57-12-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-1-25-2023-11-56-53-am", "title": "Can a retina examination be done if there is a cataract?", "question": "Can a retina examination be done if there is a cataract?", "answer": "A cataract, or cloudy lens, usually obstructs the patient’s vision , but as it sits in front of the retina , it can also obstruct your ophthalmologist’s view during a retinal exam. The more advanced the cataract is, the more limited the retinal examination will be and the less your ophthalmologist can see during a regular eye exam.\n\nThere are other imaging tools to perform a retinal exam on a patient with a cataract, such as OCT (optical coherence tomography) imaging and ocular ultrasound. They may or may not be necessary depending on how advanced the cataract is, and your ophthalmologist will let you know following your dilated eye exam .", "answer_links": [{"text": "A cataract, or cloudy lens, usually obstructs the patient’s vision", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "OCT (optical coherence tomography) imaging", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-optical-coherence-tomography"}, {"text": "dilated eye exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/drugs/dilating-eyedrops"}], "answered_by": "Nora Khatib, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/65611fdf-e347-49bc-8c49-9fedc116e7c2", "answered_at": "JAN 25, 2023", "categories": ["Eye Exams", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-1-25-2023-11-56-53-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-1-25-2023-11-56-53-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-1-8-2025-6-49-59-pm", "title": "Can multifocal IOLs be used with strabismus?", "question": "Can multifocal IOLs be used with strabismus?", "answer": "I would say it is best to avoid a multifocal IOL (intraocular lens) with strabismus (misaligned or crossed eyes) . This could be a problem because sometimes correcting the patient’s vision with an IOL can make the patient see double if their eyes are still misaligned after cataract surgery. If you end up needing strabismus surgery, it could make that procedure more complicated as well.\n\nPlease consult with both your cataract surgeon and your strabismus specialist so they can help you choose the IOL that is right for your specific situation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "multifocal IOL (intraocular lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "strabismus (misaligned or crossed eyes)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-strabismus"}, {"text": "make the patient see double", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/double-vision-2"}, {"text": "cataract surgery.", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Stacey J Kruger, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/46499a26-0d8d-4f05-a276-f12aa14ddd42", "answered_at": "JAN 08, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-1-8-2025-6-49-59-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-1-8-2025-6-49-59-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-11-14-2023-9-16-28-pm", "title": "Will my IOL aggravate my vertigo?", "question": "I have severe vertigo and vestibular disorder and will need cataract surgery in the future. With the knowledge that only a small change to my eyeglass prescription worsens my vertigo, should I expect the IOL to do the same?", "answer": "I think cataract surgery should not affect your vertigo. I would be very careful to try to get the best uncorrected vision as possible with your intraocular lens (IOL) after surgery so you can avoid using glasses for distance vision. A detailed discussion with your surgeon should clarify expectations about your visual goals.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "with your intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 14, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-11-14-2023-9-16-28-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-11-14-2023-9-16-28-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-11-15-2023-12-37-55-am", "title": "Can a patient receive a printout copy of the ORA?", "question": "As a patient considering ORA (Optiwave Refractive Analysis) during cataract surgery , can I obtain a copy of the monitor’s biometry data?", "answer": "There is no printout that I know of, although you may want to confirm this with your surgeon. The information from ORA is simply used to confirm the readings that were taken in the office.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 15, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-11-15-2023-12-37-55-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-11-15-2023-12-37-55-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-11-16-2023-12-23-57-pm", "title": "Would an IOL straighten my eye like my glasses do?", "question": "I'm considering IOL surgery and I have a lazy eye . The glasses and contact lenses I wear seem to straighten it to a degree that is hardly noticeable. Would IOLs also have this compensating effect? I’m aware it will never be perfect, but I don’t want it worse than it is now.", "answer": "The IOL should provide the same optical benefit as your glasses or contact lenses . The only change will be the loss of any “camouflage” effect the frame or lens may provide by partially hiding the appearance of the turned eye.", "answer_links": [{"text": "glasses or contact lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts-list"}], "answered_by": "Michael X Repka, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9c91065f-d048-4fd2-93c0-b2fefe845c2a", "answered_at": "NOV 16, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-11-16-2023-12-23-57-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-11-16-2023-12-23-57-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-12-12-2023-11-43-30-pm", "title": "Is it OK if I put nexanac drops in the wrong eye?", "question": "Is it OK if I put nexanac drops in the wrong eye?", "answer": "I’m assuming you were prescribed these drops to reduce pain and inflammation after cataract surgery .\n\nIf you used these drops accidentally in the eye it was not prescribed for, it would be extremely unlikely that any problem would occur. However, it’s always best to discuss any issues involving your medication with your prescribing physician or your pharmacist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "I’m assuming you were prescribed these drops to reduce pain and inflammation", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/pain-relieving-eye-drops"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "DEC 12, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-12-12-2023-11-43-30-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-12-12-2023-11-43-30-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-12-12-2023-8-32-31-am", "title": "What IOL is best for someone who doesn't need any correction?", "question": "I am 73 and have a cataract in my left eye. I had 20/20 vision in both eyes until the cataract began to affect vision in my left eye. When I was younger, I had 20/10 vision in both eyes. What IOL is best for someone who doesn't need any correction? All I read is geared to those who are nearsighted or farsighted prior to cataract surgery .", "answer": "Any type of intraocular lens (IOL) can be considered in this situation.\n\nMost commonly a monofocal IOL would be chosen for distance vision, which would require glasses for reading and intermediate vision. An extended depth-of-focus IOL can be used to offer distance with an extension of clarity to the intermediate range and glasses for reading up close. A multifocal IOL can give you vision at all distances with the cost of some glare and halos at night in some cases. Your eye health must be very good (for example, the cornea and retina need to be normal) for this lens to work as is expected. Lastly, a light adjustable IOL may be used, and the post operative vision can be adjusted. For example, it would be possible to have one eye with better distance vision, and then have the second eye adjusted to offer better close vision, as long as it is tolerated.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Any type of intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "An extended depth-of-focus IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/presbyopia-correcting-iols"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "DEC 12, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-12-12-2023-8-32-31-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-12-12-2023-8-32-31-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-12-13-2023-4-23-07-pm", "title": "Is it true that premium IOLs require laser-assisted surgery?", "question": "Do premium IOLs require laser-assisted surgery while traditional surgery with a blade is only for implanting basic monofocal IOLs?", "answer": "Having femtosecond laser-assisted cataract surgery (FLACS) may be beneficial in some cases. However, FLACS not required in order to use premium or advanced technology intraocular lenses. All of these lenses may be used whether or not the surgery is standard or laser assisted.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "All of these lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/best-artificial-lens-implant-iol-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "DEC 13, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-12-13-2023-4-23-07-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-12-13-2023-4-23-07-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-12-20-2023-2-57-12-pm", "title": "Can I use Flomax after cataract surgery?", "question": "Can I use Flomax after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Yes and it will not interfere with your healing. You may be thinking how Flomax and similar medications (known as BPH medication or alpha-blockers) can affect the iris's (the colored part of your eye) muscles during the surgery.\n\nBefore surgery, tell your ophthalmologist that you take these medications, so they can prepare for any side effects that may arise from them. After the surgery, there is no issue taking these drugs as it relates to your operated eye(s).", "answer_links": [{"text": "Flomax and similar medications", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/new-eyehealthcontent-3"}, {"text": "iris's (the colored part of your eye) muscles", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/iris-2"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "DEC 20, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-12-20-2023-2-57-12-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-12-20-2023-2-57-12-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-12-25-2022-5-46-04-pm", "title": "Will radiation treatment affect my IOLs?", "question": "My breast cancer metastasized to the tissue of my orbits in both eyes and I'm noticing blurry vision, watering and burning sensation. Will radiation affect my IOLs?", "answer": "I'm sorry you're dealing with these problems. You can be rest assured that there is no evidence radiation treatment will affect your intraocular lenses .", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "DEC 25, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-12-25-2022-5-46-04-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-12-25-2022-5-46-04-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-2-17-2025-11-48-31-am", "title": "Can I choose not to have an IOL?", "question": "Can one have a cataract removed without correcting vision? I am nearsighted with astigmatism but do a lot of close-up work. I don't mind wearing glasses and like being able to take off my glasses to see very up close and want to avoid the potential side effects of IOLs.", "answer": "An important part of the discussion that should take place with your ophthalmologist before cataract surgery is how you would like to have your vision corrected. This includes the different intraocular lenses (or IOLs) that may be available to you, as well as the refractive target, which in your case is to remain nearsighted . A helpful way to think about this is where you would like your vision to have the best focus and how clear you would like it to be without glasses.\n\nAn experienced ophthalmologist should be able to make recommendations with your preferences in mind.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "intraocular lenses (or IOLs)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "nearsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "An experienced ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-is-ophthalmologist"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "FEB 17, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-2-17-2025-11-48-31-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-2-17-2025-11-48-31-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-3-21-2025-2-10-28-am", "title": "Can I get monovision glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery with one eye corrected for distance and the other for near vision. After many years my distance is not so good. Can I get monovision glasses to correct this?", "answer": "This really depends on your correction, but if you are going to wear glasses in any way to correct your vision, I would recommend progressive lenses that will correct both eyes for all distances. If you would like monovision without glasses , contact lenses are the preferred option.", "answer_links": [{"text": "I would recommend progressive lenses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/pros-cons-progressive-lenses-computer-glasses"}, {"text": "If you would like monovision without glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 21, 2025", "categories": ["Contacts and Glasses", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-3-21-2025-2-10-28-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-3-21-2025-2-10-28-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-3-24-2023-10-28-42-am", "title": "Can you have cataract surgery too early in the disease process?", "question": "Is there such a thing as having cataract surgery too early in the natural history of the disease process? I may live another 30 years after cataract surgery and wonder what sort of ophthalmic advancements may occur after surgery at 65.", "answer": "Technology is always evolving. However, if your cataract interferes with any of your daily activities , then I would recommend surgery with the current available technology.\n\nToday's technology delivers excellent results that will endure. If clearer vision can improve your quality of life now, why wait another 10 years or more?", "answer_links": [{"text": "However, if your cataract interferes with any of your daily activities", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "I would recommend surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 24, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-3-24-2023-10-28-42-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-3-24-2023-10-28-42-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-3-7-2025-6-44-47-pm", "title": "Why can I see well with glasses after cataract surgery on one eye?", "question": "I just had cataract surgery on my left (dominant) eye with a lens for distant vision . I'm wearing my old glasses (-4.00 in each lens) and I can see distance objects very well, even though the left eye has a distance lens implanted. Why is that? I thought the left eye wouldn't be able to function with the glasses.", "answer": "You might be suppressing the distance vision in your operated eye while wearing your glasses and using your unoperated right eye for distance.\n\nIf your distance vision is fine without glasses, you might consider setting the right eye for near vision (called monovision) if you have cataract surgery in this eye in the future. However, if your distance vision without glasses is not great, then the right eye should be set for distance vision as well, leaving you more dependent on reading glasses for near vision with both eyes.\n\nIt is somewhat unusual (although not impossible) to suppress the dominant eye when viewing distance, and this suggests that perhaps your right eye is actually dominant, or that you don't have a heavily weighted dominant eye.", "answer_links": [{"text": "setting the right eye for near vision (called monovision)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "dominant eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-dominance"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 07, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-3-7-2025-6-44-47-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-3-7-2025-6-44-47-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-4-11-2023-3-33-32-am", "title": "Could my blurry vision already mean I have a PCO?", "question": "Within a week of cataract surgery , my distance vision is blurrier with more sunlight. Could I have a PCO already?", "answer": "Yes, you may have early PCO or posterior capsule opacification (when the capsule holding your eye's lens becomes cloudy after cataract surgery). Sometimes early deposits on the posterior capsule resolve on their own. If this is the cause and does not resolve itself, a YAG capsulotomy can fix the problem at about three months after your surgery .", "answer_links": [{"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "a YAG capsulotomy can fix the problem at about three months after your surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "APR 11, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-4-11-2023-3-33-32-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-4-11-2023-3-33-32-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-4-14-2023-9-28-05-am", "title": "Can I improve my amblyopia after infant cataract surgery?", "question": "I had a cataract removed as an infant , which was replaced with a monofocal IOL . At 23, that eye remains slightly amblyopic .\n\nIf adults can improve their amblyopia after damaging their good eye, can this help me? And what would be the consequences of using an intentionally wrong prescription (contacts or glasses) to cloud the good eye? Would there potentially be any negative consequences of this?", "answer": "It is so nice to hear of your good visual outcome from cataract surgery in infancy. At 23 years of age it would be unusual for any treatment to improve the vision further. Vision researchers continue to work on developing ways to reopen vision development.\n\nOn the other part of your question I do not believe there would be any harm to your good eye from some blur or patching but there is little good evidence that this would help your amblyopic eye (or an eye that failed to develop normal vision during childhood). It is true that if a patient with an amblyopic eye has severe or total vision loss in their “good” eye, then vision in the amblyopic eye may improve somewhat, but this rarely would result in “normal” vision.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Michael X Repka, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9c91065f-d048-4fd2-93c0-b2fefe845c2a", "answered_at": "APR 14, 2023", "categories": ["Amblyopia, Strabismus and Lazy Eye", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-4-14-2023-9-28-05-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-4-14-2023-9-28-05-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-4-18-2023-5-51-50-pm", "title": "Is it safe to have YAG with a PVD?", "question": "Is it safe to have YAG while you have PVD? It’s been 5 months since the PVD started.", "answer": "The YAG laser used during a posterior capsulotomy poses no risk to the vitreous inside the eye or its age-related detachment process if already underway. However, YAG capsulotomy does carry a low but real risk of retinal tear (average risk is less than 1%) and this risk is greatest if the PVD (posterior vitreous detachment) is in process or has recently occurred.\n\nBased on recent research it is typically recommended that you wait at least 6 months following a complete PVD before proceeding with YAG capsulotomy to decrease the risk of retinal tear and detachment . There may be special circumstances affecting the timing of your procedure so please discuss this question with your eye surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The YAG laser used during a posterior capsulotomy poses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "vitreous inside the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/vitreous"}, {"text": "carry a low but real risk of retinal tear", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-torn-retina"}, {"text": "PVD (posterior vitreous detachment)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-posterior-vitreous-detachment"}, {"text": "detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 18, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-4-18-2023-5-51-50-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-4-18-2023-5-51-50-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-5-1-2023-8-05-04-am", "title": "Why do I feel a scratchy sensation in my eyelid after cataract surgery?", "question": "One month after cataract surgery , why do I feel a scratchy sensation in my eyelid?", "answer": "It is not uncommon to feel a bit of scratchiness after cataract surgery. Your eye might feel a bit dry , and you may have sensitivity to the post-surgical drops or the sutures if they were used to seal the incision. Please discuss this and any other symptoms with your surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Your eye might feel a bit dry", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "MAY 01, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-5-1-2023-8-05-04-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-5-1-2023-8-05-04-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-5-14-2023-5-27-23-am", "title": "How soon after cataract surgery can I try to get pregnant?", "question": "How soon after cataract surgery can I try to get pregnant?", "answer": "We have no evidence that drops that are used after cataract surgery have any effect on the fetus. However out of abundance of caution, you may want to wait until surgery is completed on the second eye and you’ve stopped taking any post-operative medication. This is usually 5 weeks after cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 14, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-5-14-2023-5-27-23-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-5-14-2023-5-27-23-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-5-15-2023-4-05-45-am", "title": "With cataract surgery, are there accommodations for those with mobility problems?", "question": "Are there accommodations for cataract surgery patients with mobility problems? My mother is overweight and we're told she needs to be removed from her wheelchair multiple times for testing. Are there workarounds to meet these testing requirements that allow her to stay in her chair?", "answer": "While it is easiest if someone is able to transfer to an exam chair or surgical stretcher, some offices and surgery centers/hospitals are able to accommodate wheelchair-bound individuals who are unable to transfer.\n\nYou should discuss your concerns with your mother's ophthalmologist and/or office manager, as they may have such \"workarounds.\" That said, sometimes referral to a different ophthalmologist is necessary and in the patient's best interest.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "MAY 15, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-5-15-2023-4-05-45-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-5-15-2023-4-05-45-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-5-7-2023-4-44-50-pm", "title": "Why don't I see clearly with my left eye when closing the right after cataract surgery?", "question": "With mini-monovision after cataract surgery , I use my non-dominant left eye for distance. I wear driving glasses, which provide crisp distance vision and I am also able to see the dashboard clearly. I noticed, however, when I close my right eye, I cannot see clearly with my left. It is almost as if the monovision has been reversed. Is this a concern?", "answer": "With monovision (or blended vision) , a person's \"dominant\" eye is typically corrected to see better at a distance, while their \"non-dominant\" eye is corrected to see better up close.\n\nGlasses for driving usually correct both eyes to see better at a distance. If you are having trouble seeing clearly out of your left eye while wearing glasses, then have them checked by the optician who sold them to you. If the optician confirms the glasses were made correctly, then follow up with the eye care provider who wrote the glasses prescription to have this rechecked.", "answer_links": [{"text": "With monovision (or blended vision)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-monovision-blended-vision"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "MAY 07, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-5-7-2023-4-44-50-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-5-7-2023-4-44-50-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-9-26-2023-9-24-45-am", "title": "Can I use acetaminophen eye drops after surgery?", "question": "As I am allergic to NSAIDs, are there eye drops with acetaminophen I can use after cataract surgery?", "answer": "There is no drop that contains acetaminophen.\n\nPlease note that topical NSAID (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) drops are not an absolute requirement for safe cataract surgery . If you are truly allergic to NSAIDs then talk to your surgeon about not using them topically. They will most likely say that that is fine.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Please note that topical NSAID (non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) drops", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/pain-relieving-eye-drops"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 26, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-9-26-2023-9-24-45-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-9-26-2023-9-24-45-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "new-question-from-9-28-2023-8-56-10-pm", "title": "Does risk of IOL dislocation preclude YAG laser treatment?", "question": "Does a high risk of IOL dislocation in nearsighted eyes preclude laser capsulotomy treatment of PCO?", "answer": "It does not. If the intraocular lens (IOL) is currently stable and in place and there is clinically significant posterior capsule opacification (PCO) then a posterior capsulotomy is indicated and can and should be done.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 28, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/new-question-from-9-28-2023-8-56-10-pm", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\new-question-from-9-28-2023-8-56-10-pm.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "oculoplastic-doc-droopy-eyelid-cataract-surgery", "title": "Should an oculoplastic specialist examine my droopy eyelid before cataract surgery?", "question": "Should an oculoplastic specialist examine my ptosis before cataract surgery ?", "answer": "It is ideal, but not mandatory, for an oculoplastic surgeon to evaluate a droopy eyelid (ptosis) before cataract surgery.\n\nIt’s important to understand the cause of the ptosis, as there can be refractive changes from severe ptosis that may impact IOL (intraocular lens) selection. The ptosis may worsen after cataract surgery. Ultimately, it is up to the patient and the discretion of the cataract surgeon to determine timing of referral to an oculoplastic surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "droopy eyelid (ptosis)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-ptosis"}, {"text": "IOL (intraocular lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "JUL 01, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/oculoplastic-doc-droopy-eyelid-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\oculoplastic-doc-droopy-eyelid-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "oil-bubble-with-artificial-lens-iol", "title": "Should an oil bubble be used if you have an artificial lens?", "question": "Should an oil bubble to hold a detached retina in place be used if there is an artificial lens in that same eye?", "answer": "Yes, having an artificial intraocular lens (IOL) does not prevent the use of silicone oil in the eye to help repair a retinal detachment . Silicone oil is often used for retinal detachment repair in eyes with IOLs.", "answer_links": [{"text": "artificial intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "repair a retinal detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}], "answered_by": "Paul Sternberg Jr., MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/0d86e7a6-93dd-44e1-a027-981014dfd11f", "answered_at": "NOV 04, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Torn or Detached Retina"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/oil-bubble-with-artificial-lens-iol", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\oil-bubble-with-artificial-lens-iol.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "optimum-blood-pressure-before-cataract-surgery", "title": "At what level should blood pressure be prior to cataract surgery?", "question": "What should a person’s blood pressure be before cataract surgery and what is considered too high?", "answer": "In general, since cataract surgery is a voluntary procedure, most surgeons would choose not to operate if there are medical problems that are found to be uncontrolled. Most surgeons would hold off on surgery if the diastolic blood pressure is above 100 or systolic blood pressure is above 160 to 180 or so. The other factor to consider is the patient’s baseline blood pressure. If the blood pressure is significantly higher than baseline then one must consider whether the patient’s blood pressure is safely under control. Sometimes anticipation of surgery can cause a spike in blood pressure on arrival to the surgery center, which will then decrease after relaxing for a while.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Jun. 2, 2015.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 16, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/optimum-blood-pressure-before-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\optimum-blood-pressure-before-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "other-eye-worse-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why does my other eye seem worse after cataract surgery on the fellow eye?", "question": "After having an IOL implanted in my \"bad\" eye , the \"good\" eye now seems more cloudy, like the old eye used to. Is that because the eye that had cataract surgery is now highlighting the fellow eye's previously unnoticed weakness?", "answer": "Yes, most likely both eyes had cataracts and now that the first eye has been corrected, it lets you know that the “better” eye actually had issues as well. Plan to get the other eye done and you will be more in balance and happier with your vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Yes, most likely both eyes had cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 28, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/other-eye-worse-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\other-eye-worse-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "preferable-lens-choice-for-pathological-myopia", "title": "If I have pathological myopia, would it be preferable to maximize near distance instead of far distance in lens choice?", "question": "I have pathological myopia . I am wondering if it would be preferable to maximize near distance instead of far distance in lens choice , as my eye will continue to elongate after cataract surgery.", "answer": "It is doubtful that your eye will continue to elongate but you may experience some atrophy in the pigment in the central part of the retina . It is very important that you consult with a retina specialist yearly. Because it is the lens that will make you more myopic as you get older, and it is this lens that will be removed by cataract surgery , you are free to pick whatever distance you wish for correction.", "answer_links": [{"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAR 25, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/preferable-lens-choice-for-pathological-myopia", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\preferable-lens-choice-for-pathological-myopia.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "risk-develop-secondary-cataract-other-eye", "title": "Can I expect a secondary cataract on the other eye if it happened on the first eye?", "question": "I had secondary cataract soon after cataract surgery on one eye and did YAG. Now that I’ve done the other eye, am I more likely to get secondary cataract again?", "answer": "Secondary cataract (also known as posterior capsule opacification) is when the tissue (lens capsule) that once held your eye’s natural lens becomes cloudy after cataract surgery . It is common and can take months or years to develop. In my experience what happens in one eye is similar to what happens in the other. But that is not always the case. The type of cataract, specifics about the particular surgery, and the post-operative course also play an important role and this may differ between the two eyes.\n\nNonetheless, I wouldn't be overly concerned because modern YAG laser treatment (or posterior capsulotomy) is very safe and effective .", "answer_links": [{"text": "the tissue (lens capsule) that once held your eye’s natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "YAG laser treatment (or posterior capsulotomy) is very safe and effective", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUL 20, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/risk-develop-secondary-cataract-other-eye", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\risk-develop-secondary-cataract-other-eye.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "rubbing-eyes-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "I accidentally rubbed my eye two weeks after my cataract surgery. Do you think this caused any damage?", "question": "I accidentally rubbed my eye two weeks after my cataract surgery . Do you think this caused any damage?", "answer": "Rubbing your eye gently two weeks after cataract surgery is unlikely to cause harm to the eye. Vigorous rubbing, however, could cause a corneal abrasion and even damage the surgical wound. If you have any pain or change in vision, please see your surgeon right away. This question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 18, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/rubbing-eyes-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\rubbing-eyes-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "seeing-streaks-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why am I seeing streaks of light after cataract surgery?", "question": "I just had cataract surgery and when I went outside at night I saw streams or long streaks of light across the outdoor lights everywhere I looked. Can it be corrected and will it go away over time?", "answer": "Our pupils dilate in dim light, and this can cause or increase optical aberrations such as you describe, especially following cataract surgery. Still, there are potential genuine issues associated with these symptoms. You should see your ophthalmologist and have them confirm that the intraocular lens is ideally centered and your eye is in good condition.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Feb. 21, 2014.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "JAN 22, 2024", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/seeing-streaks-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\seeing-streaks-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-i-go-without-reading-glasses-if-i-have-mult", "title": "Should I go without reading glasses if I have a multifocal IOL?", "question": "during the surgery a few days ago. Will it help my brain adjust to near vision by not wearing reading glasses or are there other ways to help my brain adapt to near vision better?", "answer": "This would depend on the other eye. If your multifocal IOL was just recently inserted then you may need some time for the vision to clear at all distances. Also, if your other eye requires spectacles to read this may be a barrier to reading without glasses. Multifocal IOLs tend to work best after being inserted in both eyes. Multifocal IOLs are not guaranteed to eliminate the need for spectacles at all distances, and there may be times when glasses may help for distance, reading or in between.\n\nTo your question, I do find that if the reading is good enough without using glasses, then not using them may help you acclimate to your new ability to read and allow the brain to choose the near image to focus on.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAY 21, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-i-go-without-reading-glasses-if-i-have-mult", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-i-go-without-reading-glasses-if-i-have-mult.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-i-have-cataract-surgery-in-my-second-eye-if", "title": "Should I have cataract surgery in my second eye if my vision is still good?", "question": "I had cataract surgery performed in my right eye five months ago without complications and excellent results. I can still see clearly with my left eye which has not been operated on. Should I go ahead and have cataract surgery in my left eye too even though vision in it is still good?", "answer": "Cataract surgery is done to improve vision that interferes with quality of life issues, like working or driving. If the lens in the fellow eye is not interfering with your quality of life, but a patient wishes to have it removed, this would usually be considered an elective procedure. This means it is not covered by health insurance. Therefore, if the vision in your left eye “is still good,” you may want to consider delaying surgery until your eye develops a cataract such that it interferes with your quality of life. In certain circumstances, an ophthalmologist may recommend cataract surgery when the patient does not complain of vision problems – surgery to balance the eyes may decrease the risk of falls (which can cause hip fractures) or decrease the risk of angle closure glaucoma . A discussion with your ophthalmologist after a thorough in-person exam will help you reach a decision that is best for you.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "angle closure glaucoma", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-glaucoma"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAY 27, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-i-have-cataract-surgery-in-my-second-eye-if", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-i-have-cataract-surgery-in-my-second-eye-if.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-i-have-skin-tags-removed-before-cataract-su", "title": "Should I have skin tags removed before cataract surgery?", "question": "Should I have eyelid skin tags (“benign,” or non-cancerous, small growths of the skin) removed before cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Please ask your surgeon what her preference may be. In general. the removal of a benign skin tag is not a preoperative requirement. Unless, of course, you have a habit of rubbing your eyes in the area of the skin tags, which could cause problems after surgery.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "MAY 26, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-i-have-skin-tags-removed-before-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-i-have-skin-tags-removed-before-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-i-use-toric-lens-if-i-have-had-corneal-tran", "title": "Should I use a toric lens if I have had corneal transplants?", "question": "I have two corneal grafts (transplants) and need cataract surgery . My surgeon would implant toric intraocular lenses (IOLs) for astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea) as part of the procedure. In discussing the risks involved he says that I eventually may need new corneal transplants because of the continual changing nature of my corneas. If so, the implanted lenses would be a total mismatch for the new corneas. Is it possible to remove IOLs after a prolonged period such as 10 years? Is this ever done?", "answer": "This is an extremely complicated and nuanced decision. If your grafts are clear and stable and the astigmatism is regular then I would consider a toric intraocular lens. If the grafts are unstable, meaning changing or beginning to fail and repeat transplants are imminent then I would not consider a toric IOL. And, yes, implants can be exchanged but the longer they have been in the more difficult that may be.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 04, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Astigmatism", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-i-use-toric-lens-if-i-have-had-corneal-tran", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-i-use-toric-lens-if-i-have-had-corneal-tran.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-patients-with-pseudoexfoliation-syndrome-ha", "title": "Should patients with pseudoexfoliation syndrome have laser cataract surgery?", "question": "Should patients with pseudoexfoliation syndrome have laser cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Pseudoexfoliation of the lens capsule is when the eye’s natural lens and the supporting structures (zonules) which hold the lens in place are weakened. Modern cataract surgery and placement of the intraocular lens (or IOL, the artificial lens that replaces the cataract) are dependent on the strength of these structures. Pseudoexfoliation can vary in severity and impact on these structures.\n\nSuccessful cataract surgery and IOL placement can be performed safely with pseudoexfoliation, but it is an added risk factor for a safe result. Laser-assisted cataract surgery can minimize the stress of these structures and some ophthalmologists feel it results in a safer operation. This is an area of disagreement among ophthalmologists.", "answer_links": [{"text": "lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "intraocular lens (or IOL, the artificial lens that replaces the cataract)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "AUG 14, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-patients-with-pseudoexfoliation-syndrome-ha", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-patients-with-pseudoexfoliation-syndrome-ha.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "should-you-have-yag-before-having-cataract-surgery", "title": "Should you have YAG before having cataract surgery on the second eye?", "question": "If a patient has PCO (posterior capsule opacification) in her eye after cataract surgery, should that eye be repaired with YAG laser (or posterior capsulotomy) first, or should I have cataract surgery on the fellow eye first?", "answer": "If the PCO (when vision becomes cloudy shortly after cataract surgery) is bothering your vision significantly, have the YAG first. With YAG, or posterior capsulotomy , a laser makes an opening in the cloudy capsule holding your artificial lens and restores clear vision. It literally takes less than a minute with no restrictions afterward. You can plan to have the cataract surgery in the next days or week. There’s no harm in waiting to have the YAG either.", "answer_links": [{"text": "With YAG, or posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "artificial lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 23, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/should-you-have-yag-before-having-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\should-you-have-yag-before-having-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "surgical-clearance-before-cataract-surgery", "title": "Is routine pre-operative medical clearance needed before cataract surgery?", "question": "Is routine pre-operative medical clearance needed before cataract surgery?", "answer": "Routine pre-operative clearance for cataract surgery (which is usually done under local pain killer with IV sedation) is not usually necessary unless you have some serious health issues. It is required by the medical or health boards in some states.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 27, 2018", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/surgical-clearance-before-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\surgical-clearance-before-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "treat-puffy-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "How can I reduce puffiness under my eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "Are there any tips to reduce puffiness under the eye after cataract surgery on a dense or mature lens?", "answer": "Patients often notice puffiness under their eyes after cataract surgery. The surgery does not cause the puffiness, but enhanced vision following the surgery allows you to see the aging characteristic. Fortunately, there is cosmetic surgery called lower blepharoplasty to improve the appearance of the puffiness.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Fortunately, there is cosmetic surgery called lower blepharoplasty", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/eyelid-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "AUG 29, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Cosmetic Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/treat-puffy-eye-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\treat-puffy-eye-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "wear-makeup-same-day-as-yag-posterior-capsulotomy", "title": "Can I wear makeup the same day I have a YAG posterior capsulotomy?", "question": "Can I wear makeup the same day I have a YAG posterior capsulotomy ?", "answer": "There shouldn't be a problem wearing makeup before a YAG procedure. But be to sure ask the ophthalmologist who will be doing the procedure for their specific guidance.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JUN 12, 2025", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/wear-makeup-same-day-as-yag-posterior-capsulotomy", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\wear-makeup-same-day-as-yag-posterior-capsulotomy.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-are-odds-of-getting-halos-star-bursts-from-mu", "title": "What are the odds of getting halos or star bursts from multifocal IOLs?", "question": "I am trying to decide whether to go with monofocal IOLs or multifocal IOLs . Is there any way to assess the odds of getting halos or star bursts which do not resolve? Is there any significant difference between brands of multifocal lenses in terms of halo or star bursts which do not resolve?", "answer": "There is no specific test to assess the risk of halos, as every patient notices some halo/glare after the surgery. For most, this will decrease over the first three months. Some surgeons feel that certain corneal abnormalities found on measurements taken before the surgery can lead to more halo/glare after surgery but this is not absolute. Ask your surgeon about this. I would have your surgeon check this and all other pre-operative measurements to see if multifocal IOLs are a good option for you. Some doctors feel that certain multifocal lenses perform better than others. Ask your ophthalmologist what might work best for you.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 31, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-are-odds-of-getting-halos-star-bursts-from-mu", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-are-odds-of-getting-halos-star-bursts-from-mu.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-are-some-of-risks-associated-with-not-having-", "title": "What are the risks of not removing a cataract?", "question": "What are some of the risks associated with not having a cataract removed? Can other damage occur as the cataract continues to get larger?", "answer": "The main risk of not having a cataract removed is that you will be living with compromised vision from the cataract that is known to result in a higher incidence of falls as well as other problems. If your vision is not bothersome and you feel you can get around and do all activities of daily living, there is no harm in waiting. It is possible to wait too long, making the cataract operation more difficult if the cataract becomes mature or very dense.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract removed", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 26, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-are-some-of-risks-associated-with-not-having-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-are-some-of-risks-associated-with-not-having-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-can-be-done-if-one-develops-cataract-after-ge", "title": "What can be done if one develops a cataract after getting an implantable contact lens?", "question": "What can be done if one develops a cataract after having an ICL (implantable contact lens) to cure myopia ?", "answer": "Cataract removal can be scheduled electively and should be like a regular cataract surgery. The ICL will be removed and then the cataract is removed. The newly implanted artificial lens (IOL) replaces the ICL. If additional correction is needed, glasses, contact lenses or refractive surgery can finetune the refraction.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract removal can be scheduled electively", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "implanted artificial lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 21, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-can-be-done-if-one-develops-cataract-after-ge", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-can-be-done-if-one-develops-cataract-after-ge.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-can-i-use-my-red-itchy-eyes-after-cataract-su", "title": "What can I use for my red, itchy eyes after cataract surgery?", "question": "What can I use for my red, itchy eyes after cataract surgery?", "answer": "There are several reasons that eyes can be red and itchy after cataract surgery .\n\nIn the first few weeks after surgery, the surgical incisions and medicated eye drops can cause irritation of the surface of the eye. Less common would be an actual allergic reaction to the eye drops. Later after surgery, the area of the incisions can still cause surface irritation, sometimes for several months. Most of these situations will improve with use of artificial tears (lubricant eye drops) to soothe the eyes.\n\nEarly after surgery, while the incisions are still healing, you should use a new bottle of artificial tears or purchase preservative-free tears (which come in small plastic vials rather than a bottle) to avoid placing contaminated drops on the eye. It is best to avoid products that have vasoconstrictors to relieve redness (drops to “get the red out”). Avoid using the tears within 15 minutes before or after your medicated surgical eye drops (this could dilute the medication and reduce its effectiveness).\n\nIf the lubricating drops do not help, or if the redness and itching are severe, you should contact your ophthalmologist immediately.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "JUN 21, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-can-i-use-my-red-itchy-eyes-after-cataract-su", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-can-i-use-my-red-itchy-eyes-after-cataract-su.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-does-rating-of-4-5-cataracts-mean", "title": "What does a rating of 4.5 for cataracts mean?", "question": "What does a rating of 4.5 for cataracts signify?", "answer": "All ophthalmologists have different “ratings” for grading the density of the cataract . In a 5-point system, this would be a very dense cataract which would normally need removal .", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "need removal", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 19, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-does-rating-of-4-5-cataracts-mean", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-does-rating-of-4-5-cataracts-mean.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-happens-if-i-get-cataract-after-i-have-iol-im", "title": "What happens if I get a cataract after I have an IOL implanted?", "question": "If IOLs (or intraocular artificial lenses that replace your eye’s natural lenses) are implanted as elective surgery, what is done if cataracts develop afterwards?", "answer": "A cataract occurs when the eye’s natural lens becomes cloudy and is replaced with an artificial lens. Because the lens of your eye has been removed, you can’t ever develop cataracts again. You may, however develop what is called “secondary cataract,” which is treated with a laser in an office setting in a minute or two.", "answer_links": [{"text": "A cataract occurs when the eye’s natural lens becomes cloudy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "“secondary cataract,” which is treated with a laser in an office setting", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/how-soon-secondary-cataract"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAR 10, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-happens-if-i-get-cataract-after-i-have-iol-im", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-happens-if-i-get-cataract-after-i-have-iol-im.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-iol-is-best-if-i-ve-had-stroke", "title": "What IOL is best if I’ve had a stroke?", "question": "I am planning for cataract surgery next spring and trying to compare the various IOLs as they would affect my balance problems from an old cerebellar stroke. Would it be useful for me to consult with a neurologist as I consider my options?", "answer": "I don’t think most neurologists would have a deep understanding of IOL designs and their effects. The best physician to speak to about this is your cataract surgeon. If your old cerebellar stroke causes problems with your vision, balance or eye movements, your surgeon might consult a neuro-ophthalmologist. The simplest thing to do to minimize potential side effects after surgery would be to choose a monofocal lens or a toric lens (if you have astigmatism ).\n\nWhile there is little clinical data that discusses multifocal IOLs and neurological disease, multifocals do occasionally create symptoms that in theory could worsen your existing visual function. Your cataract surgeon will be able to help you decide on the best IOL option for your specific situation.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}, {"text": "IOL option", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 04, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-iol-is-best-if-i-ve-had-stroke", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-iol-is-best-if-i-ve-had-stroke.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-is-best-iol-choice-pilot", "title": "What is the best IOL choice for a pilot?", "question": "What is the best IOL choice for a pilot?", "answer": "With multifocal or accommodative lenses, you have to lay off flying for 3 months per FAA guidelines. Therefore, a traditional monofocal or toric (astigmatism correcting) lens would be in your best interest.", "answer_links": [{"text": "traditional monofocal or toric (astigmatism correcting) lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 29, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-is-best-iol-choice-pilot", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-is-best-iol-choice-pilot.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-is-best-treatment-option-corneal-edema", "title": "What is the best treatment option for corneal edema?", "question": "What is the best treatment option for corneal edema after cataract surgery in an 72-year-old diabetic woman?", "answer": "Corneal edema (swelling of the clear, dome-shaped window at the front of the eye ) after cataract surgery is quite common as the cornea can take some time to recover. Depending on the cause, there are different treatments recommended. Usually, with enough time (a few weeks on average), all that is needed are the standard post-operative drops to relieve swelling. However, if someone has unresolved inflammation/edema inside the eye , the corneal swelling can linger, and steroid drops are recommended.\n\nIf the intraocular pressure is very high or very low, corneal edema can also occur. This should also be brought back into normal range with the right treatment.\n\nSometimes, special eye drops may be needed to pull the excess fluid out of the cornea. As a last resort, a corneal transplant can be performed to replace the damaged endothelial cells responsible for the swelling.", "answer_links": [{"text": "clear, dome-shaped window at the front of the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "inflammation/edema inside the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/inflammation"}, {"text": "intraocular pressure", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}, {"text": "corneal transplant", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/about-corneal-transplantation"}, {"text": "endothelial cells", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/endothelium"}], "answered_by": "Omar R Chaudhary, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/8e0e0d43-5cc4-4c54-be05-971ce84e7afa", "answered_at": "JAN 26, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-is-best-treatment-option-corneal-edema", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-is-best-treatment-option-corneal-edema.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-is-closest-iol-can-be-set-near-vision", "title": "What is the closest an IOL can be set for near vision?", "question": "What is the range of clear vision (inches from the eye) for an IOL that is set for near vision? As a photographer, I would like to have clear vision at a distance of six inches.", "answer": "Presbyopia-correcting IOLs have different set points for near depending on the manufacturer. Talk to your ophthalmologist about which of these would provide the closest near vision given your eye health and vision needs.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Presbyopia-correcting IOLs", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "Talk to your ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-is-ophthalmologist"}], "answered_by": null, "answered_by_url": null, "answered_at": "AUG 11, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-is-closest-iol-can-be-set-near-vision", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-is-closest-iol-can-be-set-near-vision.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-is-recommended-time-to-wait-after-bacterial-b", "title": "What is the recommended time to wait after bacterial blepharitis clears before having cataract surgery?", "question": "What is the recommended time to wait after bacterial blepharitis clears before having cataract surgery ?", "answer": "It is recommended that surgery be delayed by one week after the infection has cleared.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 02, 2016", "categories": ["Infections", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-is-recommended-time-to-wait-after-bacterial-b", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-is-recommended-time-to-wait-after-bacterial-b.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-is-wait-time-between-cataract-surgery-blephar", "title": "What is the wait time between cataract surgery and blepharoplasty?", "question": "How long after cataract surgery should you wait to have upper lid blepharoplasty?", "answer": "Generally, cataract surgeons recommend waiting 6 weeks or so before proceeding with additional surgery. This varies depending on how the surgery went and how the eye is healing, so the wait time is best determined by your surgeon(s).", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Rona Z Silkiss, MD, FACS", "answered_by_url": "/biography/db9b9acc-2d1e-46a3-8a5f-2502cfd3983d", "answered_at": "APR 04, 2022", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-is-wait-time-between-cataract-surgery-blephar", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-is-wait-time-between-cataract-surgery-blephar.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-otc-eye-drops-can-i-use-after-my-cataract-sur", "title": "What OTC eye drops can I use after my cataract surgery?", "question": "What over-the-counter eyedrops can I use after my cataract surgery ? I used the required prescription dosage before and right after surgery.", "answer": "If the eye is red or sore, sensitive to light, very irritated or getting blurry then you need to see your cataract surgeon for the appropriate treatment. If you are having mild symptoms of foreign body sensation, burning and/or tearing and your vision is stable and not worsening you can try any over-the-counter lubricating tear drop .", "answer_links": [{"text": "over-the-counter lubricating tear drop", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lubricating-eye-drops"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 23, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-otc-eye-drops-can-i-use-after-my-cataract-sur", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-otc-eye-drops-can-i-use-after-my-cataract-sur.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-risks-are-associated-with-not-having-cataract", "title": "What are the risks of not removing a cataract?", "question": "What are some of the risks associated with not having a cataract removed? Can other damage occur as the cataract continues to get larger?", "answer": "The main risk of not having a cataract removed is that you will be living with compromised vision from the cataract that is known to result in a higher incidence of falls as well as other problems. If your vision is not bothersome and you feel you can get around and do all activities of daily living, there is no harm in waiting. It is possible to wait too long, making the cataract operation more difficult if the cataract becomes mature or very dense.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract removed", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "AUG 26, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-risks-are-associated-with-not-having-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-risks-are-associated-with-not-having-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-s-difference-between-discission-cataract-surg", "title": "What's the difference between discission and cataract surgery?", "question": "What's the difference between discission and cataract surgery?", "answer": "Cataract surgery is a removal of the cloudy lens (one that has become less transparent) in the eye . Modern cataract surgery usually includes leaving the original \"skin\" of the back surface of the eye’s natural lens (called the \"posterior capsule\") in place in an effort to better support a plastic artificial intraocular lens (\"implant\") that replaces the cataract . In some cases, this capsule becomes cloudy, and a discission—creating an opening in the capsule so that light can better pass through it—can be made. This is usually accomplished with a laser and is called a \"posterior capsulotomy.\"", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataract surgery is a removal of the cloudy lens (one that has become less transparent) in the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "eye’s natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "artificial intraocular lens (\"implant\") that replaces the cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/intraocular-lenses-iols-how-to-decide-what-type"}], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "MAY 17, 2016", "categories": ["Torn or Detached Retina", "Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-s-difference-between-discission-cataract-surg", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-s-difference-between-discission-cataract-surg.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-type-of-iol-should-i-get-myopia-astigmatism", "title": "What type of IOL should I get for myopia and astigmatism?", "question": "I wear glasses to correct myopia (nearsightedness) and astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea) . My glasses are no-line progressive lenses and I’m planning to have cataract surgery now at age 74. I’m thinking I’ll choose either an IOL for near and intermediate vision and wear glasses for distance vision, or get an IOL for distance and use glasses for near/intermediate vision. I am likely to continue working and using a computer for another five years and I also read a lot. Which option do you think might work best?", "answer": "It is not possible for me to tell you what intraocular lens (IOL) combination would work best for you, as this is a very personal decision. There are three basic ranges of vision: distance, intermediate and near. As it stands today, many intraocular lenses can provide excellent vision is any two of these three ranges, but none of the available intraocular lens provides excellent vision in all three ranges. There are many ways of using multifocal and monofocal lenses to deal with this problem:\n\n- Multifocal IOL in each eye for distance and near with intermediate range glasses\n\n- Multifocal IOL in each eye for distance and intermediate with near glasses\n\n- Multifocal IOL in both eyes for distance and intermediate but deliberately setting the IOL power of the non-dominant a slight bit nearsighted which makes distance vision slightly blurry if the dominant eye is closed, but does not affect distance vision when using both eyes and gives a small boost for reading when both eyes are open.\n\n- Multifocal IOL in each eye distance and intermediate, however, set such that the non-dominant eye’s distance vision is slightly off focus to the nearsighted side, allowing a boost for near vision.\n\n- Monofocal IOL for distance in dominant eye and non-dominant eye set for intermediate. This is called mini-monovision.\n\nAnd there are more options you should discuss with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/glasses"}, {"text": "nearsighted", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "OCT 23, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-type-of-iol-should-i-get-myopia-astigmatism", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-type-of-iol-should-i-get-myopia-astigmatism.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-viscoelastic-gel-can-be-used-in-phacoemulsifi", "title": "What viscoelastic gel can be used in the phacoemulsification stage of the surgery that does not have lidocaine in the gel?", "question": "You state that cataract surgery can be performed without using xylocaine (lidocaine) if one is allergic to it. What viscoelastic gel can be used in the phacoemulsification stage of the surgery that does not have lidocaine in the gel?", "answer": "The ocular viscoeleastic device does not contain lidocaine. As far as anesthesia is concerned there are other topical drops and injectible anesthetics that can give perfectly acceptable anesthesia for cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 06, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-viscoelastic-gel-can-be-used-in-phacoemulsifi", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-viscoelastic-gel-can-be-used-in-phacoemulsifi.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "what-will-my-range-of-focus-be-like-if-i-have-iol-", "title": "What will my range of focus be like if I have IOL set for near- or mid-range?", "question": "If I have the IOL implant lenses set for near- or mid-range, will the actual range of focus be any greater for near- or mid-work than it would be if the IOL lenses are set for distance? The main distances I need are: 14\" (reading), 20\" (playing the pipe organ), and 36\" for reading student's music while teaching.", "answer": "The focal point will be very narrow for mid/near and distance will be blurry. If set for distance do not expect any near- or mid-distance. A multifocal lens may be a better choice for what you are seeking. Another option would be modified monovision, with one eye set for reading and the other set for intermediate – this might allow you to see at all three of your target ranges without glasses, but would require glasses correction for distance. Of course, your degree of astigmatism will affect the success of any implant lens scenario and may need correction with a toric lens or corneal procedure to achieve the best vision in your target range without glasses.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 04, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/what-will-my-range-of-focus-be-like-if-i-have-iol-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\what-will-my-range-of-focus-be-like-if-i-have-iol-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "when-after-cataract-surgery-posterior-capsule-opac", "title": "How soon after cataract surgery can posterior capsule opacity happen?", "question": "I was born with cataracts in both eyes. I had them removed in my teenage years and I am now 30 years old. Recently, my doctor checked and diagnosed me with posterior capsule opacity (PCO) and said I will need laser treatment. Is it really possible to have PCO so suddenly?", "answer": "A posterior capsular opacity is a clouding of the membrane that holds the intraocular lens in place. It is the back wall of the capsule that once enclosed your eye’s natural lens as well. A PCO does not come suddenly, but once the fibrosis covers a central area, it is time for a laser treatment. Everyone needs a laser treatment at some time. It is a very minor and quick procedure and may actually make your vision sharper.", "answer_links": [{"text": "posterior capsular opacity", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "eye’s natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 25, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/when-after-cataract-surgery-posterior-capsule-opac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\when-after-cataract-surgery-posterior-capsule-opac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "when-can-my-8-month-old-get-iols-after-having-cata", "title": "When can my 8-month-old get IOLs after having cataracts removed at birth?", "question": "My 8-month-old baby had cataracts removed from both eyes and wears RGP contact lenses . At what age can IOLs be implanted?", "answer": "The timing of placing intraocular lenses (IOL) depends on the child and the condition of the eyes. If the child is doing well with contact lenses, then sometimes that is the best initial treatment. Placement of IOLs is typically withheld until 2 to 4 years of age. However, there may be factors that may limit the ability to place an IOL. For instance, the lens capsule that holds the IOL might not be able to support it. Or there may be other diseases affecting one or both eyes. It is always best to discuss this topic with your child's managing ophthalmologist who knows your child best.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lenses (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "lens capsule that holds the IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}], "answered_by": "Aaron M Miller, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/1d353ee7-10f5-4298-a733-ea4d82f1bfc8", "answered_at": "OCT 11, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Children's Eye Health", "Babies and Infants"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/when-can-my-8-month-old-get-iols-after-having-cata", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\when-can-my-8-month-old-get-iols-after-having-cata.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "when-you-have-cataract-surgery-they-tell-you-that-", "title": "When you have cataract surgery and they tell you that your distance vision will be good but you will need glasses to read, will you be able to work on a computer without glasses?", "question": "When you have cataract surgery and they tell you that your distance vision will be good but you will need glasses to read, will you be able to work on a computer without glasses, put on make-up without your glasses, etc.? I am kind of confused as to what my sight will be like after the surgery.", "answer": "The lens of the eye changes shape when you switch what you are looking at—from things that are far away to things that are very close (and at every point in between those two). A cataract is a clouding of the focusing lens . The cataract lens cannot be cleaned. It must be removed.\n\nIn the old days, people had to wear very thick eyeglasses to make up for the lost focusing power of the human focusing lens. Today we replace the human lens with an artificial lens placed inside the eye called an IOL (intraocular lens) .\n\nWe have a great variety of IOL options and these choices can be very confusing. The standard IOL that most insurance companies pay for has a single focus that you and your ophthalmologist agree upon. There are three basic zones of vision: far (driving), intermediate (computer) and near (reading).\n\nA standard IOL gives you one of these three zones and the other two usually require eyeglasses to achieve good vision. Other factors such as pupil size and the amount of light available can impact how well these people see for the other two zones of vision. Targeting that focus is not a perfectly accurate process, but usually the result is very close to your desired single visual goal.\n\nMost patients request their IOL focus to be for distance and understand they will need glasses for computer and near vision. Some patients ask for near vision and are willing to wear glasses to see far. Some patients choose mini-monovision, such that one eye is focused for far and the other eye is focused for intermediate vision like computer distance. This requires further conversation with your ophthalmologist.\n\nMore recently we have premium/multifocal IOLs that do a good job of approaching normal vision of far, intermediate and near vision, but none of them are perfect. These premium/multifocal IOLs are usually only partially covered by insurance and the patient must pay for the difference in cost between the standard IOL and the premium/multifocal IOL.\n\nI urge you to remember that no IOL guarantees perfect vision at all vision zones and under all conditions, but they do provide good to excellent visual results for most people.", "answer_links": [{"text": "A cataract is a clouding of the focusing lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "IOL (intraocular lens)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "NOV 08, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/when-you-have-cataract-surgery-they-tell-you-that-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\when-you-have-cataract-surgery-they-tell-you-that-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "which-type-of-cataract-surgery-is-better-with-dry-", "title": "Which type of cataract surgery is better with dry eye?", "question": "I have cataracts , dry eyes , and astigmatism . I am confused as to whether laser or traditional cataract surgery is best for me with my dry eyes. Is there a significant difference between them in regard to post-operative vision and dry eye symptoms?", "answer": "Some physicians prefer laser–assisted cataract surgery , and some do not.\n\nThe data do not yet show a clear benefit of one over the other. More important here is that you identify your goals and if you want better uncorrected distance vision you may consider a toric IOL to correct astigmatism. If you would like to possibly be much freer from glasses and read without glasses, then a toric IOL that is also a multifocal or extended depth of focus toric lens may be able to accomplish this.\n\nOnce you decide on your IOL, then laser assisted or conventional surgery are both fine and you can decide with your surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 15, 2019", "categories": ["Dry Eye", "Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/which-type-of-cataract-surgery-is-better-with-dry-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\which-type-of-cataract-surgery-is-better-with-dry-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-am-i-sensitive-to-light-after-combined-catarac", "title": "Why am I sensitive to light after combined cataract-glaucoma surgery?", "question": "Any reason for the intense light sensitivity after combined cataract-glaucoma surgery with stents (small device that helps lower intraocular pressure) implanted ? It’s been two months with very little improvement.", "answer": "Light sensitivity after cataract surgery is not a rare complaint. People experience this to varying degrees because of both inflammation (swelling), and because with removal of the cataract, more light is able to enter your eye. For some, removing a cataract is like having a brown pair of sunglasses removed for the first time in many years. You should adjust some over time, but may always need sunglasses in brighter environments. Check with your ophthalmologist , but I think it is unlikely the light sensitivity has anything to do with the glaucoma stents.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "sunglasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/sunglasses-3"}, {"text": "ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/about/what-is-ophthalmology"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "SEP 05, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts", "Glaucoma"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-am-i-sensitive-to-light-after-combined-catarac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-am-i-sensitive-to-light-after-combined-catarac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-are-multifocal-iols-not-recommended-me", "title": "Why are multifocal IOLs not recommended for me?", "question": "I'm 64 and a monofocal lens is recommended due to dense cataracts and destabilizing supporting structures inside the eye. Is this a good reason not to go with multifocal or accommodative lenses? How does the multifocal lens differ from the monofocal, with respect to the supporting structures of the eye?", "answer": "must be placed in a secure\n\nand well-centered. If the “supporting structures” (presumably of the capsular bag) are inadequate, then a multifocal IOL may not be the best idea. Your surgeon may also be concerned about the lens becoming dislocated and moving in ensuing years. Small dislocations may create significantly more symptoms in a patient with a multifocal lens.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Multifocal lenses", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}, {"text": "capsular bag (or lens capsule, the thin membrane securing the eye’s natural lens that’s left intact after surgery to hold the IOL)", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/anatomy/lens-capsule-definition"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "MAR 10, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-are-multifocal-iols-not-recommended-me", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-are-multifocal-iols-not-recommended-me.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-can-t-my-cataracts-be-removed-now", "title": "Why can't my cataracts be removed now?", "question": "and want them removed, although my doctor said removal is not medically necessary. I am experiencing glare during night driving, blurry vision, and watery eyes. Why would I be required to wait for surgery?", "answer": "The decision about timing for cataract surgery is usually made based on three factors: your symptoms, your measured visual acuity (with and without glare), and the appearance of your cataract. If all three factors suggest your cataract is the primary cause for your visual difficulties, then surgery is a reasonable option to improve your vision and is generally covered by your insurance (or “medically necessary” to improve your vision). Cataracts can technically be removed when they are very early, but if the three factors to not meet certain criteria, then your insurance may not agree with the decision for surgery, and you may have to pay out-of-pocket.\n\nIn your situation, the watery eyes are not a cataract symptom, but if the glare with night driving and the blurry vision are not improved with new glasses and the surgeon can document that your eyes are otherwise normal and your vision (with or without glare testing) is less than 20/20 , then cataract surgery is typically an option.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The decision about timing for cataract surgery", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "your measured visual acuity", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/tips-prevention/visual-acuity-3"}, {"text": "vision (with or without glare testing) is less than 20/20", "url": "https://aao-my.sharepoint.com/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-does-20-20-vision-mean"}], "answered_by": "J. Kevin McKinney, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/9b1680a8-2729-45f3-9d3e-dbc4fbbbe757", "answered_at": "MAR 09, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-can-t-my-cataracts-be-removed-now", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-can-t-my-cataracts-be-removed-now.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-didn-t-my-toric-lens-fully-correct-my-astigmat", "title": "Why didn’t my toric lens fully correct my astigmatism?", "question": "I had a toric Symfony lens implanted in both eyes . In one eye I still have the same astigmatism I had before the implant. The surgeon is recommending a limbal relaxing incision surgery. I am having a lot of night aberrations. He thinks this could help. Is it possible for LRI to help the night issues and is this the best approach to correct the astigmatism? I'm confused why the toric lens did not correct the astigmatism in the first place.", "answer": "A toric lens implant is an excellent way to correct limited amounts of the most common type of astigmatism (an irregularly shaped cornea that distorts vision) in a patient who is going to have cataract surgery . The implant lens must be positioned exactly for your astigmatism. One of the problems with any toric lens is that they might shift position in the early days after surgery, reducing the desired effect. Sometimes the cataract incision changes the astigmatism from the preoperative measurements, thus changing the effect of the toric lens you are given.\n\nLRIs (limbal relaxing incisions, incisions made between the cornea and white of the eye to correct astigmatism) were used before toric implants were perfected and are another method of treating astigmatism. LRIs can be used without entering the inside of the eye, but work best for fairly small amounts of astigmatism. LRIs don't rotate like toric lenses can do.\n\nSometimes we use both torics and LRIs when the astigmatism is greater than the toric can correct.\n\nIf you want to avoid glasses or contact lenses, the solution your eye surgeon advises is your only option without going inside your eye again. When weighing the risks and benefits, it is recommended that the surgeon not go inside the eye again and instead have the LRI.\n\nIf aberrations such as halo and glare are the major issues, correction of the astigmatism may not take care of this. Some patients with multifocal or extended depth- of-focus lenses do not adapt to the optics of the lens. If this is the case, removal and replacement of the lens with a traditional monofocal lens may be the best solution. If the amount of your residual astigmatism is low, this may be the best solution for you. Please discuss with your surgeon. This question was originally answered on October 3, 2017.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism (an irregularly shaped cornea that distorts vision)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "If aberrations such as halo", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/halos-around-lights"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAY 06, 2022", "categories": ["Surgery", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-didn-t-my-toric-lens-fully-correct-my-astigmat", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-didn-t-my-toric-lens-fully-correct-my-astigmat.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-do-binoculars-eliminate-my-iol-halos", "title": "Why do binoculars eliminate my IOL halos?", "question": "I have minor halos from multifocal IOLs. My vision is awesome at all distances except for the halos. However, I noticed that when looking through binoculars, the halos vanish. What is it about the binoculars that causes this and are there glasses I could buy to get the same effect?", "answer": "The halos are related to the intraocular lens (IOL) design, which has circular rings of correction. The binoculars cut off the external (non-parallel) rays of light from entering the eye. This decreases the amount of light hitting the peripheral rings of correction in the IOL.\n\nThere is really no way to do this with any glasses, but you may ask your surgeon to prescribe some drops that you can use to make the pupil smaller. This may decrease but not eliminate the halos.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 04, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-do-binoculars-eliminate-my-iol-halos", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-do-binoculars-eliminate-my-iol-halos.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-do-i-have-balance-dizziness-problems-after-cat", "title": "Why do I have balance/dizziness problems after cataract surgery?", "question": "Why do I have balance/dizziness problems after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Depending on the type of anesthesia (painkiller) used during the operation, one can experience balance problems and dizziness after surgery, but this typically would only last a few hours.\n\nPersistent dizziness can be related to the new artificial lens that was implanted after removal of your eye's cloudy natural lens . The new artificial lens (IOL) may have a different refractive power from your previous lens and may be creating an imbalance to which you are unaccustomed. It also could be that the dizziness is completely unrelated to your surgery. You should report these symptoms to your surgeon who can investigate further.\n\nThis question was originally answered on Aug. 3, 2016.", "answer_links": [{"text": "artificial lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "natural lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "AUG 03, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-do-i-have-balance-dizziness-problems-after-cat", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-do-i-have-balance-dizziness-problems-after-cat.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-do-i-have-to-have-lasik-done-after-i-have-had-", "title": "Why do I have to have LASIK done after I have had YAG surgery?", "question": "Why do I have to have LASIK done after I have had YAG surgery ? I had a lens for distance implanted during cataract surgery . After the YAG, my vision is still blurry, and I cannot focus. Now they want to do LASIK. Is this normal?", "answer": "Yes, if the target was not hit with your lens implant to begin with, it is typical to perform the YAG to see if it changes the vision. If not, then LASIK is an excellent way to fine tune the final result .", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK is an excellent way to fine tune the final result", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JAN 25, 2019", "categories": ["LASIK and Laser Surgery", "Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-do-i-have-to-have-lasik-done-after-i-have-had-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-do-i-have-to-have-lasik-done-after-i-have-had-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-do-i-see-distinctive-black-c-in-my-vision-afte", "title": "Why do I see a distinctive black “C” in my vision after having a toric lens implanted?", "question": "I had a toric intraocular lens implanted which corrected my astigmatism and cataract in my left eye. My vision is terrific but it looks like I'm wearing a contact lens that has a distinctive black “C” on it. It does not affect my vision, but it does not seem \"normal.\" It almost seems like someone took a black sharpie marker and drew on the left edge of the lens. Do I need a replacement?", "answer": "What you are describing is known as a negative dysphotopsia—an unusual reflection image. Replacement does not always fix the problem, but time usually makes it go away. Another option can be the insertion of what is called a piggyback lens which can negate the image. Talk to your surgeon about the options.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUL 22, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-do-i-see-distinctive-black-c-in-my-vision-afte", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-do-i-see-distinctive-black-c-in-my-vision-afte.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-do-i-see-halos-with-my-multifocal-lens", "title": "Why do I see halos with my multifocal lens?", "question": "I just had a Panoptics lens put in a week and a half ago and I notice that I have a small crescent moon to the right. Letters have a slight glow or fuzz to them, and I have pretty severe halo effect at night and the street signs have a glow around them. Should I give it some time to change and how long? Or should I start planning on removing it and have a plain lens put in?", "answer": "With the Panoptix lens or any multifocal lens , it is normal to have some glow as well as halos for the first six weeks or so. They generally tend to get better but do not completely go away. The small crescent moon may be what we call a negative dysphotopsia. This can happen with many IOLs and also should get better with time. Of course, if the visual symptoms do not improve over time, you will need to discuss alternatives including removal and replacement of the lens although this is rarely necessary.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Panoptix lens or any multifocal lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 11, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-do-i-see-halos-with-my-multifocal-lens", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-do-i-see-halos-with-my-multifocal-lens.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-has-my-near-vision-gotten-worse-since-my-catar", "title": "Why has my near vision gotten worse since my cataract surgery two weeks ago?", "question": "My near vision has gotten worse since my cataract surgery from two weeks ago and it feels totally different than my other eye. What is the problem?", "answer": "If you had a monofocal lens implanted (single focus lens), your area of best focus will be determined by the power chosen for this eye. If you have concerns, ask your operating surgeons what options you have in the future for better near vision if that is what you desire.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 26, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-has-my-near-vision-gotten-worse-since-my-catar", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-has-my-near-vision-gotten-worse-since-my-catar.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-have-i-experienced-leaky-eyes-since-having-my-", "title": "Why have I experienced leaky eyes since having my cataracts removed?", "question": "Why have I experienced leaky eyes since having my cataracts removed? This has caused a dryness to eyelids as well as swelling and redness around my eyes.", "answer": "This is not typically associated with cataract surgery . I would check with your ophthalmologist to see if there is a blocked tear drainage duct that is causing the issue. This can be fixed if it is the problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "blocked tear drainage duct", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blocked-tear-duct"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "SEP 22, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-have-i-experienced-leaky-eyes-since-having-my-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-have-i-experienced-leaky-eyes-since-having-my-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-multifocal-lens-implant-not-possible-after-", "title": "Why is a multifocal lens implant not possible after vitrectomy/scleral buckle surgery?", "question": "Why is a multifocal lens implant not possible after vitrectomy and scleral buckle surgery (surgery that helps reattach the retina, or light sensitive tissue, to the back of the eye)? I will be having a cataract removed (surgery to replace eye’s cloudy natural lens with clear artificial lens) eventually and might prefer this to monovision .", "answer": "This can depend on a number of things. If the macula (center of the retina) was damaged by the retinal detachment or hole , multifocal lenses are not recommended as they can actually make vision worse since they decrease the amount of incoming light. Also, if there was damage to the posterior capsule of the lens during the vitrectomy , there would not be a support structure to hold this type of lens in place. It is best to ask your surgeon what he recommends and why.", "answer_links": [{"text": "macula (center of the retina)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/macula-6"}, {"text": "retinal detachment", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/detached-torn-retina"}, {"text": "hole", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-macular-hole"}, {"text": "vitrectomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-vitrectomy"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 22, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-multifocal-lens-implant-not-possible-after-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-multifocal-lens-implant-not-possible-after-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-my-eye-tearing-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why is my eye tearing after cataract surgery?", "question": "I had cataract surgery a year ago and one of my eyes has been watering continuously almost every day for the last six months. I wake up with that eye extremely crusted at times and a thick film over it that I cannot see through until I am up and blinking it for a few minutes, then it starts watering again. Can you give me an idea of what to do?", "answer": "This may be due to a blockage in the tear drainage duct in the eyelid . I would see your eye surgeon to evaluate this. There is surgery to correct this, which is usually performed by an oculoplastic surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "blockage in the tear drainage duct in the eyelid", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blocked-tear-duct"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "MAY 21, 2021", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-my-eye-tearing-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-my-eye-tearing-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-my-vision-not-sharp-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why is my vision not sharp after cataract surgery?", "question": "It’s been three years since my cataract surgery and I have multifocal lenses. I have readers and distance vision is not sharp. What can I do for blurriness in the intermediate range (like the automobile dashboard)?", "answer": "Results like this are not common but do happen with all types of IOLs after cataract surgery . A comprehensive ophthalmic exam specifically looking for dry eyes , other problems with the cornea at the front of the eye, clouding behind the IOLs (known as posterior capsule opacification ), or problems with the retina in the back of the eye is recommended. If anything is found that can be treated, such as dry eyes, the treatment should be maximized.\n\nNext, the refractive error should be tested and then corrected with the proper spectacles (perhaps a low addition progressive), or even laser vision correction . If there is no eye disease and your distance vision is not acceptable even with glasses, then, in very rare cases, multifocal implants can be exchanged for monofocals, as long as the patient realizes they will not be independent of glasses.", "answer_links": [{"text": "all types of IOLs", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "A comprehensive ophthalmic exam", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "dry eyes", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}, {"text": "the cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}, {"text": "posterior capsule opacification", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "the retina in the back of the eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "refractive error should be tested and then corrected with the proper spectacles", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts-list"}, {"text": "laser vision correction", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "FEB 27, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-my-vision-not-sharp-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-my-vision-not-sharp-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-my-vision-still-blurry-after-having-catarac", "title": "Why is my vision still blurry after having cataract surgery a year ago?", "question": "Why is my vision still blurry after having cataract surgery a year ago?", "answer": "Persistent blurry vision after cataract surgery can be due to many different things. Some causes may relate to the surgery and others, such as macular degeneration among others, are unrelated to the surgery. See your ophthalmologist for a comprehensive exam to find the cause and the appropriate treatment.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "macular degeneration", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amd-macular-degeneration"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 12, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-my-vision-still-blurry-after-having-catarac", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-my-vision-still-blurry-after-having-catarac.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-reading-more-difficult-several-years-after-", "title": "Why is reading more difficult several years after my cataract surgery?", "question": "Several years ago, I had cataract surgery and lens replacement . What can I do now that reading has become more of a problem? I had the trifocal lens installed.", "answer": "If this was several years ago, I would have your surgeon look at your measurements again, do a dilated examination and see if the capsule holding the lens implant in place has clouded (may need a laser treatment). This is normal for many people after cataract surgery. The capsule is treated with a laser (called a posterior capsulotomy) that helps restore clear vision.", "answer_links": [{"text": "dilated examination", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/eye-exams-101"}, {"text": "The capsule is treated with a laser (called a posterior capsulotomy)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 05, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-reading-more-difficult-several-years-after-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-reading-more-difficult-several-years-after-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-saline-used-during-cataract-surgery", "title": "Why is saline used during cataract surgery?", "question": "Why is saline used during cataract surgery?", "answer": "It’s not exactly saline but it is called balanced salt solution. There needs to be a fluid inflow during cataract surgery to keep the eye pressurized . A saline type solution is more compatible with the existing fluid in the eye called aqueous humor .\n\nIf one were to use sterile water with no salt then it could chemically damage the cornea . It can also permanently damage the very sensitive endothelial cells of the cornea that are required to pump water out of the cornea to maintain its clarity.", "answer_links": [{"text": "There needs to be a fluid inflow during cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "eye pressurized", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/eye-pressure"}, {"text": "aqueous humor", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/aqueous-humor"}, {"text": "the cornea", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "JAN 24, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-saline-used-during-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-saline-used-during-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-there-clear-mucosal-film-over-portion-of-my", "title": "Why is there a clear mucosal film over a portion of my eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "I'm 70 years old and just recently had cataract surgery in both eyes. One eye is fine but the other has what I would call a clear mucosal film over a portion of my eye. I can wipe it away with my finger but after a few minutes it comes back. I did not have this problem prior to the surgery. Could you please tell me what is going on?", "answer": "There is no way to tell without an exam. This could be a conjunctivitis or a blocked tear duct or something completely different. It is not a symptom of a complication of cataract surgery. Please have your surgeon re-examine your eye.", "answer_links": [{"text": "conjunctivitis", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/pink-eye-conjunctivitis"}, {"text": "blocked tear duct", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blocked-tear-duct"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "JUN 14, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-there-clear-mucosal-film-over-portion-of-my", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-there-clear-mucosal-film-over-portion-of-my.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-is-there-such-great-difference-in-cost-to-pati", "title": "Why is there such a great difference in cost to patient between putting in regular lens for cataracts versus toric for astigmatism?", "question": "Why is there such a great difference in cost to patient between putting in regular lens for cataracts versus toric for astigmatism ? It seems to be same operation.", "answer": "The issue is that the lens itself is more expensive by many times and is not reimbursed by insurance. Plus, more pre-operative measurements and calculations are needed and the follow-up after surgery can be more involved. Even the surgery itself can be different: The capsulotomy (or opening the anterior lens capsule) is lens specific. The eye has to be specifically marked for the axis correction of the toric lens, and sometimes an aberrometer (a special device that measures the way light travels through your eye) is used to make sure the lens is correctly placed.\n\nThough the operation is very similar, there are some important differences that do add cost to the procedure.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 08, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-is-there-such-great-difference-in-cost-to-pati", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-is-there-such-great-difference-in-cost-to-pati.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-would-doctor-place-contact-lens-on-patient-s-e", "title": "Why would a doctor place a contact lens on a patient’s eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "Why would a doctor place a contact lens on a patient’s eye after cataract surgery?", "answer": "There are several reasons an ophthalmologist might put a contact lens on a patient after cataract surgery . A person might have sustained drying of the surface of the eye (the cornea) during the operation and a \"bandage\" soft contact lens could make the eye more comfortable while the results of the drying heal. Some ophthalmologists place a bandage contact lens on an eye after cataract surgery, like we use a band-aid normally, to protect the small incision where the cataract surgery took place. Another reason is that a bandage contact lens can help antibiotic eye drops used after surgery remain in the eye longer and not be washed out as rapidly by tears.", "answer_links": [{"text": "ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-is-ophthalmologist"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "surface of the eye (the cornea)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/cornea-103"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "MAY 02, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-would-doctor-place-contact-lens-on-patient-s-e", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-would-doctor-place-contact-lens-on-patient-s-e.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "why-would-someone-with-iol-need-lasik-on-same-eye-", "title": "Why would someone with an IOL need LASIK on the same eye four weeks later?", "question": "Why would someone with an IOL (artificial intraocular lens placed in eye after cataract removal surgery) need LASIK on the same eye four weeks later?", "answer": "No one has to have LASIK after cataract surgery , but if not all of your myopia (nearsightedness) , hyperopia (farsightedness) or astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea) could be corrected with the IOL, LASIK can be used to fine tune the visual result.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}, {"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "myopia (nearsightedness)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "hyperopia (farsightedness)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/hyperopia-farsightedness"}, {"text": "astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 24, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/why-would-someone-with-iol-need-lasik-on-same-eye-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\why-would-someone-with-iol-need-lasik-on-same-eye-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-cataract-surgery-affect-development-of-dry-am", "title": "Will cataract surgery affect development of dry AMD in that eye?", "question": "Will cataract surgery to my right eye, which is in the beginning stage of dry AMD, have any effect on the further development of my dry AMD in that eye?", "answer": "This is an important question that has been asked by many. There’s no evidence that the surgery should affect your AMD, but it’s important for your retinal specialist to be sure that you have no signs of occult neovascularization (abnormal blood vessels that grown inside the eye when one has wet AMD) prior to surgery.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "C P Wilkinson MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/fc0199ce-ff28-49b0-8df5-ef8d8783f119", "answered_at": "SEP 10, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Diseases", "Macular Degeneration"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-cataract-surgery-affect-development-of-dry-am", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-cataract-surgery-affect-development-of-dry-am.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-cataract-surgery-help-with-my-watering-eyes", "title": "Will cataract surgery help with my watering eyes?", "question": "I have a weeping left eye and normally watery eyes. I’ve just been diagnosed with cataracts and require surgery. Will this help with the watering eyes?", "answer": "Watery eye (or tearing) sounds like such a simple problem, but actually there are many causes of this condition. This can be due to excessive tear production or poor tear drainage .\n\nGlare from cataracts can cause excessive tear production under certain lighting conditions but would not be expected in dimmer light. I am also concerned that you report cataracts in both eyes but only report excessive tearing in your left eye. It is possible that you have a tear drainage problem on the left. I would suggest that you speak with your ophthalmologist and ask him/her about your left eye tearing problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Watery eye (or tearing)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/tearing"}, {"text": "poor tear drainage", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-blocked-tear-duct"}, {"text": "Glare from cataracts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "ophthalmologist", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/tips-prevention/what-is-ophthalmologist"}], "answered_by": "Omar R Chaudhary, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/8e0e0d43-5cc4-4c54-be05-971ce84e7afa", "answered_at": "MAY 24, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-cataract-surgery-help-with-my-watering-eyes", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-cataract-surgery-help-with-my-watering-eyes.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-cataract-surgery-repair-my-worsening-nearsigh", "title": "Will cataract surgery repair my worsening nearsightedness?", "question": "I had a macular hole repaired . In the year since, I have become more nearsighted in that eye (from 3 to 9). Will the cataract surgery I will need repair this and stop it from getting worse?", "answer": "After macular hole surgery, cataract formation and worsening of cataract are common. As the cataract forms, it generally induces more nearsightedness and that can be corrected with cataract surgery.", "answer_links": [{"text": "nearsightedness", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}], "answered_by": "Abdhish R Bhavsar, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/58472acf-5519-403d-a07d-cd531a738f6d", "answered_at": "SEP 24, 2020", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-cataract-surgery-repair-my-worsening-nearsigh", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-cataract-surgery-repair-my-worsening-nearsigh.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-cataracts-complicate-my-glaucoma-visual-field", "title": "Will cataracts complicate my glaucoma visual field test?", "question": "Will a visual field test to check on my glaucoma be useful since I also have cataracts which affect my vision?", "answer": "It should be useful. Part of the software in the testing machine helps minimize the effects of the cataract.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "JUL 28, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Glaucoma"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-cataracts-complicate-my-glaucoma-visual-field", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-cataracts-complicate-my-glaucoma-visual-field.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-dmso-arthritis-harm-my-iol", "title": "Will DMSO for arthritis harm my IOL?", "question": "I use DMSO for arthritis and I need cataract surgery. Will DMSO harm the implant?", "answer": "DMSO, a cream that is applied to the skin, helps treat arthritis and is also used to help the body absorb other medications. It will have little effect on the eye once it enters your body and no effect on cataract removal surgery or your intraocular lens (the implant) . If DMSO helps your arthritis, carry on.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract removal surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "intraocular lens (the implant)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}], "answered_by": "Richard E Bensinger MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/6ba9cec3-5d75-463d-a97b-f0d9c0d6a8a1", "answered_at": "SEP 12, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-dmso-arthritis-harm-my-iol", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-dmso-arthritis-harm-my-iol.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-dull-colors-brighten-after-my-second-cataract", "title": "Will dull colors brighten after my second cataract surgery?", "question": "I had a cataract removed 3 months ago and noticed the yellow/brown tint I had been seeing disappeared and whites became bright! But after having my second eye done 3 days ago, and I’m seeing the dull yellow/brown colors again. Will this resolve or is something wrong?", "answer": "This may be temporary if your retina (light sensitive tissue in the back of the eye) is normal and without disease. If it continues, please have your surgeon re-evaluate.", "answer_links": [{"text": "retina (light sensitive tissue in the back of the eye)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 05, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-dull-colors-brighten-after-my-second-cataract", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-dull-colors-brighten-after-my-second-cataract.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-i-become-blind-from-delayed-cataract-surgery", "title": "Will I become blind from delayed cataract surgery?", "question": "I am 62-year-old with diabetes and was diagnosed with cataract on one eye which worsened with time. My doctor scheduled surgery for this month, but it’s postponed indefinitely. My vision in the affected eye is totally blurred. Will I eventually become blind without surgery ?", "answer": "Without treatment, the vision will become worse in the affected eye. But the cataract can still be removed in the near future when elective surgery becomes more widely available. Despite its delay, cataract surgery will correct the vision impaired by the cataract. Hang in there, help for your vision is coming.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 18, 2020", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-i-become-blind-from-delayed-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-i-become-blind-from-delayed-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-i-need-new-eye-examination-new-lenses-after-c", "title": "Will I need a new eye examination and new lenses after cataract surgery?", "question": "Will I need a new eye examination and new lenses after cataract surgery ?", "answer": "Yes. All measurements will usually change after your surgery and new glasses will be prescribed.", "answer_links": [], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 05, 2016", "categories": ["Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-i-need-new-eye-examination-new-lenses-after-c", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-i-need-new-eye-examination-new-lenses-after-c.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-lasik-help-my-vision-after-cataract-surgery", "title": "Will LASIK help my vision after cataract surgery?", "question": "within the last year. Is it possible to have LASIK surgery now to reduce my dependence on glasses? I have astigmatism in both eyes.", "answer": "Depending on the type and amount of correction and the health of your corneas, LASIK is certainly a possibility . Schedule a discussion with your surgeon who can identify the best strategy to meet your visual goals given your eye health.", "answer_links": [{"text": "LASIK is certainly a possibility", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/lasik"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 05, 2022", "categories": ["LASIK and Laser Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-lasik-help-my-vision-after-cataract-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-lasik-help-my-vision-after-cataract-surgery.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-monofocal-iol-improve-myopia-as-well-as-toric", "title": "Will a monofocal IOL improve myopia as well as a toric IOL?", "question": "Will a monofocal IOL improve myopia as well as a toric IOL?", "answer": "Both a monofocal IOL and a toric IOL can correct myopia (nearsightedness) . However, if you have astigmatism, your vision without glasses will be better with a toric IOL than with a monofocal IOL. The toric lens can correct both myopia and astigmatism while the monofocal lens can only address the myopia.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Both a monofocal IOL and a toric IOL", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "myopia (nearsightedness)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/myopia-nearsightedness"}, {"text": "astigmatism,", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "NOV 15, 2019", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-monofocal-iol-improve-myopia-as-well-as-toric", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-monofocal-iol-improve-myopia-as-well-as-toric.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-my-astigmatism-be-different-after-having-cata", "title": "Will my astigmatism be different after having cataract surgery?", "question": "I need cataract surgery . I've been told that I have astigmatism (irregularly shaped cornea) in both the back of my eyes and front of my eyes but that these offset each other which explains why my glasses only have a relatively small astigmatism adjustment of 0.25. Should I anticipate that my astigmatism will be different after IOL implants ?", "answer": "You may need a toric lens to correct your astigmatism , since the internal astigmatism created by the lens of your eye (the cataract ) will be removed. Please discuss this with your surgeon to see what your options are.", "answer_links": [{"text": "astigmatism", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-astigmatism"}, {"text": "lens of your eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/lens-9"}, {"text": "cataract", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "OCT 12, 2017", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-my-astigmatism-be-different-after-having-cata", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-my-astigmatism-be-different-after-having-cata.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-my-aunt-s-surgery-be-successful-if-she-refuse", "title": "Will my aunt’s surgery be successful if she refuses eye drops afterwards?", "question": "My disabled aunty had cataract surgery but is refusing to let anyone put in the eye drops. Will the operation still be successful without her using them?", "answer": "Of course, it is best that all drops are used to prevent infection and inflammation . If she is not using the drops I suggest you call her doctor ASAP and see what else can be done. If you can teach her to put her own drops in, maybe she would accept that?", "answer_links": [{"text": "inflammation", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/inflammation"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "NOV 09, 2020", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-my-aunt-s-surgery-be-successful-if-she-refuse", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-my-aunt-s-surgery-be-successful-if-she-refuse.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-my-iol-correct-my-lazy-eye-after-cataract-sur", "title": "Will my IOL correct my lazy eye after cataract surgery?", "question": "My eyeglass prescription straightens my lazy eye. If I get cataract surgery, will it also correct my lazy eye?", "answer": "The short answer is that if someone were to have cataract surgery , and the refractive correction they were using in their glasses is now transferred to an intraocular lens , most but not all of the time the strabismus (misaligned or “crossed” eyes) control will be about the same. There are some patients whose strabismus control worsens, and this is something to discuss with your surgeon before cataract surgery.\n\nIf the question pertains to prism correction (special glasses that are used to correct double vision) , the prism cannot be transferred into the intraocular lens. So, prism glasses will be needed after cataract surgery.\n\nOne thing to consider when discussing glasses use after cataract surgery with \"lazy eye,\" is what type of lazy eye you have. If it is strabismus, then sometimes glasses will not be needed, and the strabismus control will remain the same. This is not always the case but most of the time does hold true. If by lazy eye you mean “amblyopia” , then cataract surgery may partially but not completely improve the vision. Depending on the severity of the amblyopia, cataract surgery may not improve the vision at all. For patients with moderate to severe amblyopia, they should always plan on wearing glasses after cataract surgery as the glasses protect their healthy \"good\" eye from injury. They will always need eye protection.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}, {"text": "glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts-list"}, {"text": "intraocular lens", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "strabismus (misaligned or “crossed” eyes)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-strabismus"}, {"text": "prism correction (special glasses that are used to correct double vision)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/what-is-prism-correction-in-eyeglasses"}, {"text": "lazy eye you mean “amblyopia”", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amblyopia-lazy-eye"}], "answered_by": "Aaron M Miller, MD, MBA", "answered_by_url": "/biography/1d353ee7-10f5-4298-a733-ea4d82f1bfc8", "answered_at": "APR 09, 2019", "categories": ["Amblyopia, Strabismus and Lazy Eye", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-my-iol-correct-my-lazy-eye-after-cataract-sur", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-my-iol-correct-my-lazy-eye-after-cataract-sur.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-my-iols-work-in-tandem-with-my-contact-lenses", "title": "Will my IOLs work in tandem with my contact lenses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I am 29 and I have cataracts . I work with computers, so I’ve decided to get an under-corrected monofocal intraocular lens for near vision. Currently, I wear contacts to see far. I also wear these contacts while I work on my computer. After cataract surgery, will I still be able to wear contacts to see far and see my computer at the same time? In other words, will my IOLs work in tandem with my contacts lenses or would I need them taken off to see my computer?", "answer": "These are common choices that all cataract patients need to make. You may want to consider an extended depth-of-focus lens. This will give you a continuous focus from close, intermediate (computer), and far away—perhaps requiring reading glasses for very fine print or in dim lighting. If you go with under-correction, you will need bifocals to see both near and distance at the same time. Contacts can be worn, but unless you wear multifocal contacts, which do not work for everyone, you can either see far or near, not both. Another option is monovision—one eye for distance and one eye for near or intermediate, but not all people adapt to this choice. You should discuss these options in detail with your cataract surgeon.", "answer_links": [{"text": "reading glasses", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/tips-choosing-right-reading-glasses"}, {"text": "Contacts", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/glasses-contacts/contact-lens-102"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "DEC 28, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery", "Glasses, Contacts and Vision Correction"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-my-iols-work-in-tandem-with-my-contact-lenses", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-my-iols-work-in-tandem-with-my-contact-lenses.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-my-near-vision-be-better-worse-without-glasse", "title": "Will my near vision be better or worse without glasses after cataract surgery?", "question": "I'm farsighted and wear tri-focal glasses. I'm having a cataract removed and replaced with a lens where I won't need glasses for distance. Will my near vision be better or worse without glasses?", "answer": "I need to see your eyeglasses prescription before any surgery to be able to answer accurately. In most cases, farsighted people will be less farsighted after cataract surgery with a lens implant and most of the time that will make the required glasses for reading and for computer less strong. That would consequently mean that your unaided reading and computer distance vision would be somewhat improved, but not perfect by any means. I suggest you discuss this with your ophthalmologist.", "answer_links": [{"text": "cataract surgery", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-cataract-surgery"}], "answered_by": "Wayne F Bizer DO", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d78e2474-1891-4ca7-b914-e9491fcbacac", "answered_at": "DEC 20, 2016", "categories": ["Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-my-near-vision-be-better-worse-without-glasse", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-my-near-vision-be-better-worse-without-glasse.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-new-iol-help-my-vision-after-having-cataract-", "title": "Will a new IOL help my vision after having a cataract removed at age 3?", "question": "Have cataract surgery techniques improved sufficiently in the past 20 years to consider having a new intraocular lens (IOL) placed to improve eyesight, and is this even possible? I was diagnosed with and operated for a congenital cataract 20 years ago at age 3. A monofocal IOL was placed, and I now see 60 percent from my left eye. Though I am very glad to see anything from that eye at all, I lack depth perception, I can’t read with the affected eye, and regularly worry about the consequences if something were to happen to my other eye. As such, I was wondering whether any significant improvement can be made in terms of eyesight through a repeat surgery.", "answer": "Significant improvements have been made in IOLs, but nothing that is likely to help your problem. If your childhood cataract led to a loss of vision from amblyopia (when vision is one or both eyes don’t develop normally during childhood) , an intraocular lens would be unable to improve this deficit. Check with your local ophthalmologist to be sure.", "answer_links": [{"text": "amblyopia (when vision is one or both eyes don’t develop normally during childhood)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amblyopia-lazy-eye"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "FEB 04, 2018", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Pediatric Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-new-iol-help-my-vision-after-having-cataract-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-new-iol-help-my-vision-after-having-cataract-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-rubbing-eyes-dislodge-IOL", "title": "Is there any risk that rubbing my eyes will dislodge the IOL?", "question": "After cataract surgery , is there any risk to dislodging the IOLs from rubbing my eyes in the morning due to excessive tearing?", "answer": "While eye rubbing is generally discouraged right after cataract surgery, doing so will not cause an intraocular lens (IOL) to move out of position after an uncomplicated cataract surgery once the eye is well-healed.\n\nThere are no hard rules here so I would recommend asking your ophthalmologist what their preference is regarding this.", "answer_links": [{"text": "intraocular lens (IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-iol-implants"}], "answered_by": "Kurt Kelley MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/b716c9e9-1ee5-44c3-b92f-d0f649b9a7bc", "answered_at": "AUG 10, 2023", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-rubbing-eyes-dislodge-IOL", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-rubbing-eyes-dislodge-IOL.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-secondary-cataract-surgery-worsen-my-amd", "title": "Will secondary cataract surgery worsen my AMD?", "question": "Will a laser procedure on a secondary cataract possibly worsen macular degeneration?", "answer": "There is little evidence to suggest that correcting a secondary cataract with laser ( posterior capsulotomy ) can make your AMD (age-related macular degeneration) worse. Your visual improvement from the laser could be limited by the AMD, but the laser is not likely to worsen the AMD.", "answer_links": [{"text": "posterior capsulotomy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "AMD (age-related macular degeneration)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/amd-macular-degeneration"}], "answered_by": "James M Heltzer, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/d1ff08d6-1394-42e8-9bc0-9b3cff983031", "answered_at": "JUL 27, 2019", "categories": ["Macular Degeneration", "Surgery", "Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-secondary-cataract-surgery-worsen-my-amd", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-secondary-cataract-surgery-worsen-my-amd.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "will-sodium-chloride-solution-resolve-corneal-edem", "title": "Will sodium chloride solution resolve corneal edema after cataract surgery?", "question": "Is applying sodium chloride solution only a temporary relief for cornea edema after cataract surgery or will it permanently resolve this problem?", "answer": "Sodium chloride drops and/or ointment help remove fluid from the cornea that causes the “edema” or swelling. Topical steroids are also helpful. Corneal edema after cataract surgery usually resolves completely with time and use of the medications. Rarely, removing a very large cataract with preexisting corneal diseases such as Fuchs’ dystrophy can prevent the edema from resolving. In these cases, a procedure known as endothelial keratoplasty can be performed to cure the corneal edema.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Fuchs’ dystrophy", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-fuchs-dystrophy"}], "answered_by": "Omar R Chaudhary, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/8e0e0d43-5cc4-4c54-be05-971ce84e7afa", "answered_at": "SEP 22, 2019", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/will-sodium-chloride-solution-resolve-corneal-edem", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\will-sodium-chloride-solution-resolve-corneal-edem.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "with-my-vision-changing-rapidly-how-will-i-choose-", "title": "With my vision changing so rapidly, how will I choose an intraocular lens after cataract surgery two years from now?", "question": "I'm 46. My eyes are changing so rapidly that I'm buying new glasses every year (not small tweaks). Right now I'm 20/400 walking around in 20/300 lenses from last February. I have cataracts and will have surgery in a couple of years. With my eyes not being stable, how do I choose an IOL ?", "answer": "Once you are 20 or over, the changes that occur in your glasses are mostly likely due to changes in the lens of your eye —the very thing that has reduced your vision with cataract at this time. These changes have no bearing on the IOL choice since once the lens is removed (the cataract is the lens), the changing part of your problem will be gone. The IOL choice will be based on other things unique to your eyes and you should ask your ophthalmologist what lenses you can consider.", "answer_links": [{"text": "lens of your eye", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/cataracts-causes"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "APR 28, 2016", "categories": ["Cataracts", "Surgery"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/with-my-vision-changing-rapidly-how-will-i-choose-", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\with-my-vision-changing-rapidly-how-will-i-choose-.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "would-cataract-surgeon-be-able-to-identify-rotated", "title": "Would a cataract surgeon be able to identify a rotated IOL during an examination?", "question": "Would a cataract surgeon be able to identify a rotated IOL during an examination?", "answer": "Assuming you are talking about a toric lens (astigmatism-correcting IOL) being possibly rotated, the answer is yes. As long as the pupil is dilated wide enough to get a good look , this should not be a problem.", "answer_links": [{"text": "toric lens (astigmatism-correcting IOL)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/iols-intraocular-lens"}, {"text": "pupil", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/pupil"}, {"text": "dilated wide enough to get a good look", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/drugs/dilating-eyedrops"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "DEC 11, 2017", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/would-cataract-surgeon-be-able-to-identify-rotated", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\would-cataract-surgeon-be-able-to-identify-rotated.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "would-cataracts-cause-me-to-see-completely-differe", "title": "Would cataracts cause me to see completely different colors?", "question": "I have cataracts, which affect my vision, however I now see completely different colors versus subtly different hues of the same color I had seen previously. These stark differences come and go, but generally happen when I first wake up. Can I chalk this up to cataracts and old age creeping in?", "answer": "Cataracts can cause changes in color perception as they progress . The variability may be due to pupil size, lighting or dry eyes . Most likely these symptoms are due to progression of your cataracts. However, please consult with your ophthalmologist to confirm this because retina and optic nerve problems in the back of the eye can also cause these changes.", "answer_links": [{"text": "Cataracts can cause changes in color perception as they progress", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-are-cataracts"}, {"text": "dry eyes", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/diseases/what-is-dry-eye"}, {"text": "retina", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/retina-103"}, {"text": "optic nerve problems", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/anatomy/optic-nerve-3"}], "answered_by": "Gary S Hirshfield, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/c01afde3-578d-42ff-a5dd-e8b3aacbdba2", "answered_at": "SEP 06, 2022", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/would-cataracts-cause-me-to-see-completely-differe", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\would-cataracts-cause-me-to-see-completely-differe.html"}
{"record_type": "qa", "slug": "yag-starburst-lights-cataract-laser-surgery", "title": "Can YAG cause starbursts around lights?", "question": "Can YAG treatment cause you to see huge starbursts around lights at night? I have a light-adjustable lens (LAL).", "answer": "The YAG treatment (or posterior capsulotomy) should not have anything to do with seeing starbursts around lights at night . The light-adjustable lens should not cause much in the way of halo or starburst, either. Check with your surgeon so they can investigate what might be responsible for this symptom.", "answer_links": [{"text": "The YAG treatment (or posterior capsulotomy)", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/treatments/what-is-posterior-capsulotomy"}, {"text": "starbursts around lights at night", "url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/symptoms/starbursts-around-lights"}], "answered_by": "Jeffrey Whitman, MD", "answered_by_url": "/biography/283b28a7-7743-4a13-bb0f-4be928da5bd3", "answered_at": "AUG 15, 2024", "categories": ["Cataracts"], "source_url": "https://www.aao.org/eye-health/ask-ophthalmologist-q/yag-starburst-lights-cataract-laser-surgery", "language": "en", "html_path": "data\\raw\\html\\qa\\yag-starburst-lights-cataract-laser-surgery.html"}
